<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The agreement of the Unitarians with the Catholick Church being also a full answer to the infamations of Mr. Edwards and the needless exceptions of my Lords the Bishops of Chichester, Worcester and Sarum, and of Monsieur De Luzancy.</title>
            <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11240492</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11240492</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47056</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52604)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47056)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1447:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The agreement of the Unitarians with the Catholick Church being also a full answer to the infamations of Mr. Edwards and the needless exceptions of my Lords the Bishops of Chichester, Worcester and Sarum, and of Monsieur De Luzancy.</title>
                  <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVII [1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Stephen Nye is generally credited with having had a hand in writing this book."--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>"Part 1" appears on t.p. ; part 2 begins on p. 32.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Unitarianism --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47056:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE AGREEMENT OF THE Unitarians, WITH THE <hi>Catholick Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING ALSO A full Anſwer, to the Infamations of Mr. <hi>Edwards;</hi> and the needleſs Exceptions, of my Lords the Biſhops of <hi>Chicheſter, Worceſter,</hi> and <hi>Sarum,</hi> and of Monſieur <hi>De Luzancy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PART I. In Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> and my Lord the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <div type="discourse">
               <pb facs="tcp:47056:2"/>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47056:2"/>
               <head>In Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Edwards.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Edwards</hi> after having written ſome trifling Books, ſome indifferent ones, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers good ones; and one excellent Book, his <hi>Demonſtration of the Exiſtence and Providence of God;</hi> found an Inclination in himſelf, that he could not reſiſt, of contriving a New Religion, or rather Impiety; and of imputing it to the Socinians. By whom he means (it appears) the Unitarians.</p>
               <p>Thoſe in <hi>England,</hi> who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Unitarians, never were in the Sentiments of <hi>Socinus,</hi> or the Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Notwithſtanding, as our Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers have pleaſed themſelves in calling us Socinians, we have not always de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined the Name: becauſe in inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting many Texts of Scripture, we cannot but approve and follow the Judgment of thoſe Writers, who are confeſſed by all, to be excellent Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and very judicious. As particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly (and chiefly) <hi>H. Grotius;</hi> who, it muſt be granted, was Socinian all over: and <hi>D. Eraſmus,</hi> who, tho he lived conſiderably before <hi>Socinus,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly interprets that way; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is charged by Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> as a downright Arian. <hi>Non poterat,</hi> ſays the Cardinal, <hi>Arianam cauſam manifeſtius propugnare.</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Eraſmus</hi> could not more openly eſpouſe the Arian ſide, than he has done, in his Notes on the Fathers, and the principal Texts of Scripture.</q> 
                  <hi>Pref. ad Libros</hi> 5. <hi>de Chriſto.</hi> But tho, as I ſaid, we are not Socinians, nor yet Arians; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> has contrived a Creed for us, under the Name of Socinians: I will anſwer both directly and ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, concerning the ſeveral Articles of the Creed, which he pretends to be ours.</p>
               <p>As to <hi>the References,</hi> unto places in particular Authors; where Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> would have it thought, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of that Creed are affirmed: I have examined ſome of his principal References, and can ſay of 'em; they are either Perverſions, or downright Falſifications, of what the Authors (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to) did intend. Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> whoſe diſhoneſt Quotations out of the Socinians, have been deteſted by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Body, is hardly more blamable in that kind, than Mr. <hi>Edwards;</hi> ſaving that the Doctor being, as one rightly tells him, ſomewhat <hi>more than a Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> did but foul his own Neſt, by his Forgeries; but we cannot certainly ſay, what is the Opinion of Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> in the great Article, in queſtion among us. But come we to the Creed, which he ſays, is ours. As I promiſed, I will anſwer to every Article of it, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and directly.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:47056:3"/>I. <q>I Believe, concerning the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; that there are Errors, Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes, and Contradictions, in ſome places of it. That the Authority of ſome Books of it is queſtionable: yea, that the Whole Bible has been tampered with, and may be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be corrupted.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That <q>there are Errors, Miſtakes, and Contradictions in the Bible; was never ſaid, by any that pretended to be a Chriſtian; if by the Bible, you mean <hi>the Bible, as it came out of the hands of the (inſpired) Authors of it.</hi>
                  </q> As on the other hand, that there are Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Miſtakes, or Contradictions in the vulgar Copies of the Bible, uſed by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for inſtance, or the Engliſh Church, was never queſtioned by any Learned Man, of whatſoever Sect or Way; and leaſt of all, can Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſay it. He has publiſhed a Book, concerning <hi>the Excellency and Perfection of Scripture;</hi> in which Book he finds great Fault with our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Bible: he ſaith of it, in the Title of his 13th Chapter; <q>It is <hi>Faulty</hi> and <hi>Defective,</hi> in many places of the Old and New Teſtaments; and I offer all along in this Chapter, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Emendations,</hi> in order to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it more exact and compleat.</q>
               </p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Copies of the Bible; 'tis well known, ſome are more perfect, and ſome leſs: they differ very much; for in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Hebrew Criticks have noted 800 various Readings; in the New, there are many more. Mr. <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> ſo much eſteemed, and even ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated for his admirable Learning, ſays hereupon; and ſays it, <hi>cum Licentia Superiorum:</hi> 
                  <q>There is no Book in the World, that hath ſuffered ſo much by the hand of time, as the Bible.</q> 
                  <hi>Preface, p.</hi> 4. He judged, and judged truly; that tho the firſt Authors of the Bible, were <hi>divinely inſtructed</hi> Men: yet the Copiers, Printers, and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhers in following Ages, were all of them <hi>Fallible</hi> Men; and ſome of them <hi>ill-deſigning</hi> Men. He knew that all the Church-Hiſtorians, and Criticks have confeſſed, or rather <hi>have warned</hi> us, that ſome Copies of the Bible, have been very much Vitiated by the hands, as well of the Orthodox, as of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks: and that 'tis matter of great Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, at this diſtance of time from the Apoſtolick Age, to aſcertain the true Reading of Holy Scripture, in <hi>all</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it.</p>
               <p>Yet we do not ſay hereupon, as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> charges us; that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, much leſs (as he imputes to us) the <hi>Whole</hi> Bible, is corrupted. For as to the faulty Readings, in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bibles of ſome Churches, and in ſome Manuſcript Copies; the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God has ſo watched over this Sacred Book, that we know, what by Information of the antient <hi>Church-Hiſtorians,</hi> and the Writings of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> what by the <hi>early Tranſlations</hi> of the Bible into Greek, Syriac and Latin, and the <hi>concurrent</hi> Teſtimony of the more <hi>Antient Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript Copies;</hi> both who they were that introduced the corrupt Readings, and what is the true Reading in all <hi>Texts of weight and conſequence.</hi> In ſhort, as to this matter, we agree with the Criticks of other Sects and Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations; that tho ill Men have often attempted, they could never effect, the Corruption of Holy Scripture: the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47056:3"/>
                  <hi>Manuſcripts,</hi> the firſt <hi>Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> of the Church, are ſufficient Directors, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the authentick and genuine Reading, of doubtful Places of Holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>Farther, whereas Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> would intimate, that we reject divers <hi>Books</hi> of Scripture. On the contrary, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive into our Canon, all thoſe Books of Scripture, that are received, or owned, by the Church of <hi>England:</hi> and we reject the Books, rejected by the Church of <hi>England.</hi> We know well, that ſome Books, and Parts of Books, reckoned to be wrote by the Apoſtles, or Apoſtolical Men, were queſtioned; nay were refuſed, by ſome of the Antients: but <hi>we</hi> concur with the Opinion of the <hi>preſent</hi> Catholick Church, concerning them; for the Reaſons given by the Catholick Church, and which I ſhall mention by and by, in the Reply to my Lord of <hi>Chicheſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> would have truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented the Opinion of the Socinians, concerning the Scriptures; he knew where to find it, and <hi>ſo</hi> expreſſed, as would have ſatisfied every body. He knows, that in their <hi>brief Notes on the Creed of</hi> Athanaſius; they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, what is their Senſe, in very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exceptionable Words, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures are a <hi>Divine,</hi> an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible,</hi> and <hi>Compleat</hi> Rule, both of Faith and Manners.</q> 
                  <hi>Br.</hi> Notes, <hi>p.</hi> 1. The Church, neither requires, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, that they ſhould ſay more.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <q>I believe, concerning God; that he is not a <hi>Spirit,</hi> properly ſpeaking: but a ſort of Body; ſuch as Air, or <hi>Aether</hi> is. That he is not Immenſe, Infinite, or every where preſent; but confined to certain Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. That he hath no Knowledg of ſuch future Events; as depend on the Free Will of Man: and that it is impoſſible, ſuch things ſhould be foreſeen by him. That there is <hi>a Succeſſion,</hi> in God's eternal Durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as well as in Time, which is the meaſure of <hi>that</hi> Duration, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to <hi>finite</hi> Beings.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That Almighty God is <hi>Incorporeal, Omni-preſent,</hi> and <hi>Omni-ſcient;</hi> has not only been confeſſed, but proved, by the Unitarians of this Nation, in divers of their late Prints. As to the other, that all Duration; that of God, as well as of Creatures; conſiſts <hi>in a Succeſſion,</hi> is affirmed by ſome learned Men of all Perſwaſions and Ways, as well as by the Unitarians. It ſhould ſeem, Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> holds; that God poſſeſſes eternal Life <hi>all at once:</hi> that Eternity is, to God, one ſtanding <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent Moment.</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> is of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mind, for he deſcribes the Durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, by <hi>a Succeſſion;</hi> by <hi>was, is,</hi> and <hi>is to come.</hi> 
                  <q>Grace be to you, and Peace, <hi>ſays he;</hi> from him who <hi>is, was,</hi> and <hi>is to come,</hi> Rev. 1.4.</q> 'Tis undeniable by any, but affected Wranglers, that here the Duration of God, his Continuance in Being, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by the <hi>threefold Succeſſion (was, is,</hi> and <hi>ſhall be</hi>) which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all other Beings. Eternal Life poſſeſſed <hi>all at once,</hi> is one of the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Paradoxes, which our Oppoſers maintain; for all that I ſee, merely from a Spirit of Contradiction: for it has no manner of ground, either in Reaſon or Holy Scripture. I deſire to know of 'em, how the Duration of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47056:4"/>
God, is the leſs perfect; becauſe 'tis ſaid to conſiſt in <hi>a Succeſſion,</hi> or what is the ſame, to be diſtinguiſhed by <hi>was, is,</hi> and <hi>ſhall be:</hi> ſeeing 'tis confeſſed, on all hands, that he carrieth <hi>all</hi> Perfections, into <hi>every</hi> Succeſſion of his Duration.</p>
               <p>But is it not a Scandal, that ſome U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians of foreign Parts, have denied the Spirituality (or Incorporeity) of God; his Omnipreſence, and Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: ſaying, and contending for it, that he is <hi>a Body,</hi> with ſuch Configu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Parts as Men have; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that he is in Heaven, inſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed and governing all things, but by the Miniſtry of the ſeveral Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Angels; and that he doth not foreſee <hi>contingent</hi> Events; but only ſuch Events as are neceſſarily (not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarily) produced by their Cauſes? Doubtleſs; but no more a Scandal to the Unitarians, than to their Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers: for they are <hi>Errors,</hi> which ſome of the <hi>Fathers</hi> (even the moſt Antient, Learned, and Pious of them) have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended as Truths. Nay, it ſhould ſeem; they were ſometime the prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Opinions, in ſome Places: namely, when the Anthropomorphite Doctrine was ſo zealouſly eſpouſed; that the Hermits and Caenobites could not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure their Biſhops, if they but ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 'em of <hi>Origen</hi>'s Doctrine, that God is <hi>a Spirit, without Parts, or Paſſions.</hi> And in denying the Spirituality and Omni-preſence of God; they muſt needs be underſtood, not to believe his (cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and abſolute) Preſcience, of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent</hi> Events. About the Year 400, when almoſt every body concerned themſelves in condemning, and depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as far as poſſible) from the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of <hi>Origen;</hi> the Anthropomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phite Doctrine, and its Conſequences, were <hi>the Standard-Orthodoxy</hi> of many Places, and were <hi>Hereſy</hi> no where. Even St. <hi>John Chryſoſtom,</hi> at <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> hardly defended the <hi>Fratres lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi</hi> from the Proſecutions of <hi>Theophilus,</hi> Archbiſhop and Patriarch of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria;</hi> who was a profeſt Anthropomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phite, and had expelled the <hi>Fratres longi</hi> for adhering to <hi>Origen</hi>'s Doctrine, of the Spirituality and Omni-preſence of God.</p>
               <p>But as I ſaid, we not only diſlike, but utterly reject the dangerous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; that God hath a Body, is like to Man: together with its Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences; that he is neither Omni-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor Omni-ſcient. It may as well be ſaid, he is not at all: nay this latter, tho the Anthropomorphites ſee it not, ſeems to be implied and included in the former. But we condemn not the <hi>Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinah,</hi> or glorious Appearance of God in Heaven, which learned Men hold, neither the ſpiritual Body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <q>I believe farther, concerning God; that there is no Diſtinction of <hi>Perſons,</hi> or <hi>Subſiſtencies,</hi> in God. And that the Son, and Holy Ghoſt, are not God: the former of them, being only a <hi>Man;</hi> the latter, no other than <hi>the Power,</hi> or Operation of God. That there was nothing of <hi>Merit,</hi> in what Chriſt did, or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; that therefore he could not make <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for the Sins of the World.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> too much miſtakes. The Queſtion is not at all concerning three <hi>Perſons,</hi> or three <hi>Subſiſtencies,</hi> in God: but whether there are three In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite <hi>Subſtances;</hi> three eternal <hi>Minds,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:47056:4"/>
and <hi>Spirits?</hi> We deny the latter, with the whole Catholick Church, againſt <hi>the Realiſts:</hi> We never queſtioned the former, <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Subſiſtencies; but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as Perſons and Subſiſtencies are taken for Spirits, Minds, and Beings.</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever denies this to be the true Faith, is (himſelf) a Heretick, and out of the Catholick Church. But of this, more hereafter, in my Reply to the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> and to the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we ſay, Chriſt is only a <hi>Man;</hi> and the Holy Spirit, only <hi>the Power</hi> of God. No, we ſay; the Lord Chriſt is <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> He is <hi>Man,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his reaſonable Soul, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Body; <hi>God,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>God in him.</hi> Or more ſcholaſtically, in reſpect of the Hypoſtatical (or Perſonal) Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of the Humanity of Chriſt, with the Divinity. By which, the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church means, and <hi>we</hi> mean: the Divinity was not only <hi>occaſionally</hi> aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto, but was (and <hi>is) always</hi> in Chriſt; illuminating, conducting, and actuating him. More than this, is the Hereſy of <hi>Eutyches;</hi> and leſs, we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver held: tho we confeſs, that careleſs, or leſs accurate Expreſſions, may have been uſed by both Parties; of which, neither ought to take Advantage, againſt the other, when it appears there is no Heterodox Intention.</p>
               <p>That by <hi>the Spirit</hi> of God, is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times meant (in Holy Scripture) <hi>the Power</hi> of God, cannot be denied: but concerning the three Divine Perſons, we believe, as the Catholick Church believes; that they are <hi>relative Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtencies,</hi> internal <hi>Relations</hi> of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to it ſelf. Or as the Schools explain this; Original <hi>unbegotten</hi> Wiſdom or Mind, reflex or <hi>begotten</hi> Wiſdom, and the eternal <hi>Spiration</hi> of Divine Love. But we do not think theſe Terms fit to expreſs that Senſe.</p>
               <p>But do you not ſay; <q>There was no <hi>Merit,</hi> in what Chriſt did, or ſuffered: and that he could not make <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for our Sins?</q> He may for our Parts be <hi>Anathema,</hi> that teaches, or believes that Doctrine. <hi>We</hi> believe, that the Lord Chriſt by what he did, and what he ſuffered, <hi>was,</hi> by the gracious Acceptance of God, a true and <hi>perfect Propitiation</hi> for Sinners, that repent, and turn to the good ways.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <q>In the next Article, he makes us believe a great many things; as <hi>that</hi> the firſt Man was not created in <hi>a State of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs.</hi>
                  </q> As if it were poſſible, that Men in their right Senſes, ſhould think; the firſt Man was created <hi>a Sinner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <q>by his Fall, <hi>Adam</hi> did not loſe <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and Holineſs, which are (part of) <hi>the Image</hi> of God.</q> As who ſhould ſay, that by being a Sinner, he did <hi>not ſin,</hi> or become <hi>unlike</hi> to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no <hi>hurt,</hi> or <hi>ſtain,</hi> by his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy.</q> As if you ſhould ſay; that neither his <hi>bad Example,</hi> nor the <hi>Curſe</hi> that made the Earth ſo much leſs fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, was any <hi>hurt:</hi> and that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of an Anceſtor, no not againſt God, is no blot in his Family. I ſhall grow quite out of Conceit, with theſe Unitarians; if they ſay many more, ſuch weak things. But in very deed, I imagine, Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> had a mind to have charged 'em more home; when he does, we ſhall conſider what to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47056:5"/>
I am of opinion, that in this part of the Article, he is ſomewhat aſhamed of his own Doctrine: and that he feared to make himſelf, and Party, ridiculous; by a clear and diſtinct Repreſentation of their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> 
                  <q>Mankind, notwithſtanding <hi>Adam</hi>'s <hi>Fall,</hi> have <hi>by Nature</hi> an Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to deſire and imbrace <hi>all</hi> ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Good; and to avoid <hi>all</hi> that is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or vitious.</q> They are <hi>bold Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans.</hi> What, imbrace <hi>all</hi> the Goſpel-Precepts, by mere <hi>Nature:</hi> When 'tis not poſſible, ſo much as to know divers of them, but by <hi>Revelation Divine?</hi> And can they avoid too <hi>all</hi> that is viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, by only <hi>Nature?</hi> In good truth, they are better, and ſtronger, by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, than ever I hope to be, in this Life, by the (ſuper-added) <hi>Grace of the Goſpel.</hi> But here again, he did not ſtrike home; he intended more than he durſt ſay: and he durſt not ſay it, leſt we ſhould ask him; whether he believes the juſt contrary?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> 
                  <q>there is <hi>no</hi> need of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to repent, believe, and perform religious Acts.</q> 'Tis a ſerious Point. We anſwer with St. <hi>Paul; the Spirit HELPETH our Infirmities,</hi> Rom. 8.26. But we judg, for all that; the Holy Scripture giveth no occaſion to any, to turn Enthuſiaſts: and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the whole Duty we owe, and muſt perform to God, and to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; into praeternatural Impulſes, as if we were Machines, and not Men. Or Puppets, moved by inviſible Wires; not Men, that act by their own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and Choice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> 
                  <q>Men are <hi>Righteous</hi> before God; not, by the Merit of Chriſt: but, by their own good Works.</q> We anſwer, with all but Antinomians, and the more rigid Calviniſts: the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt is not reckoned to us, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good Works of our own. But I am not certain, that the Calviniſt or Antinomians would not aſſent to this Propoſition, or not allow it to be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Another Branch of our Creed, according to Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> runs thus: <q>I believe concerning a future State; that the Souls of the Deceaſed have no Knowledg, or Perception of any thing: they are not ſenſible of any Rewards, or Pains; and <hi>their very Nature is abſorpt.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>That at Death, the Soul as well as the Body <hi>ſleeps,</hi> was an <hi>Error</hi> of ſome of the moſt antient <hi>Fathers,</hi> as well as of <hi>ſome</hi> Unitarians. But neither of them ſaid, as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> pretends, that in Death the very <hi>Nature of the Soul is abſorpt:</hi> they both held, that there is a Reſurrection of the Soul, as well as Body. But why does Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> impute that Opinion to <hi>us;</hi> when he had read (for he quotes the Book) in the firſt Part of the <hi>Conſiderations on the Explication of the Trinity,</hi> what is our Senſe of this Matter? The Words there, at <hi>p.</hi> 33. are theſe: <q>This <hi>Error</hi> was common to <hi>Socinus,</hi> with ſome of the Fathers. The learned Mr. <hi>Du. Pinn</hi> has noted, in his Abridgment of the Fathers; that <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Irenaeus, Minutius Foelix,</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius,</hi> were in this Sentiment. There was no Reaſon to object <hi>this,</hi> to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinus;</hi> as if it were a peculiar Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>his:</hi> much leſs to the Engliſh Unitarians, who never defended it;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47056:5"/>
nor (that I know of) do any of them hold it.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. He ſays next; <q>I believe we ſhall not riſe with the <hi>ſame Bodies,</hi> that we now have: but that another <hi>Matter</hi> or <hi>Subſtance,</hi> ſhall be ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in their Place.</q> I ſee, moſt of our Oppoſers have affected to miſtake our Meaning, concerning the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Body: We hold no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that is ſingular in the caſe; we differ not from the Catholick Church, about it. We ſay with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.35. <hi>How are the Dead raiſed; and with what Bodies do they come? —Thou ſoweſt not the Body that ſhall be.</hi> The Body that is raiſed, is not in <hi>all</hi> reſpects, <hi>the ſame</hi> that was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Earth: in divers, perhaps in <hi>the moſt,</hi> it is. We riſe not <hi>Infants,</hi> or decrepit <hi>old Men,</hi> or <hi>lame,</hi> or <hi>deaf,</hi> or any way <hi>diſtorted;</hi> tho many ſo lived, and ſo died. Nay, as to <hi>the Paſſions,</hi> reſulting from the Complexion of the <hi>preſent</hi> Body; and therefore to be reckoned the Modifications (and as it were, Parts) of our Body: we riſe not, with them; it is not the <hi>ſame</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in reſpect of thoſe Paſſions, that it here lived. For inſtance, ſome are (by Complexion) very cowardly, or penſive, or cholerick, or jealous; <hi>the Body that ſhall be</hi> will not be ſuch: it will be conformed to the Likeneſs of the glorious Body of the Lord Chriſt; that is, be freed from all (both exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and internal) Imperfections. Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, our preſent Body (Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Philoſophers ſay) is in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Flux: all the Parts of it, internal as well as external, continually decay; and are continually renewed. They decay, by the Perſpiration, that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually cauſed by the internal Heat; and are continually renewed, by the Nouriſhment taken in, and converted into Blood, Spirits, Fleſh, and Bones. 'Tis ſaid by the Learned in theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; that no Man's Body is the very ſame, as to the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> of it, this preſent Year, that it was the laſt Year, and will be the next Year: 'tis wholly new-built, by the Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the preſent Year. We ſay therefore, there ſhall be a Reſurrection of the Body; and as ſome of the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Creeds ſpoke, of the <hi>ſame Body;</hi> as truly, and as properly, as <hi>N. N.</hi> is the <hi>ſame Man</hi> this Year, that he was one, or ſeven, or twenty Years ago. If Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> requires us, to ſay more; he exacts more than the Church believes: for by the Reſurrection of the <hi>ſame Body,</hi> the Church intends only; that 'tis as truly the ſame, as a Man (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Flux of his Parts) is now the ſame <hi>N. N.</hi> that he was ſeven, or ten Years paſt; yet not altogether the ſame, becauſe inconceivably better: that is, without any external, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Deformities or Weakneſſes.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. <q>I believe, that at the Day of Judgment, Men ſhall not be required to give an Account of their Actions; the moſt flagitious Sinners ſhall not be <hi>examined,</hi> concerning any thing of their paſt Life: only they ſhall be puniſhed; and their Puniſhment is this, to utterly ceaſe, or periſh, for ever. The unquenchable Fire is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Annihilation.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I do not know, that the Scriptures, or the Catholick Church, do require any to believe; that Sinners ſhall be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47056:6"/>
                  <hi>examined concerning their paſt Life,</hi> at the Day of the General Judgment. To what purpoſe, I pray? Doth the all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing Judg need to be informed, concerning the Particulars of their Guilt? If every Perſon is to be ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examined, concerning the Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of his tranſacted Life; the Day of Judgment will extend it ſelf to many Millions of Ages more, than the whole Duration of the World, from its Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to its Conſummation. It ſhould ſeem, Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> thinks, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scriptures ſpeak of the great Judgment by God, in the Terms and Language of Men, and of humane Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatories; ſuch as Trumpets, the Throne of the Judg, a formal Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, the Pleadings of the Guilty, the Anſwers of the Judg: that therefore in very deed, we are to expect ſuch a Scene, at the Judgment by God, as at a common Aſſize. I conceive, on the contrary; that all ſuch Expreſſions and Words, whereſoever they are found in Scripture, are not intended as real De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions: but as Compariſons, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances; by which, the Capacities of the Vulgar may be aſſiſted, and their Affections wrought upon. All that is intended by ſuch Expreſſions, is only this: that every one ſhall be ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed, at the Reſurrection; as is worthy of the Holy Judg, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate Father of the World.</p>
               <p>But we hold, he ſaith; that the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Wicked, is only <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction:</hi> their Life ſhall be deſtroyed for ever, by the (unquenchable) Fire, into which they are caſt. Which Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that it may look ridiculous, he words (for us) thus; <q>The unquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Fire</hi> is, nothing but <hi>Annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </q> What the Scriptures have ſaid, concerning the Puniſhment of the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after the Reſurrection, is not ſo clear; but that the Opinions of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men, <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Moderns,</hi> have been very different, about it. Some, (of which Number is <hi>Origen,</hi> the moſt conſiderable of the Ante-Nicenes) held, that not only wicked Men, but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Devils, will repent, and reform, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Puniſhments they indure: that therefore they will be pardoned; be admitted to a new Trial of their Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and may attain to Bleſſedneſs. Theſe ſay, that Man being a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is therefore a docile, or teachable Creature; and it not looking proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the Wiſdom of God will loſe any part of his Creation, but will bring it to <hi>the Perfection,</hi> and upon that to <hi>the Bleſſedneſs,</hi> of which 'tis capable: therefore, what by Inſtructions, what by Puniſhments, and Encouragements, God will reclaim the Bad, will perfect and confirm the Good; and ſo in the long-run of things, be acclaimed <hi>the Saviour of All.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others, among whom have been ſome (it may be, the moſt) of the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Unitarians, have thought; that the Righteous are rewarded with an everlaſting Life of Bleſſedneſs; and the <hi>impenitent Wicked</hi> puniſh'd, by that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable Fire, which will wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their Being. They believe, this is the Reaſon; why the Puniſhment by Hell-fire is called eternal <hi>Death</hi> in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture. But the more current Opinion, among all Denominations of Chriſtians, is; that the Puniſhment of the Impenitent in Hell-fire, is called Death: not becauſe it utterly deſtroys the Life of the Sufferer; but becauſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47056:6"/>
'tis a continual and <hi>endleſs Dying.</hi> The <hi>extreme Pains</hi> of Hell may well be called, an <hi>everlaſting Dying,</hi> or an <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death;</hi> tho the Sufferer is never extinct.</p>
               <p>I do not find any thing in the Books of the Engliſh Unitarians, concerning theſe Opinions; they may hold as va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly concerning them, as the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of other Denominations. But if I may anſwer for them, by what I judg of 'em, by Converſation with 'em: I would ſay, <hi>We</hi> approve the Doctrine delivered by Archbiſhop <hi>J. Tillotſon,</hi> in a Sermon before her late Majeſty, of happy Memory, <hi>March</hi> 7, 1689. on <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.46. which Sermon was printed by their Majeſties ſpecial Command.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. <q>I believe, as to Chriſtianity it ſelf; that every thing in it, is to be ſubmitted to the Dictates of <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Reaſon;</hi> and that there are no Doctrines in it, that are myſterious.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Neither of theſe was ever ſaid, by any Unitarian; and all our Prints, more particularly thoſe in the Engliſh Tongue, are expreſs: that there are many things, as well in Religion, as Nature, that are far above the Capacity of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Reaſon, to declare or underſtand <hi>the manner of 'em;</hi> or how they ſhould be what, we either ſee, or are <hi>infallibly</hi> taught, they are. We never pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the <hi>human Reaſon is the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Truth;</hi> as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> and Mr. <hi>Norris</hi> charge us; ſo that what our Reaſon does not comprehend, we will not believe on any other Evidence whatſoever. We never ſaid it, or thought it; we reject no Doctrines, but ſuch as are <hi>contrary to Reaſon:</hi> and of that, I will ſpeak fully, in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Mr. <hi>De Luzancy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">IX. <q>As to Divine Worſhip, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; it may be given to another, beſides God: to Chriſt, who is <hi>but a Creature.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But we have diſavowed nothing more, in all our Prints, than giving Divine Worſhip to any, but only God: that 'tis a marvel to me, that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſhould impute to us, ſuch a Doctrine; we have ſcarce an Engliſh Print, where we do not expreſly oppoſe it.</p>
               <p>Nor do we reckon of the Lord Chriſt, as <hi>but a Creature:</hi> I have ſaid before, <hi>He is God, and Man.</hi> The Divinity doth <hi>ſo</hi> inhabit the Humanity of Chriſt; doth <hi>ſo</hi> exert in it, the moſt glorious Effects of Omnipotence and Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: that if others have been called God, becauſe <hi>they repreſented God;</hi> Chriſt is to be ſo called, becauſe <hi>he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">X. <q>I believe, Prayer was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, under the Old Teſtament. The Lord's Day is a ceremonious Obſervance, aboliſhed by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. There is no ſpiritual Bleſſing conferred in the Uſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Baptiſm is an uſeleſs Rite; and the Baptiſm of Children, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vain. There is no diſtinct Function or Office of Miniſters, in the Chriſtian Church: the very Lord's Supper it ſelf may be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by a private Perſon.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I think, Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> is in the right, againſt thoſe (if any ſuch there were) who denied, that Prayer was a Duty or Precept of the Old Teſtament, and the Law; when he ſays, it is included and implied in the general Precepts of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47056:7"/>
Fearing, Serving, or Worſhipping God. But he is as much out, in the next Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle; that ſome have ſaid, that the <hi>Lord's-day</hi> is aboliſhed by the Goſpel; for it was never taught by any. He meant, I ſuppoſe, that the <hi>Seventh Day,</hi> or Sabbath, is aboliſht: and I take it to be the Doctrine of the Catholick Church, that <hi>the Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> was Ceremonial, and is aboliſht. It may better however be ſaid, that the Sabbath <hi>is transferred,</hi> from the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, to the Firſt Day; than that 'tis <hi>abſolutely aboliſht,</hi> or taken away. In ſhort, the Engliſh Unitarians hold no private Opinion, about either the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, or the Lord's-day; but as well in Principle as Practice, concur with the Catholick Church.</p>
               <p>It is too looſly ſaid; that <q>there is no ſpiritual Bleſſing conferred, in the uſe of the Sacraments.</q> For there is no Ordinance of God, but the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and devout Performance of it, draws a Bleſſing on the Doer. For all that, many exceed, in aſcribing to the Sacraments certain Powers and Ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, without competent Warrant from the Word of God. I do not know, that Baptiſm is any thing more than a <hi>federal Rite,</hi> by which we are initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, into the Chriſtian Religion; or the <hi>Holy Supper</hi> any thing more, than <hi>a Commemoration of the Sacrifice of Chriſt;</hi> offering himſelf to God, as an Atonement for repenting Sinners. I know not to what purpoſe ſo many ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Books are written; to teach People, how to prepare themſelves for the <hi>Memorial Supper:</hi> when an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Intention, and a <hi>reverent</hi> Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, are ſufficient both <hi>Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> and <hi>Qualifications, for,</hi> and <hi>in</hi> all Goſpel-Ordinances. The Apoſtle ſays; <q>He that eateth that <hi>Bread</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, or unworthily drinketh that Cup, is guilty of the Blood of Chriſt; <hi>nay,</hi> eateth and drinketh <hi>Judgment</hi> to himſelf.</q> But he alſo warns 'em, what he means by <hi>unworthy</hi> Partaking; namely, their <hi>not tarrying for one another:</hi> and withal, eating and drinking, with ſo little regard either to God or Men, that ſome of 'em <hi>made themſelves drunk with the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Wine,</hi> while others could not ſo much as taſte of it. Briefly, their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling to this ſolemn <hi>Commemorative Sacrifice,</hi> was more like <hi>a Carouſal,</hi> than a Celebration, of the Holy and Bleſſed Memory, of a dying Saviour. Theſe were the Diſorders, and Irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities, concerning which they were to <hi>examine themſelves;</hi> and thereby avoid an unworthy Communicating, and the Conſequences of it.</p>
               <p>We do not ſay, <q>Baptiſm is an <hi>uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> Rite: or that the Baptiſm of Children is altogether <hi>vain.</hi>
                  </q> What the Wiſdom of God has appointed to <hi>all Nations,</hi> is not to be eſteemed <hi>uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs;</hi> tho we our ſelves knew not the Uſes of it: and it is Uſe enough, that this Sacrament is <hi>an initiating Rite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor is it a good Exception, againſt this Sacrament's being continued ſtill, that <hi>now</hi> People are Chriſtians <hi>by Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:</hi> ſeeing there is the ſame Reaſon for <hi>its Continuance,</hi> as for <hi>its Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> namely, a ſolemn, publick and formal <hi>Initiation, into the Religion of Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this may in ſome ſenſe be done <hi>in Infancy,</hi> by the Intervention of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers, commonly called Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and how it can be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47056:7"/>
'em, I ſee not. But it is without all reaſon, that Parents ſhould not be admitted to be Undertakers; when others cannot, or cannot eaſily be had. It were well, methinks, if the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Church-wardens (together with the Parents) were obliged to be Undertakers <hi>ex Officio,</hi> or <hi>ratione Officii,</hi> by their Place and Office; and it were yet better, if the whole Church under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took for the Infants. Moreover, where <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> is the Cuſtom of the Church; <hi>Confirmation</hi> (or the Perſon's taking upon himſelf the Covenant and Promiſes, that were made in his Name, by his Undertakers) ought to be as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle neglected as <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> nay the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot be ſaid, to be a <hi>compleat</hi> Chriſtian, or to be Chriſtianly bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd, till he is <hi>Confirmed;</hi> that is, has publickly taken upon himſelf, his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Engagements.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, As to that, <q>I believe there is no diſtinct Function or Office of <hi>Miniſters:</hi> and the very Lord's-Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per may be adminiſtred by a private Chriſtian.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer for my ſelf, and the many Unitarians; there is a threefold Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Church-Officers, by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves modeſtly called <hi>Miniſters:</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Biſhops, Presbyters (call'd Prieſts) and Deacons. The former were of <hi>Divine Right:</hi> the other of <hi>Apoſtolical Inſtitution only;</hi> and that too (as appears from <hi>Acts</hi> 6.3, 4.) not by any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Inſpiration, but meerly on Motives of Prudence and Charity. Theſe three Orders are of that Antiquity, and Univerſality; that <hi>as ſoon as,</hi> and <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,</hi> Chriſtianity was profeſſed, the Churches were governed after this Form. A Form received among all the Sects of Chriſtians, as well as by the ſounder part of 'em, called <hi>the Church;</hi> till Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> in <hi>a Caſe of Neceſſity,</hi> introduced a new ſort of Church-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration. Theſe are they, to whom only (except <hi>in Caſe of Neceſſity,</hi> ſuch as <hi>the Reformation</hi> was) it belongs to adminiſter the Sacraments; and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and exhort publickly. But what makes <hi>a Caſe of Neceſſity,</hi> is a Queſtion by it ſelf; on which I am not obliged to enter: I wiſh the Church had not given, and may never give cauſe to the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians; either by Excluſion, or Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or unlawful Terms of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; to have recourſe to Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Expedient.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. <q>As to Moral Points, I believe that <hi>Officious Lies</hi> are lawful; the Motions of <hi>Concupiſcence,</hi> not viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; idle or obſcene Words, Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, Drunkenneſs, Riot, Luxury, and impure Deſires and Luſts, were not forbidden till <hi>Chriſt's</hi> time.</q> By <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Lies</hi> are meant thoſe <hi>Falſities,</hi> that do good to ſome, without doing any hurt to others. As when the Hebrew Midwives made <hi>Pharaoh</hi> believe, that the Hebrew Women were ſo quick, that they were (commonly) deliver'd of their Children, before the Midwife could come to them; and therefore there was not Opportunity to ſtrangle their Children, as they came forth, from the Womb. So alſo, when <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> eſcaped from <hi>Saul,</hi> by the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of his Wife <hi>Michal;</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> was therefore angry with his Daughter <hi>Michal:</hi> She ſaid, <hi>David</hi> threatned to kill her, if ſhe did not agree <hi>to,</hi> and aſſiſt his Eſcape. And <hi>Jonathan</hi> excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Abſence of <hi>David, by feigning</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:47056:8"/>
that <hi>David</hi> had asked his leave, to aſſiſt at the yearly Sacrifice, made by his Family, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.17. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.6, 28, 29. <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.19. To <hi>Officious Lies,</hi> belong alſo Compliments; very low Bowings, and reſpectful Carriage, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Perſons for whom we really have not the Kindneſs, or Regard, of which we make ſhow by thoſe external (and falſe) Significations. I think, it may excuſe <hi>Volkelius,</hi> whom Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> cites upon this part of his Charge; that the Officious Lies of the Midwives, of <hi>Michal</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> are related in Scripture, without blaming them: they are not cenſured by the Inſpired Writers; they are told by the Prophets (<hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi>) without the leaſt Signification that they were Sins. <hi>Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelius</hi> might infer from hence, that the Texts which forbid Lying and Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are intended of ſuch Lying as is <hi>hurtful,</hi> and <hi>prejudicial</hi> to another: and that what does no hurt, can be the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of no Law. To forbid what helps ſome, even to the ſaving of Life, or Goods, without any wrong or hurt to another; why ſhould any Lawgiver forbid it? Notwithſtanding, I think, Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſays well; <q>If once ſuch Doctrine is commonly taught, all Lies will be reckoned ſome way or other <hi>Officious;</hi> and Truth and Sincerity will be baniſht from the Earth.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Motions of <hi>Concupiſcence,</hi> are not vitious or ſinful.</q> By <hi>Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence</hi> is meant ſome unlawful Deſire, or Inclination, ariſing in the Mind, but not conſented to, or put into practice. Methinks, ſo far forth as ſuch Motions in the Mind, are <hi>involuntary;</hi> they ſhould rather be called Frailties, than Sins: and the diſapproving, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting them, ſhall be rewarded by God.</p>
               <p>Concerning <q>obſcene Words, Riot, Gluttony, Drunkenneſs, impure De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, not forbidden by <hi>the Law,</hi> and not ſtrictly unlawful, till prohibited by the Goſpel:</q> We are not much concerned, in ſuch a Diſpute; it being confeſt on all hands, that they are forbid in the Writings of the New Teſtament. Notwithſtanding, I wonder, that any ſhould ſay, they are not prohibited in the Moſaick Law. Some of them were puniſhable with Death, by that Law: as Gluttony and Drunkenneſs, by the Law at <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.20. Luxury, Riot, Luſt, and ſuch like, are contrary to the Good of a Man's Children, and of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; or of his Neighbour, and the Commonwealth: and therefore are <hi>(implicitely)</hi> forbid by that Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.18. which requires, that a Man ſhould love his Neighbour, as himſelf. I do not love my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, as my ſelf, if I am guilty of <hi>Luxury</hi> or <hi>Riot,</hi> by which <hi>my Heir,</hi> and <hi>the Poor</hi> are defrauded: or if I am guilty of Ambition, Covetouſneſs, or Luſt; by which I ſpoil, or grind, or wrong my Neighbour. Nay, Luſt, Riot, Exceſs, Covetouſneſs, do unfit us, and very much, for the Service of God, and for the honeſt and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſcharge of our Station, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever that be, in the Commonwealth; therefore they are <hi>implicitely</hi> forbidden, by all thoſe Commandments of the Law, that require either the Fear, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard and Service of God, or the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and Eſteem of our Neighbour, or ſelves.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:47056:8"/>XII. <q>Concerning Magiſtrates, I believe, 'tis not lawful for them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, to inflict Capital Puniſhment <hi>(Death)</hi> on any Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, no not on Murderers.</q> This was the Doctrine, of divers of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of the 3 firſt Ages; ſcarce any of them believed otherwiſe. Nay, they added, it is not lawful to go to War, as a Souldier; or to aſſiſt at Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutions; or even to defend a Man's own Life, by any ſuch reſiſtance, as will take away the Life of the (injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) Aggreſſor. The Reaſon they gave for this <hi>laſt</hi> was; that by killing a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who attempts to murder me, he is diſpatched out of the World <hi>without Repentance,</hi> and therefore is certainly damned: but <hi>the Chriſtian</hi> by being killed, loſes only <hi>this</hi> Life; and enters upon a bleſſed Immortality. Some Unitarians have been of this mind; while others have written againſt the whole Doctrine. In ſhort, it is not their Doctrine <hi>as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians;</hi> for ſome of them have held it, while others (I believe the moſt) diſallow it.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. <q>Concerning ſome other Points, I believe, as the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> believes; for we agree with them, in ſeveral Points of Doctrine.</q> What theſe Points are, he tells us at <hi>Ch.</hi> 9. from <hi>p.</hi> 201. namely that ſome things were ſaid by our Saviour, by way only of Monition or Counſel, not of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. That we Merit, by a good Life; and may be perfect. That all Sins are not damnable. That the Prayers of the Living may help the Dead. Nay the Author of <hi>the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, on the Explications of the Trinity,</hi> ſpeaks favourably of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation.</p>
               <p>Let us begin at the foot of this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. The Author of <hi>the Conſiderations,</hi> is no otherwiſe favourable, to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> than by ſaying of it: <q>'tis only a <hi>Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Error,</hi> or <hi>Folly;</hi> not an Impiety, <hi>page</hi> 21.</q> And again, at <hi>page</hi> 22. <q>'Tis <hi>a Miſtake,</hi> into which the Papiſts have been cozened, by the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy of <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>
                  </q> Would Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> think, a Man favoured the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, in his Books; if he called them Miſtakes, Errors, and Follies? Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> finds Impiety, Irreligion, Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, and what not, in all Doctrines, and all Authors, he diſlikes: <hi>We</hi> are not ſo dextrous. We ſometimes think, that we ſpy an <hi>Error,</hi> or <hi>Miſtake;</hi> and ſometimes it ſeems ſo groſs, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Name of <hi>a Folly:</hi> but to call it Impiety, Irreligion, Abnegation of Chriſtianity; how much ſoever Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> delights in it, and makes it his conſtant Practice, as well in Preaching as Writing; we cannot approve the Example, it being always contrary to Charity, Good Manners, and Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Prayers of the Living may help the Dead.</q> There is no Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Scripture, nor (I think) any ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid ground in Reaſon, for ſuch a Belief. Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> quotes for it, but one So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian Writer, nor is that Author po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, in the Caſe. He only ſays; <q>Thoſe who believe <hi>a middle State</hi> of the Dead, do well to pray for them.</q> That is, in caſe you ſuppoſe, beſides Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Hell, ſome <hi>middle place,</hi> where Souls may repent and reform, or where they have not yet received their Doom: it is Charity, to intercede by our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47056:9"/>
for them; as much as we would for the Living. I believe, he is the only Writer of his Sect that can be charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any ſuch thing: but we have it (in Print) concerning a late Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sheldon;</hi> that he prayed for the Dead, in his <hi>daily Prayers.</hi> But what one particular Man does, or ſays, ought not to be imputed to his whole Party; and reported to the World as <hi>an Article of their Creed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>All Sins are not damnable. A Chriſtian <hi>may Merit,</hi> by his good Works; and may be <hi>perfect.</hi>
                  </q> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Perfection may be <hi>truly,</hi> or <hi>falſly</hi> ſaid, of the Works and Life of a Chriſtian Man; according as you interpret the Terms, Merit and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Taking 'em in the ſenſe, that Proteſtants uſe them; no Man can me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, the infinite Recompences of Heaven, and of Bleſſedneſs everlaſting: nor was any Man perfect, or without Sin; but only that <hi>Lamb of God, who taketh away the Sins of the World.</hi> But Merit and Perfection are ſometimes uſed in <hi>a popular Senſe;</hi> namely, for that (tho imperfect, yet) <hi>ſincere Obedience</hi> to God's Commandments, to which God has graciouſly appointed the <hi>recompence</hi> of everlaſting Bleſſedneſs in Heaven: and for <hi>univerſal Obedience,</hi> as it is oppoſed (not to Overſights and Frailties, but) to <hi>a wilful Indulging</hi> our ſelves, in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Sins. In this Senſe, every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtian both merits, and is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Yet I own, divers Unitarian Writers have ſpoke either too looſly, or too incorrectly on the Point of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; but they have been as much oppoſed, by ſome of their own Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. The ſame cannot be ſaid, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the diſtinction of Sin, into Mortal and Venial; for our People are poſitive and unanimous, that as St. <hi>John</hi> words this Matter, <hi>there is Sin, which is not unto Death,</hi> 1 John 5.16. God Almighty, they ſay, hath not appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Hell-fire for our Frailties and Inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertencies; but for our <hi>Contempts,</hi> and <hi>adviſed</hi> Breach of his Laws.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Some things ſaid by our Saviour, are Counſels, to ſuch as would be perfect; not abſolute indiſpenſible Commands, to all the Faithful with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception.</q> He quotes for this, an obſcure Paſſage of one ſingle Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Writer; who never was eſpouſed, in that matter, by any of his Party. We judg, the diſtinction of Counſels and Commands, is a great and very dangerous Preſumption; a Back-door, by which to eſcape from (almoſt) a Man's whole Duty. The two Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of <hi>Counſels for the Perfect,</hi> and <hi>probable Opinions,</hi> will furniſh the moſt profligate Wretch in the World, with Defences, for his very greateſt Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Laſtly, after all I believe, tho the aforeſaid Articles are <hi>all</hi> neceſſary, to make a Man <hi>a Socinian:</hi> yet the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of only one, is enough, to make a Man <hi>a Chriſtian:</hi> and that <hi>one</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle is, that <hi>Jeſus is the Meſſias.</hi> In which, it is not included, whether he be <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Man;</hi> or whether he ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Divine <hi>Juſtice</hi> for our Sins by <hi>his Death:</hi> but only, that a Man of <hi>Nazareth</hi> was ordained, and ſent of God, to be <hi>a Saviour.</hi>
                  </q> I ſee, all Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi>'s Colts-teeth are not yet out of his Head; he cannot forbear, dealing ſometimes in Railery and Wit:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47056:9"/>
but I muſt (ſeriouſly) deſire him, to name me any Socinian or Unitarian Writer, that ever ſaid; no more is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to make <hi>a Chriſtian,</hi> but only that he believe, that <hi>Jeſus is the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias.</hi> The Truth of the matter is this; Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> has been lately very much foiled, firſt by a Learned Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, then by a Divine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> upon this Queſtion: <q>Whether it be of the Eſſence of a Chriſtian, <hi>as a Chriſtian,</hi> to aſſent to more than this one Article, that <hi>Jeſus is the Meſſias, ſent by God to inſtruct and ſave the World?</hi>
                  </q> They do not doubt, that 'tis a Chriſtian's Duty, to learn (by degrees) all the other Articles of the Chriſtian Creed, and to believe them; but if he hath attained, or (by occaſion of <hi>Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of any ſort,</hi> that were not cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his own Negligence, or Perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) he can attain, to no more <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,</hi> or <hi>Faith:</hi> yet this one Article doth make him a Chriſtian. It doth not ſatisfy Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> that upon all the Points in queſtion, they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared themſelves to be Anti-Socinians: he reſolves for all that, they ſhall be Socinians; and this Opinion which they maintain againſt him, <hi>a new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle</hi> of the Socinian Creed. It may be one way, he thinks, to reduce them to Silence; if he calls their Opinion, Socinianiſm: and if after that, they will not pull in their Horns, in his next Book it ſhall be Irreligion, or downright Atheiſm; or at leaſt, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negation of Chriſtianity, or Popery; his other Compliments to thoſe, whom he is pleaſed to attack.</p>
               <p>I have now anſwered, concerning all the Articles of our Religion, with Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity; without any the leaſt diſguiſe, or reſerved, or unuſual Meaning, or Meanings. And I am not ſorry, that Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> (almoſt) conſtrained us, to explain our ſelves, concerning theſe Points. For as unſincere and untrue, as his Imputations are; and as ſcurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, as his manner of repreſenting 'em, and diſcourſing upon them, ſometimes is: the Retortion (or Anſwer) here made, will be judged by indifferent and diſcerning Perſons, to be home, and ſatisfactory. As to the Man himſelf, Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> has been ſerviceable, to the common Chriſtianity, by ſome learned Books; therefore I wiſh to him whatſoever Good, himſelf deſires to himſelf; theſe Concertations between us notwithſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:47056:10"/>
               <head>In Anſwer to the <hi>Vindication, of four Sermons,</hi> of his <hi>Grace,</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>J. Tillotſon;</hi> by my Lord the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HIS <hi>Lordſhip</hi>'s Preface is, for the bigger part of it, an angry Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Reſpects, paid to the Archbiſhop, and other Perſons of Dignity and Learning, by the Author of <hi>the Conſiderations,</hi> through his whole Anſwer to them. But I doubt, as to that, we muſt always hold our ſelves content: for in the <hi>Holy War,</hi> againſt reputed Hereticks, what in poor <hi>Laicks</hi> would be cenſured as want of Urbani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Charity; in <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> is <hi>the Zeal of thy Houſe</hi>—.</p>
               <p>In one Place of his Preface, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip objects to <hi>the Conſiderer;</hi> that there was a time when <hi>Paulus</hi> and <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus,</hi> Unitarian Archbiſhops, flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and their Followers abounded eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where. Well, what then? Why, he will tell it us, <hi>as a Secret;</hi> they did not treat <hi>the Trinitarians,</hi> as Fathers their Children, but like tyrannical Judges. Violences and Outrages, Fire and Faggot, were in Faſhion among them; Biſhops were depoſed, exiled, and ſlain; and the whole Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire put into a Combuſtion, by theſe infamous Practices. His Lordſhip does well, to tell us this, <hi>as a Secret;</hi> for 'twas never heard of, till he publiſhed this Vindication of the Archbiſhop's Sermons. I deſire him, to name the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, from whom theſe Calumnies have been taken up: and becauſe I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded he has none to cite; I will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to ſay, he cannot avoid the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of too haſty taking up a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach. <hi>Paulus</hi> and <hi>Photinus</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as his Lordſhip ſays, Unitarian Metropolitans. The former ſucceeded, tho not immediately, to the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in the Patriarchal Chair of <hi>Antioch:</hi> The other was Primate of <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyricum.</hi> It is true alſo, what his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip adds; that their Followers abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every where. In the time of the firſt Nicene Council, or the Year 325. they had their Biſhops and Presbyters, their Deacons and Deaconeſſes, like other Denominations and Sects of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; as is intimated in the 19th Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of that Council. But they never were Perſecutors; but the perſecuted. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Photinus</hi> were both of them ejected, out of their Biſhopricks; <hi>Paul</hi> by <hi>a Pagan Emperor,</hi> at the inſtance of a Council of Heretical Biſhops, who denied <hi>Homo-uſios: Photinus</hi> by <hi>an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Emperor,</hi> at the Requeſt of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of Biſhops no leſs heretical; for they contended for <hi>Homoi-uſios.</hi> And for their Followers, the other Unitarians; it never was in their Power, to be Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors: for they never were the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Party, but always lived <hi>ſub Cruce;</hi> they chearfully took up, and imbraced <hi>the Croſs,</hi> in hopes to <hi>inherit the Promiſes.</hi> Whereas his Lordſhip pretends, that <hi>Fire and Faggot</hi> were in faſhion, when the Followers of <hi>Paulus</hi> and <hi>Photinus</hi> abounded, and (as he would have it thought) prevailed every
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47056:10"/>
where: 'tis certain, <hi>that ſort of Church-Diſcipline</hi> was not known to the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, whether Trinitarians or Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; it was not introduced till about the Year 1216, and was exerciſed firſt on the Albigenſes, by <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic,</hi> Founder of the Order of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans.</p>
               <p>He concludes his Preface, that he will not ask Pardon, for what he has imputed to us; that we have been great Perſecutors, even as far as Fire and Faggot. And I anſwer, when he proves his Imputations, we will ask <hi>his</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; and beſides, will moſt willingly undergo any Penalty, or Shame, how great ſoever.</p>
               <p>The Body of his Lordſhip's Book, is divided into two (very unequal) Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: the firſt, concerning the Divinity of our Saviour; the other, concerning his Incarnation. The Section concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Saviour's Divinity, is part of it laid out, in aſſerting the Authority of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel; the reſt, on ſome Texts (cited by the Archbiſhop) either for the Divinity of our Saviour, or for his Pre-exiſtence. I will firſt ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>in general,</hi> concerning the Bleſſed Trinity; the Deity of our Saviour, and his Incarnation: and then, make Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it, to his Lordſhip's Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <head>Of the Trinity; Divinity, and Incarnation, of the Lord Chriſt.</head>
               <p>I Am perſwaded, that the Queſtions concerning the Trinity, the Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Saviour, and the Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo long controverted, between the Church and the Unitarians; are a Strife, moſtly about Words and <hi>Terms,</hi> not of Things and <hi>Realities.</hi> And this Diſcovery is owing, to the Sagacity and Dexterity of the <hi>Engliſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians:</hi> who having (firſt) diſtinguiſhed thoſe that pretend to be the Church, into <hi>Nominal Trinitarians</hi> and <hi>Real Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians;</hi> or if you will, into <hi>Trinitarians</hi> and <hi>Tritheiſts;</hi> they (next) prove their Agreement with the former of theſe, <hi>the Nominals;</hi> and (then) that the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Party</hi> is what ought to be called <hi>the Church.</hi> That the <hi>Nominal Party</hi> is the Church, is inconteſtably proved; becauſe their Doctrine, or Explication of the Trinity, has been directly (and in Terms) eſpouſed by <hi>General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils,</hi> and the contrary (the Explication or Doctrine of <hi>the Realiſts</hi>) as expreſly and directly cenſured and condemned by the ſame Authority.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Realiſts</hi> believe, that the Trinity is three diſtinct infinite <hi>Subſtances, Minds,</hi> and <hi>Spirits;</hi> all of them co-eternal, of like Dignity, Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and all other Divine Attributes. And as to three ſuch Perſons being one God; they ſay: <q>Becauſe they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meate, or are (inſeparably) <hi>in one another,</hi> therefore they are called one God; tho each of them (diſtinctly conſidered) is perfect God. Yet this Perichoreſis, Immeation or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtence, is not ſuch an In-being of theſe three Spirits or Subſtances in one another; but that they really re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main as <hi>diſtinct</hi> Subſtances, Minds,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47056:11"/>
Spirits, and Beings, as three Angels, or three Men are.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>the Nominals</hi> abhor this, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Tritheiſm; they ſee plainly, and proclaim it aloud to every body, that three infinite <hi>Spirits,</hi> tho as <hi>Spirits</hi> they may, and as <hi>infinite</hi> Spirits they muſt be ſuppoſed to immeate (or inexiſt in) one another: yet they are no more made to be one God, by ſuch <hi>alternate Penetration;</hi> than if they were at ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great a Remotion from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Reaſon is; becauſe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their mutual Inexiſtence, neither their Underſtandings, or Wills, or other Powers, nor their Subſtances, become continuous or identified, but remain truly diſtinct, ſeveral, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. They are ſuppoſed indeed to be <hi>in</hi> one another; but as diſtinctly, and without Confuſion either of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances or Powers: as three Angels (while they occupy the ſame Space, and exclude not one another) are. Or to uſe another, perhaps a better, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon; as theſe three Divine Spirits themſelves, are <hi>in</hi> all things, in the whole Creation; and the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>in</hi> them. Such an Inexiſtence as this, every one ſees, is ſo far from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king three (eternal infinite) Spirits to be one God; that we can poſſibly have no other Notion of three Gods. For what is the Conception that any Man has, or can have of three Gods; but this: <hi>viz.</hi> ſo many infinite Spirits, which ſo pervade or inexiſt in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that (notwithſtanding) their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, Faculties, and Attributes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main <hi>diſtinct</hi> and <hi>divers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is ſuch a Reaſon, and ſo obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; that <hi>the Nominals</hi> utterly reject, and with the greateſt Abhorrence, the Doctrine of three infinite Spirits; and explain the Trinity, or three (Divine) <hi>Perſons,</hi> in a metaphyſical way.</p>
               <p>They ſay; we are not to conceive of the three Divine Perſons, as we do of <hi>created</hi> Perſons: the Conception we ought to have of <hi>their Perſonalities,</hi> or what they are as they are <hi>Perſons,</hi> is as different from the Perſonalities of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Beings, whether they be Angels or Men; as the Perfections of the Divinity are ſuperiour, to Human or Angelical Perfections. God is but one Being, but one Subſtance, Mind, or Spirit; with one only Will, Underſtanding, Energy, or Power of Action: nor are the Divine Attributes multiplied, or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated</hi> in the Deity; for there is in God no more than one Omnipotence, Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience, or other Divine Perfection. It is only <hi>God,</hi> that phyſically and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly exiſts, as a vital Being, or a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Spirit and Mind: <hi>the Perſons</hi> are only the Subſtance of God (his infinite, ſpiritual, and moſt perfect Subſtance or Nature) with the three Properties, to be <hi>of none,</hi> to be <hi>begotten,</hi> and to <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some are yet more particular, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring or explaining, what the Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalities and Perſons are. Theſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in God, firſt <hi>original Mind,</hi> or original Wiſdom; this is the Perſon of <hi>the Father.</hi> Then, <hi>reflex Wiſdom;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the <hi>Logos,</hi> or Wiſdom, that reſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from God's contemplating or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own Perfections; or (what is the ſame) the perfect <hi>Image,</hi> that is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated or <hi>begotten,</hi> by God's knowing and underſtanding himſelf: which is called <hi>the Son.</hi> Laſtly, the (immanent) Act of <hi>LOVE,</hi> by which God willeth or loveth himſelf; his <hi>eternal Spiration</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:47056:11"/>
(or as it were, Breathing) of Love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward himſelf: this is named the <hi>Holy Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort, the Trinity believed by the Realiſts, is <hi>three</hi> diſtinct infinite and pre-eternal Spirits; each of which is a perfect God: and all of them but one God, by their mutual Inexiſtence, or that they are <hi>in</hi> one another; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Confuſion, or identifying their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, or their Powers. The Trinity believed by the Nominals, is <hi>one</hi> living eternal infinite Spirit; conſider'd under this threefold Diſtinction, Unbegotten, Begotten, and Proceeding; or <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Mind</hi> which is unbegotten, <hi>reflex Wiſdom</hi> which is generated, and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love</hi> which proceeds. Original Mind being unbegotten, is therefore named <hi>the Father; reflex Wiſdom</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (manifeſtly) generated by original eternal Mind, is called <hi>the Son;</hi> the <hi>laſt</hi> being a Spiration of God, has there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Appellation of Holy Spirit. And tho the Nominals uſe ſometimes other Terms, in ſpeaking of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſuch as Modes, Relations, relative Subſiſtences: yet no more, or other is meant by them, than has been already ſaid.</p>
               <p>This Trinity of the Nominals is moſt directly (as I ſaid) and explicitly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, by divers <hi>General Councils;</hi> in whom only it is, to declare the Faith, and to pronounce what is to be deemed Hereſy. And this alſo is the Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that has been followed without any Variation, by all particular Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whether Reformed, or Roman Catholicks, or of the Greek (or Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ental) Church; ſince the Year 1215.</p>
               <p>But if this be the Catholick Faith, as it certainly is; the Unitarians are as ſound Catholicks, as any other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of Chriſtians whatſoever. They believe the Trinity before-ſaid; even <q>
                     <hi>one</hi> infinite ſpiritual Subſtance, with its <hi>three</hi> Properties, Unbegot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, Begotten, and Proceeding. <hi>One</hi> eternal Spirit, under the triple Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of <hi>Original Mind, Reflex Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Divine Love.</hi> They approve of it, that the firſt of theſe being <hi>unbegotten,</hi> the ſecond <hi>genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and the third <hi>a Spiration;</hi> they be therefore called Father, Son, and Spirit.</q> Indeed the Terms <hi>Trinity,</hi> and <hi>Perſon,</hi> are unſcriptural; but we accept them, according to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication by the Church: that is, as the Catholick Church has (in the manner aboveſaid) explained her ſelf concerning the three <hi>Perſons</hi> of the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> We have therefore no Difference with <hi>the Church;</hi> but only with <hi>the Realiſts,</hi> who are a few <hi>Engliſh Writers,</hi> that have departed from the Doctrine of the Catholick Church.</p>
               <p>It was a ſtrange Imputation, on his <hi>Grace</hi> the late Archbiſhop; that he was an Unitarian: his Grace was a Realiſt. He underſtood by <hi>Perſons</hi> in the Deity, not Perſons in a metaphyſical Senſe; as the Nominals do, and as was before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained: but Perſons in a phyſical Senſe of the Word, or ſuch Perſons (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as vitally ſubſiſting, and as really diſtinct) as three <hi>Angels,</hi> or three <hi>Men</hi> are. According to the Modes of Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>now</hi> in uſe; only <hi>compleat Beings,</hi> not Properties or Faculties, or imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Acts, are called Perſons: and his <hi>Grace</hi> expreſly declares, that he means by Perſons, <q>ſuch Perſons as we <hi>uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally intend</hi> when (in common Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) we ſpeak of ſo many Perſons,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47056:12"/>
or ſuch and ſuch Perſons.</q> But let us, for avoiding Cavils, take his Senſe in his own Words; he ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 120. <q>Here I fix; that there are three Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in the Deity, of which the Scriptures ſpeak by the Names of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; and farther, ſpeak alſo every where of them, <hi>as we uſe to do, of three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Perſons.</hi> Therefore I ſee no Reaſon, to abſtain from the word <hi>Perſons;</hi> tho I remember, St. <hi>Jerom</hi> deſires (ſomewhere) to be excuſed from it.</q> It is certain, that <hi>in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Diſcourſe,</hi> or (as his Grace ſpeaks) <hi>uſually,</hi> we mean by three or more Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſo many <hi>compleat Beings;</hi> and if thoſe Beings are <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> we always mean ſo many <hi>Spirits.</hi> As for Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, immanent Acts, mere relative Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtences, Modes; tho formerly (and properly) they were, yet <hi>now</hi> they are not called Perſons; but are conſider'd and ſpoke of, as only the <hi>Affections of Perſons.</hi> It cannot therefore be denied to his <hi>Grace,</hi> that he was a Realiſt; the three Divine Perſons (or the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) according to him, are three ſuch kind of Perſons as are <hi>uſually meant</hi> in common Diſcourſe: namely, ſo many <hi>compleat Beings;</hi> and becauſe theſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are infinite and ſpiritual, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore three ſeveral infinite <hi>Spirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Lord of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> having under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, to write a Defence of his <hi>Grace's</hi> Sermons; 'twere not unreaſonable to ſuppoſe, that he eſpouſes alſo the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop's Notion of the Trinity. But however that be, we muſt put it to him, either to profeſs the Archbiſhop's Explication; which would commit him with the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Heads of Colleges, who have decreed it to be Hereſy: or to ſay, that by Perſons in the Deity, he underſtands only three <hi>Properties,</hi> or <hi>relative Subſiſtences,</hi> conſidered with the Subſtance in which they are; and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly <hi>unbegotten Mind, reflex Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and <hi>Divine Love;</hi> and then we deſire much, to know, why he hath written againſt the Unitarians, who believe that Trinity as much as other Catholicks do.</p>
               <p>I know not, whether it be neceſſary to take notice of my Lord of <hi>Sarum</hi>'s (unlucky) Trimming, between the two Parties of the Nominals and Realiſts. He repreſents it, as a very inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Difference; that <q>ſome Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in their Explications of theſe My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, ſo much adhere to <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Deity, that their <hi>Trinity</hi> ſeems unconceivable: while others aſſert ſuch <hi>a Trinity,</hi> as ſeems incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
                  </q> By the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe, he means <hi>the Nominals;</hi> by the other, <hi>the Realiſts.</hi> He declares, that as different as their Explications are; their Religion is the ſame. Juſt (ſays he) as ſome Proteſtants believe the Conſubſtantiation; others, a real Preſence; and others, only a figurative one: or as ſome believe, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of God are grounded on his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of future Events, while others think, that the Decrees of God are the fixed Cauſes of all Events; and yet this Diſſent notwithſtanding, the Litigants on both ſides truly have the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Sarum<hi>'s Letter, to Dr.</hi> Williams, <hi>p.</hi> 85, 86.</p>
               <p>I obſerve, that ſome Men overflow with Charity; and have a Catholick and boundleſs Latitude, in their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: but then they diſpenſe both the one and the other, wholly by Motives
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47056:12"/>
of Policy. Sometimes (namely, when both Parties are powerful) they will comprehend the Phariſees, with the Sadduces; otherwhile the Breadth of a Philactery, ſhall be an intolerable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: but the one and the other, as the Maxims of ſecular Policy, and the Air of Popularity, ſhall invite. His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip could afford to write a Paſtoral Letter to his Clergy, againſt the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians, as Hereticks, <hi>whoſe Principles are deſtructive of the common Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:</hi> but the Nominal Trinitarians, who hold neither more nor leſs than the Unitarians, differ ſo little (he ſaith) from the other Trinitarians; that they not only have the ſame Religion, but <hi>they ought not to be at all offended at one another,</hi> p. 86.</p>
               <p>But the Parties concerned, are of a very contrary Judgment to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. The <hi>Oxford</hi>-Heads declare, that the Doctrine of three infinite Spirits, Minds, or Subſtances, is <hi>Impiety and Hereſy.</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> and his Fellow-Realiſt anſwer that, <q>What the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>-Heads have condemned, as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical and Impious, is the very Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Faith: and that this Decree or Declaration cenſures the Nicene Faith, and the Faith of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as Hereſy; and expoſes both, to the Scorn and Triumph of the Socinians.</q> 
                  <hi>Examination of the</hi> Oxford-<hi>Decree,</hi> pag. 46. And who indeed, but he that wilfully ſhuts his Eyes, can avoid ſeeing it; that to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm but <hi>one</hi> infinite Mind and Spirit, and to ſay there are <hi>three</hi> ſuch Minds and Spirits, is a Difference as weighty, as 'tis unreconcileable? They who ſay the former, and they who contend for the latter, can no more be ſaid to be of the <hi>ſame Religion;</hi> than Paganiſm and Polytheiſm can be pretended to be the ſame with Judaiſm or Chriſtianity. <q>But what I chiefly inſiſt on, is this; that his Lordſhip being ſo indifferent, whether we hold <hi>one</hi> or <hi>three</hi> eternal and infinite Spirits; yet he publiſhes his Invectives againſt the Unitarians, as undermining (he ſaith) and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ining the main Articles of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: while <hi>the whole that can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to 'em,</hi> is, that <hi>they believe</hi> (with all the Nominal Party) <hi>but one infinite and eternal Spirit.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Archbiſhop was of Opinion, that <q>the Trinity is three ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as we <hi>uſually intend,</hi> when in <hi>common Diſcourſe</hi> we ſpeak of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi>
                  </q> Namely, compleat intelligent Beings, diſtinct from every other Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; not Properties, Relations, or other Affections of Beings. My Lord of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> on the contrary, ſays expreſly; <q>by <hi>a Perſon</hi> in the Trinity, is not meant ſuch a Being, <hi>as we commonly underſtand by that Word:</hi> namely, <hi>a compleat intelligent Being;</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that every one of <hi>the bleſſed Three,</hi> has a peculiar Diſtinction, by which he is different from the other two.</q> The Biſhop contradicting <hi>in Terms,</hi> the Doctrine of the Archbiſhop; the latter believing three <hi>ſuch</hi> Perſons of the Deity, as we <hi>uſually mean</hi> by Perſons in common Diſcourſe; the other denying expreſly, that there are any <hi>ſuch Perſons</hi> in the Godhead as we <hi>commonly underſtand</hi> by the word <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and particularly not three diſtinct <hi>compleat Beings:</hi> it was very expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, a neceſſary piece of Prudence, that the Biſhop (in the Letters he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects to his Clergy) ſhould endeavour
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47056:13"/>
to poſſeſs 'em; that his Difference with his Metropolitan, is a mere Trifle; and that it matters not, whether we hold <hi>three</hi> diſtinct compleat (infinite) Beings and Spirits, or <hi>one</hi> ſuch Being only. I am perſwaded however, that there are great Numbers in the <hi>Salisbury</hi>-Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; that cannot be ſo impoſed on: they will ſee, that their Dioceſan, in purſuit of the Principles laid down in his Letters to them, ſhould have cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned them againſt the Archbiſhop's Sermons; not againſt the Unitarians, whoſe Doctrine perfectly agrees with his own. Saving that (with the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>-Heads) we believe it to be <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy,</hi> to profeſs the Faith of more than <hi>one</hi> infinite Being, which is a <hi>compleat Being</hi> diſtinct from all other Beings; but his Lordſhip holds it to be <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> whether we affirm or deny <hi>three</hi> infinite Beings and Spirits.</p>
               <p>His Lordſhip propoſed, to write with that Caution and Guard, that no Body ſhould be able to attack him; and by Trimming between the Nominals and Realiſts, to ſet up for <hi>a Healer of the Breaches,</hi> a Mediator of Peace. But the Event wholly fails him. He utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſobliges the Realiſts; by denying, in Terms, what the Archbiſhop (with all other Realiſts) had affirmed, in Terms; and the whole Realiſt Party look upon as a Fundamental Article. The Nominals are as much diſpleaſed with him; becauſe he ſets no Value on the Catholick Faith, but repreſents it as a very indifferent Truth, that may be as orthodoxly denied, as affirmed. The Unitarians complain of him, as having pretended to Principles of Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and a true Catholick Charity; but uſing neither, but perhaps as the turns of Popularity, and Rules of ſecular Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, ingage him.</p>
               <p>But this was a Digreſſion. Let us take up our Point again, that the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians hold the Faith of the Catholick Church, or Nominal Party: that is, they believe but one eternal and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Spirit; and as to three Divine <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> they admit the Church's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (<hi>viz.</hi> that they are <hi>relative Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtences, Properties</hi> of the Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) concerning them. They agree, that there are <hi>three Diſtinctions</hi> in God, which may be fitly called Original Mind, Reflex Wiſdom, and Divine Love: the firſt unbegotten and Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and therefore named the Father; the other Generated, and therefore (in the Language of Men) called the Son; the third a Spiration, and therefore ſtiled the Holy Spirit. Whether you call theſe, Properties, Modes, Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Perſons, relative Subſiſtences, or ought the like; we will not contend with the Church: for it being agreed that they are not diſtinct <hi>Beings,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Spirits</hi> and <hi>Minds,</hi> ſeveral <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances;</hi> but <hi>one</hi> infinite Subſtance, Mind, Spirit, and Being, with one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Underſtanding, Will, and Energy; it is plain, that the Unity of God is preſerved; and that the Terms uſed are only obſolete and odd, but imply no Falſhood, nor any real Innovation in Religion. And I ſay hereupon, that unleſs my Lord of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs <hi>three</hi> Divine Beings, Spirits, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and Minds, contrary to the Deciſions of divers General Councils; the Conſent of Writers, ſince the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination in the Council of <hi>Lateran, Anno</hi> 1215. and the late Decree of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford:</hi> I ſay, if he will
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47056:13"/>
not contravene all theſe; neither ought he to have defended the Archbiſhop's Sermons, nor could he oppoſe <hi>the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations,</hi> that were not (for all that I ſee) written againſt the Doctrine of the Church, but the Error of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts.</p>
               <p>As we accord with the Catholick Church, in the Article of <hi>the Trinity;</hi> ſo alſo in that of <hi>the Incarnation,</hi> or the Divinity of our Saviour. For when the Church ſays, the Lord Chriſt is God, when ſhe worſhips him, invocates him, imputes to him the Creation of all things; and for all this, alledges Authorities, and Examples, out of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture: nothing of all this is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended of his Humanity, or <hi>to</hi> his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity; but to the indwelling Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. In ſhort, ſhe means, that as the <hi>Cloud of Glory,</hi> in the Times of the Old, Teſtament, was called God, and was worſhipped, becauſe God dwelt in it after an eſpecial manner: ſo, and much more, may we call the Lord Chriſt, God and Creator, and the reſt, becauſe of the Godhead dwelling in him after an ineffable unexplicable manner, and without meaſure; but whatſoever of <hi>Divine,</hi> is ſaid of him, is ſaid merely in reſpect of the <hi>inhabiting Divinity,</hi> and not of the Humanity. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of Idioms, as Divines ſpeak, is merely verbal, not real: Chriſt is God, and the Creator, is worſhipped and invocated, becauſe of the Deity in him; for tho theſe things are ſaid of the <hi>Man</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, they are ſaid only in reſpect of the Divinity, and are intended only of that.</p>
               <p>If any ſay, no Indwelling (or, as the Church ſpeaks, Incarnation) in what ſoever manner or meaſure, can give to ſuch Perſon the Name of <hi>God;</hi> much leſs of Creator. So indeed <hi>Neſtorius</hi> thought; and therefore refuſed, to call our Saviour <hi>God,</hi> or to aſcribe to him either the Works or Attributes of God: and many learned Men have contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that <hi>Neſtorius</hi> was as raſhly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, as he was (afterwards) bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly uſed. Yet upon ſerious weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the matter, it appears not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to litigate about Terms and Words, on which the Authority that impoſes them, puts an honeſt Senſe and Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The Church would never have obliged <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> to call the Man Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Creator;</hi> but declaring at the ſame time, that tho it is the <hi>Man</hi> that is called God, he is ſo called only in reſpect of the Indwelling of God in him: which Indwelling is after a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſo extraordinary, ſo abundant, or rather ſo ineffable; that Chriſtians may with greater Right call him God, than <hi>the Cloud of Glory</hi> is ſo named, becauſe of the Angel (in it) who repreſented God; or than any other Appearance of God (whatſoever, or in what manner ſoever) mentioned in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Brightneſs of the Cloud of Glory, was only from the Power of the inhabiting Angel; yet becauſe the Angel repreſented God, the bright Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance between the Cherubims, was named Jehovah and God: How much more may the Lord Chriſt be ſo called, in whom the Divinity it ſelf did dwell; not as a Man in his Houſe, but as the Soul in the Body: that is to ſay, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly illuminating, conducting, and actuating him; nay and exerting in him the moſt glorious Effects of Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and Omnipotence, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Attributes of the Divinity? 2 <hi>Kings</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:47056:14"/>
19.15. Hezekiah <hi>prayed, and ſaid; O Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which dwelleſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Cherubims: thou art God, even thou alone.</hi> 1 Chron. 13.6. <hi>David went up, and all</hi> Iſrael, <hi>to</hi> Baalah; <hi>to fetch thence the Ark of GOD, JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH that dwelleth between the Cherubims, whoſe Name is called on it.</hi> It cannot (I think) be denied, that here the bright Appearance between the Cherubims; becauſe God was in it, tho only by his Angel, not by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertion of any miraculous Acts, by no Acts of Omniſcience or other Divine Attribute; is named <hi>Jehovah, God,</hi> and <hi>only God,</hi> or <hi>alone God.</hi> The Church never required of <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> to ſay, the Lord Chriſt is <hi>Creator,</hi> or <hi>God;</hi> without this Explication, <hi>in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God in him:</hi> which ſeeing <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius</hi> owned, and having the Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the Jewiſh Church and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Old Teſtament, who cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Appearance between the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims by all the Names and Titles of God; he needed not to have contended, but ſhould have conſulted the Churches Peace; for no words are to be refuſed, when the Authority that impoſes 'em, interprets 'em to a ſound Senſe.</p>
               <p>This is what the Unitarians believe concerning the Trinity; and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Divinity of our Saviour, or the Incarnation. We have no Conteſt with the Catholick Church, concerning either of theſe: we do not indeed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the Churches Language, or Terms, becauſe <hi>they are unſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> and <hi>liable to Heretical Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations;</hi> but we embrace her whole Meaning and Senſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Church ſays, and we aſſent to it; that there is one only eternal (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite and all powerful) Spirit or Mind: and this Mind or Spirit, is what we call <hi>God,</hi> or the Divinity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But whereas in God, the Church owns alſo a threefold diſtinction, which ſhe calls three <hi>Perſons,</hi> or more expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly, <hi>original unbegotten Wiſdom;</hi> the <hi>Logos,</hi> or begotten <hi>reflex Wiſdom;</hi> the Proceſſion, or Spiration of <hi>Divine Love:</hi> and theſe, for the Reaſons above-mentioned, are alſo named <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son,</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> three Relations, three Properties, Modes, and divers the like. We cry; remove your Jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, and give us only the Words of Scripture. The Church anſwers; No, you ſhall ſubmit to theſe Terms, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as much as they ſeem improper, being now out of common Uſe; they were once as proper and appoſite, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in common Uſe; and you admit the whole that we intend by theſe (antiquated) Words and Phraſes. We ſubmit.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Then, as to the Incarnation; or that the Lord Chriſt is God, and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, is to be invocated and worſhipt: the Church profeſſes, that this is ſaid, or required, only <hi>in reſpect of God in him.</hi> How in him, is the infinite God commenſurate to a finite Manhood? No, but <hi>in reſpect of God in him,</hi> that is, Illuminating, Conducting, Actuating, and (as much as Infinite can inhabit Finite) <hi>dwelling in,</hi> Him; as intimate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, immediately, and powerfully, as the Soul the Body. Nay, exerting in him the Divine Attributes, Omniſcience or the <hi>Knowledg of the Future, and of the Thoughts,</hi> and Omnipotence or <hi>Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Actions.</hi> If the Angel that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſented God, and the Cloud il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminated by that Angel, have all that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47056:14"/>
often ſaid of 'em, in Holy Scripture; that is wont to be ſaid <hi>of,</hi> or <hi>to</hi> God: how much more, when 'tis for Peace; and with Liberty, of declaring your Meaning; may you call the Lord Chriſt, whatſoever they are called? Here again, we would willingly demur, as <hi>Neſtorius</hi> did: but Charity and Peace are two ſuch great Goods; that we will not Non-conform, for the ſake of <hi>(dangerous) Terms, honeſtly explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is by this Declaration of our Meaning, that all our Books (paſt or to come) are to be interpreted. We never intend to oppoſe any Body, in the Article of the Trinity; but the <hi>Tritheiſts</hi> (or <hi>Realiſts</hi>) who are Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks to the Church, as well as to us: nor in the Article of the Divinity of our Saviour, but the <hi>Eutychians,</hi> who make the <hi>Communication of Idioms</hi> to be Real, and not only Verbal; which is an Heterodoxy condemned in divers General Councils. When we oppoſe the Doctrine of the Trinity; 'tis only the (Chimerical) Trinity, of <hi>three</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite All-perfect <hi>Spirits:</hi> when we deny, the Lord Chriſt is God, the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, may be invocated, or worſhipt; we mean not this, of <hi>the Divinity in him,</hi> but of the Humanity. The inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting Divinity, or Chriſt <hi>in reſpect of God in him,</hi> is God over all, all things were made by him; and God is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly to be worſhipt and invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>If his Lordſhip aſſents not to theſe things, he contravenes the Doctrine of the Catholick Church; and eſpouſes <hi>Philoponus, Joachim, Gentilis,</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychius:</hi> but we do not in the leaſt ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that this Learned Prelate will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own the Catholick Doctrine; or be of Party to Hereticks, that have <hi>been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by ſo many General Councils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any object to us, that as much as we now claim to be Catholicks; and profeſs to aſſent to the Churches Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, tho we wiſh ſhe would diſcharge her humanly-invented Terms and Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; yet we have been always diſowned, and oppoſed, nay perſecuted by the Church; and by that very Party of Nominals, whom we pretend to be the Catholick Church. I anſwer; there has been an unhappy Miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, between the genuine Members of the Catholick Party. The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitaries</hi> (who diſlike nothing, but the Liberty that is taken, to uſe any other but Scripture-words and Language, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the Faith) and the Nominals (who alſo wiſh, that all would return to, and content themſelves with, the Simplicity of Scripture) have pelted one another as Enemies: but upon ſuch a groſs Miſtake, as the two <hi>German</hi> Cavaliers are noted for, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>the Reformation;</hi> who quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled, and challenged one another up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on difference of Religion, one of them being a <hi>Martiniſt,</hi> and the other a <hi>Lutheran.</hi> I doubt not, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Diſcourſe concerning the <hi>Nominals</hi> and <hi>Realiſts,</hi> has convinced all Learned and Ingenuous Men; that Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> for inſtance, and Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> and other Nominals, had no more Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fall foul on the Unitarians, than the Lutheran on the Martiniſt: and the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding between them being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to proceed from a Miſtake of one anothers true Opinions; they ought now to own each other, as Brethren. If the Nominals are ſhy, of cloſing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47056:15"/>
with us, and owning us for Orthodox; we ſeek not their Patronage: and the common Oppoſers of both, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, will always tell 'em; that the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals and Unitarians differ juſt as the Martiniſts and the Lutherans.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <head>On the reſt of his Lordſhip's Book; and an Application of what hath been ſaid.</head>
               <p>FOR the reſt of his Lordſhip's Book; one great part of the firſt Section is imployed, in finding out Anſwers, to the Arguments of ſome of the antient Unitarians: who pretended to prove, that St. <hi>John</hi> was not the Author of the Goſpel, or the Revelation; which now bear his Name. The Remainder of the Section, is an Endeavour to wire-draw the firſt Verſes of that Goſpel to a purpoſe (in my Judgment) very contrary to the true Intention of the Evangeliſt; and to impreſs ſome other Texts, into the Service of the <hi>Realiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The preſent Unitarians, whether in <hi>England</hi> or elſewhere, receive the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of St. <hi>John,</hi> as his. But as Faith has degrees, or is not always ſuch a Plerophory of Aſſent as to be without all Alloy of doubt: ſo we wiſh, this Goſpel had never been queſtioned; and that the Reaſons of the Alogians, who imputed this Goſpel and the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> were inconteſtably ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. We cannot take his Lordſhip's Anſwers, or Arguments; as at all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory: becauſe his Reaſonings are (oftentimes) very Inaccurate; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as often) they are contrary to notorious Matter of Fact. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, who can bear it; when he ſays: <q>
                     <hi>Cerinthus</hi> taught, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was a <hi>mere</hi> and a <hi>late-born</hi> Man: but St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, the WORD <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways</hi> was; and came down from Heaven, and was made Fleſh. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Cerinthus</hi> could not be Author, of the Goſpel of St. <hi>John;</hi> without moſt plainly contradicting himſelf.</q> For it is certain, on the contrary; that <hi>Cerinthus</hi> never ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was a <hi>mere</hi> and <hi>late-born</hi> Man, but an <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> and <hi>impaſſible Spirit.</hi> In the Perſon of our Saviour, <hi>Cerinthus</hi> diſtinguiſh'd <hi>Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi> he called the Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity by the Name of <hi>Jeſus:</hi> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> or the WORD, according to <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> was a certain Divine and Impaſſible Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; which deſcending on Jeſus at his Baptiſm, dwelt in him, and forſook him not till the very moment of his Death; when he cried out, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Iren. Lib. 1. c. 25. I do not ſee, how this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count contradicts any thing in St. <hi>John;</hi> whoſe Goſpel the Alogians ſaid was written by <hi>Cerinthus.</hi> But I will not diſpute with his Lordſhip, about this matter; for as I ſaid, the Unitarians do receive that Goſpel and the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as St. <hi>John</hi>'s: as they receive the Epiſtle to the Hebrews, the Epiſtle of St. <hi>James,</hi> the Second of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> the Second and Third of St. <hi>John;</hi> all which were ſometime doubted of, nay rejected, by divers Catholick Writers and Churches, but have at length been owned by the whole Church. Tho the Catholick Church now owns theſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, and ſome Chapters and Sections
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47056:15"/>
in the Goſpels; as written by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, whoſe Names they bear: yet not with <hi>the degree of Aſſurance;</hi> that ſhe receives thoſe Parts of Scripture, that were never controverted. The <hi>Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> cannot be equal, where <hi>the Grounds</hi> of Aſſent are unequal: but the Grounds of Aſſent, to the Writings of which we are ſpeaking, cannot be ſaid to be equal; becauſe in Matters whether of Record or Fact, what was <hi>always</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and granted by <hi>all,</hi> is more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick and credible, than what has been queſtioned, and even rejected by divers of the Antients (<hi>Writers</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi>) who were <hi>Catholicks.</hi> In ſhort, concerning all Books, and Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Books, of the New Teſtament; ſometime doubted of, by ſome of the Antients: the Unitarians acquieſce in the Judgment of the Catholick Church; and for the Reaſons, given by the Church. As <hi>firſt;</hi> becauſe tho they were queſtioned, and even rejected by ſome, <hi>Writers</hi> and <hi>Churches;</hi> yet it appears, they were approved by many more; by ſo conſiderable a Majority, that in a ſhort time they were admitted by all. We ſee in <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> that even <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus,</hi> and <hi>Photinus,</hi> receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Goſpel of St. <hi>John.</hi> Secondly, becauſe not only they contain nothing that is <hi>certainly</hi> contrary to the unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned Parts of Scripture; but they are written with the ſame kind of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that the undoubted Portions of Scripture are: there is a Likeneſs in the Thoughts, Expreſſions, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever elſe recommends to us the other Books of Scripture, as written by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Apoſtolical Men. Theſe are ſufficient Motives of Aſſent, and ought to prevail with us; tho there are ſome Difficulties, not eaſy to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved: we ſubmit to the weight of theſe Arguments; tho we confeſs, that what has been alledged by the Alogians and others, is not deſpicable or ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. To conclude, we receive, with the Catholick Church, the controverted Books; without cenſuring in the mean time, much leſs condemning thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, or Moderns, who were or are of another Mind.</p>
               <p>What remains of his <hi>Lordſhip's</hi> firſt Section, is a Scuffle with <hi>the Conſiderer,</hi> on behalf of the Arch-Biſhop's Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the firſt Verſes of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel, and of ſome other Texts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by his <hi>Grace,</hi> to confirm his ſaid Explication. To all which, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. There is no Form of Words, that were not conceived deſignedly to preclude all Exception, but is liable to cavil; nay our Lawyers ſcarce obtain their purpoſe, when in Deeds and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances they imploy the whole Art of Grammar, to aſcertain the Meaning and Intent of the Conveyance or Deed: it is not therefore to be wondred at, that Perſons, highly intereſted by their Education, Honour and Parties, <hi>can</hi> (and with ſome colour) interpret ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure or ambiguous Texts, to a Senſe, not intended by the Original Author. If People are not diſpoſed to be ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; a little Wit, ſome Learning, and a long Practice in the Polemics, will enable 'em to maintain a Squable till Doomſday, about the Senſe of any (ordinary and familiar) Context. I do not think therefore, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention between the Unitarians and the Realiſts, will ever be healed by that Pretence of either Party, that <hi>theirs is the only Interpretation</hi> or Senſe, of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47056:16"/>
which the litigated Texts are capable, in the Court of Grammar and Criticiſm. But towards a Coalition, it will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to agree in ſome <hi>common Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, confeſſed to be clearly aſſerted in Scripture;</hi> by Conſonancy to which Principles, all otherwiſe <hi>doubtful Texts and Contexts</hi> of Scripture, and <hi>their Interpretations,</hi> ſhall be judged of. This Rule of interpreting, is very certain; none can diſtruſt it, without ſuppoſing, either that the Sacred Scripture contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts it ſelf: or that the human Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is not capable of judging the Agreement, or the Diſſonance of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with it ſelf. No Body, I believe, will ſay the former; that the Scripture contradicts it ſelf: and if any ſay the other, that we cannot judg of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonance, or Agreement of Scripture with it ſelf; or of <hi>particular Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> with <hi>Principles</hi> that are yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be found in Scripture; <hi>all Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is at an end, on both ſides.</hi> But if the Rule be allowed, that ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon agreed Principles are to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht; by which, all obſcure (that is, all <hi>controverted</hi>) Texts muſt be interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: the Queſtions and Interpretations debated between us, being thus brought before the Bar of Reaſon and <hi>common Senſe,</hi> will ſoon be judged of.</p>
               <p>Is there <hi>but one only God?</hi> Or if this be a <hi>Principle</hi> of too much Latitude, and capable of more Senſes: Is there more than one (numerical or ſelf-ſame) eternal and infinite Spirit? meaning by one eternal and infinite Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>one eternal and ſpiritual Subſtance, with one only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Will, and Power of Action.</hi> If it be agreed, as <hi>a Principle</hi> manifeſtly laid down in Scripture, as well as certain in Reaſon, that there is <hi>but one ſuch Spirit;</hi> either we ſhall all preſently accord, in inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting this famous Context of St. <hi>John,</hi> and other obſcure and doubtful Paſſages of Scripture: or our difference in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting <hi>it,</hi> or <hi>them,</hi> will no way af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect any Article of our Creed: ſo that there will be no real Controverſy left. The Unitarians are far from denying the Trinity of Divine Perſons, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of God, the Divinity or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of our Saviour; provided that thoſe Doctrines be interpreted to a Conſiſtency, with <hi>this Principle</hi> of Holy Scripture and of the Catholick Church, that <q>there is but one infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Spiritual Subſtance, with one only infinite Underſtanding, Will, and Energy.</q> Or more briefly, thus; <hi>but one infinite and eternal Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Either his Lordſhip ſays, there is but one ſuch Spirit; and therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprets the Term <hi>Perſons,</hi> and the Words <hi>Father, Son</hi> and <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> not to be ſo many diſtinct Spirits, but one Spirit diſtinguiſhed by three <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Properties;</hi> in explaining the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of which, the Church has always indulged ſome Variety and Latitude: and if ſo, we have no controverſy with him, nor he with us; and he may (for us) interpret the firſt of St. <hi>John,</hi> and the other Texts on which he inſiſts, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhall pleaſe. Or he ſaith, there are <hi>three</hi> eternal and infinite Spirits; and that the Divine Perſons are ſo many ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Subſtances, Minds, and Beings: and if ſo, we ſhall to our Power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Doctrine of Holy Scripture, and of ſo many General Councils, as have decreed the Doctrine of <hi>three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Subſtances and three infinite Spirits</hi> to be Hereſy. Let him therefore be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47056:16"/>
pleaſed to ſpeak out, and to declare himſelf categorically and explicitly; when we certainly know, what his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is, we promiſe to take into Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, not only what he has writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, but what he ſhall write, on the controverted Texts: till then, 'tis to no purpoſe to diſcuſs, what he has ſo generally and looſly diſcours'd; that we know not, whether he is for us, or againſt us. He cites, and inlarges on a great many Texts, to prove <hi>the Deity</hi> of our Saviour, <hi>his Pre-exiſtence,</hi> and his <hi>Incarnation:</hi> if he means only, that our Lord Chriſt is <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>did pre-exiſt,</hi> in reſpect of his Godhead, that is <hi>in reſpect of God in him,</hi> as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſpeak; and that God <hi>did inhabit</hi> after an extraordinary peculiar and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exampled manner in the human Nature of the Lord Chriſt, which the Church calls <hi>the Incarnation of God;</hi> the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians neither now, nor in any time paſt did queſtion any thing of this: they never intended to oppoſe the Churches Doctrine, but only the Hereſy of the Realiſts, <hi>viz.</hi> that an (imagined) <hi>Second</hi> Infinite and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Spirit, (for the Tritheiſts hold <hi>three</hi> ſuch Spirits) was incarnate in the Lord Chriſt: and that God is <hi>a Trinity of Spirits,</hi> not of <hi>Perſons,</hi> in the philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical and phyſical Senſe of the term <hi>Perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I meddle not therefore, with the reſt of his <hi>Lordſhip's</hi> Book: no not with the Diſcourſe concerning the <hi>little My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi> (as he fancies them to be) of the Tritheiſtick Scheme; and the <hi>great ones</hi> (as he repreſents them) of our Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem of Religion. For the Author of <hi>the Conſiderations,</hi> has ſo ſolidly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht what he ſaid on thoſe Subjects, in <hi>the Conſiderations</hi> themſelves: that there is no manner of Fear, that <hi>his Lordſhip's Bellows ſhould blow out the Sun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There follows a Letter of the Bp. of <hi>Sardis,</hi> to Dr. <hi>Williams,</hi> which we are next to conſider: and it will give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, more fully to diſcuſs all theſe great Points.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:47056:17"/>
            <head>PART II. In Anſwer to my Lord the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> Monſieur <hi>De Luzancy,</hi> and my Lord the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="discourse">
               <head>On the Letter of the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HIS Lordſhip through this whole Letter, writes like one extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly netled, very angry, and acted by a Spirit of Revenge. At length, the Cauſe of the great Offence he has taken, appears; at <hi>p.</hi> 98, 99. it is this. After having weighed what his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſays, in ſeveral Places of his Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Letter; concerning the Divinity, the Incarnation, and Satisfaction of our Saviour; <hi>the Conſiderer</hi> concludes with this: that <q>he ſubmits to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's whole Doctrine; which differs in nothing, from what the Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ever profeſſed, in all their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</q> His Lordſhip aſſures <hi>the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderer;</hi> that he takes this, as the heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all Imputations. And taking oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion at ſo great a Slander as (he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends) this is; he hath thought no Hardneſs of Expreſſion, and no Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation either ſo ſcandalous or ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, as to forbear it toward the <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer.</hi> Whether Cauſe was given by <hi>the Letter,</hi> to ſay, that the Doctrine of it, is perfectly Unitarian; I will now examine, by an Induction of what is there ſaid on the Points, in Controverſy between us and the Realiſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <head>The Doctrine of the Paſtoral Letter, concerning the Trinity.</head>
               <p>WHen we ſpeak of a Trinity, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body knows; the Queſtion is not, concerning the term <hi>Trinity,</hi> or <hi>three (divine) Perſons:</hi> but concerning what we ſhould mean by the word <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> or <hi>Trinity.</hi> If you make the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity (or <hi>three</hi> divine Perſons) to be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly three Attributes of God; Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and Power: as ſome do. Or if you ſay, they are only <hi>three ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Relations</hi> of God, to his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; <hi>viz.</hi> that he is their Creator, Redeemer, and Sanctifier: as others have taught, and were applauded alſo for it. Or if the three Perſons are called three relative Subſiſtences, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Modes, or Relations: which are not ſo many diſtinct Beings, Spirits,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47056:17"/>
or individual Subſtances; but only Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, or Affections of a Spirit, Being, or Subſtance; as generally they are named, and deſcribed. Or (if yet more particularly) they are <hi>original Mind, reflex Wiſdom,</hi> and the eternal <hi>Spiration of Divine Love;</hi> as ſome of the Fathers, and the Divines of the Schools, have affirmed. Or if Men will in effect ſay nothing at all, but only name them <hi>three ſomewhats;</hi> or <hi>the three,</hi> or the <hi>Holy three:</hi> which are Words without any certain Senſe. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, 'tis plain, there is no Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy with the Unitarians; for none of theſe Explications of a Trinity, are any way contrary to the Unity of God, as believed by them: they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves admit <hi>all,</hi> or <hi>any of</hi> theſe Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations. The Controverſy of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians, with ſome that are called Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians, but ſhould be called Trithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts, is this: <q>Whether, in ſaying <hi>three Divine Perſons,</hi> we ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend by the word <hi>Perſons,</hi> ſo many <hi>diſtinct Beings;</hi> three ſpiritual Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, in Number, tho called <hi>one Subſtance</hi> in reſpect of Sameneſs of Properties; three <hi>Minds,</hi> with ſo many diſtinct Underſtandings, Wills, and Powers of Action?</q> Or to ſay all this, in Words underſtood by all; <hi>three eternal and infinite Spirits?</hi> He that affirms, or denies, any of theſe; doth (therein, and thereby) affirm, or deny all the reſt. For inſtance, he that affirms three (diſtinct) Spiritual <hi>Beings,</hi> affirms three <hi>Minds,</hi> and three ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Subſtances</hi> diſtinct and divers in Number: and he that denies the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons are diſtinct <hi>Beings,</hi> denies alſo they are ſo many Minds, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, or Spirits. This is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted; therefore let us ſee, what kind of Trinity <hi>the Letter</hi> teaches: whether it doth not expreſly declare againſt that Trinity, which is denied and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Unitarians; and is the only Trinity, that it ever was in their Thoughts to oppoſe or deny?</p>
               <p>At <hi>p.</hi> 96. he ſays: <q>By <hi>Perſon,</hi> in theſe Queſtions, is not meant ſuch a Being, <hi>as is commonly underſtood by that word;</hi> namely, <hi>a compleat intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Being, diſtinct</hi> from every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Being.</q> He needs ſay no more; for if the Trinity of Divine <hi>Perſons</hi> are not ſuch <hi>Perſons,</hi> as are <hi>commonly</hi> meant and deſigned when we uſe the word <hi>Perſons;</hi> and if, as he farther adds, they are neither <hi>diſtinct,</hi> nor <hi>compleat,</hi> nor <hi>intelligent</hi> Beings: what Contentions ſoever he may affect to raiſe, with the Unitarians; they will never have any with him, concerning the Trinity. They oppoſe no other Trinity of Perſons, but ſuch as are cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter'd to be diſtinct, and compleat, and intelligent Beings; in a word, ſuch Perſons, as are <hi>commonly</hi> intended by the word Perſons: which Trinity, we ſee, his Lordſhip expreſly diſavows. And 'tis certain, that ſo alſo does the Catholick Church; eſpecially ſince the Lateran Council, <hi>Anno</hi> 1215.</p>
               <p>In very deed, to be a true Unitarian, he needed only to ſay; that the Divine Perſons are not three <hi>intelligent Beings,</hi> they are <hi>but one intelligent Being:</hi> for this being granted, the Unitarians have gained all they contend for; becauſe by but <hi>one Divine Perſon,</hi> they mean <hi>but one intelligent Being.</hi> But when his Lordſhip adds, the Divine Perſons are <hi>not diſtinct Beings;</hi> nor <hi>ſuch</hi> Perſons as we <hi>commonly mean,</hi> when we uſe the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47056:18"/>
word Perſons: it is evident, that his writing againſt the Unitarians was a mere Act of Zeal. He is now got con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably into the Intereſts of the Church; and that it may appear <hi>(to the Men of little Faith)</hi> that he is a Biſhop in Heart, as well as in Name: therefore he attacks, in one Book, all the Church's Enemies; without ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be informed, whether they are Enemies indeed, either to the Church, or to himſelf.</p>
               <p>Let us take another Paragraph, out of the (before-cited) Diſcourſe to the Clergy; which will farther evince his Lordſhip's Syncretiſm with the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians. <hi>Pag.</hi> 98, 99. <q>The Fathers in divers Places ſo expreſs themſelves, concerning the <hi>ſame Subſtance</hi> or Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, as if they meant <hi>the ſame Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in a general Senſe;</hi> even as all human Souls are of the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that is, are <hi>the ſame Order or ſort of Creatures.</hi> And they [the Fathers] ſeem to intitle the Divine Perſons, to <hi>different Operations;</hi> not only in the Oeconomical way, but ſo that one of them does that, which the other does not. This indeed was eaſily apprehended, but it ſeemed directly to aſſert three Gods; which is very contrary to the moſt expreſs Declarations, of the Old and New Teſtaments: in which, the Unity of God is ſo often held forth; that others took <hi>another way</hi> of explaining the Trinity, <hi>viz.</hi> by making their Foundation, that <hi>the Deity is one (numerical) Being.</hi> Theſe latter ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; that the <hi>Sun,</hi> beſides his own Globe, had an Emanation of <hi>Heat,</hi> and another of <hi>Light:</hi> which have <hi>different Operations,</hi> and all from the ſame Eſſence. Alſo that the Soul of Man hath <hi>Intellection,</hi> and <hi>Love;</hi> which flow from its <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</hi> So they conceived, that the <hi>primary Act</hi> of the Divine Eſſence, was its <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> by which it ſaw all things; and <hi>in</hi> which, as in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward WORD, it deſigned all things: this, they thought, might be called the <hi>Son,</hi> as being <hi>the Generation</hi> of the <hi>eternal Mind.</hi> While from that Fountain-Principle [eternal Mind] together with this inward WORD or Wiſdom, there did ariſe <hi>a Love,</hi> that was to <hi>iſſue forth,</hi> and was to be the Soul of the Creation; but more eſpecially to animate the Church. This was reſted on; and was afterwards dreſſed up, with a great deal of dark Nicety, by the Schools: nay, it grew to be <hi>the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally-received Opinion.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Is this he, that writes againſt the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians; and has no better Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for 'em, but <hi>irreligious profligate Villains?</hi> The World knows, what the Doctrine of the Unitarians, is; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>the Deity is one (numerical) Being;</hi> one Subſtance (not as ſome of the Fathers, who are therefore blamed by his Lordſhip, ſaid, <hi>one Subſtance on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a general Senſe,</hi> but) in Number, with one only Underſtanding, Will, and Power of Action: and this is what they call <hi>one Perſon;</hi> they deny the Deity to be three Perſons in no other Senſe, but of three numerical intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Subſtances. What now does his Lordſhip ſay? Why, that ſome of the Fathers indeed thought otherwiſe; they took the Deity to be three ſuch Perſons, that they are three (ſpiritual intelligent) Subſtances, not indeed for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47056:18"/>
                  <hi>ſort</hi> or <hi>kind,</hi> but in Number, three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct <hi>Beings</hi> that have <hi>different Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> but, ſaith his Lordſhip, 'tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the moſt expreſs Declarations, of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Teſtaments. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he ſaith; <hi>the univerſally received Explanation</hi> of the Trinity, and which is the Explication of the Divines of the Schools, is; that from <hi>eternal Mind,</hi> as a Fountain-Principle, have proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Love: Wiſdom</hi> is the firſt Act of <hi>Mind;</hi> and being as it were generated by Mind, is therefore called <hi>the Son.</hi> So that eternal <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Mind,</hi> the immanent Act of <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> generated thereby, and the <hi>iſſuing forth</hi> (or Spiration) of Divine <hi>Love,</hi> are by his Lordſhip's expreſs Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what the Divines of the Schools (after St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and other Fathers) have called the Trinity of Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. Nay, this is <hi>the univerſally-received Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> of the Trinity. But did the <hi>irreligious Villains</hi> ever oppoſe this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, univerſally (as his Lordſhip ſays) received? Do they deny eternal origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Mind;</hi> the everlaſting immanent Act of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> generated by it; or the perpetual Spiration of <hi>Divine Love,</hi> proceeding from original Mind, and the inward <hi>Logos</hi> or Wiſdom? He knows the contrary; he knows we are Brethren: for I hope, that himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves <hi>the univerſally-received Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> But then, why are we out of his Favour? why <hi>irreligious Villains,</hi> againſt whom and their Doctrine, 'tis ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to caution and inſtruct the (poor ignorant) Clergy of the Dioceſs of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisbury?</hi> The Queſtion, I doubt, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be anſwered; but by ſaying: here his (freſh) Epiſcopal Zeal, for Holy Mother Church, in the Intereſts of which he is got to be a conſiderable Part, was by much too forward. As Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> who is <hi>a Socinian and an half,</hi> could publiſh I know not how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Letters, and Sermons, againſt the Socinians; aſperſing alſo (in the moſt bitter, and falſe manner) the very Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Patriarch <hi>Socinus:</hi> So his Lordſhip, not expecting to be rightly informed of their Doctrine and Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, calls thoſe <hi>irreligious Villains,</hi> who hold and maintain <hi>the univerſally-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Explication;</hi> and profeſſes to take it as <hi>the very heavieſt of all Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations,</hi> when <hi>the Conſiderer</hi> ſaid, in Terms of Reſpect, <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to his Lordſhip's Doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Methinks, no Man ever had leſs Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion given him, to anſwer ſo unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly, I had almoſt ſaid inhumanly, as his Lordſhip has done. It is eaſy to ſee, in the Air and Spirit of his Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; that <hi>the Conſiderer</hi> (had he not affected the contrary) could have choſe ſuch Expreſſions and Terms, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Lordſhip's Doctrine; as ſhould have wakened, and drawn down upon him, all the Enemies he has in the World. The leaſt of thoſe many things, that a Perſon ſo well verſed in theſe Queſtions, as <hi>the Conſiderer</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be, could have ſaid; the leaſt and ſofteſt of his Imputations, might have been this: that his Lordſhip is not ſo Catholick, or Orthodox, in any of theſe (depending) Queſtions; as the Unitarians are. But let us go on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:47056:19"/>
               <head>On the Account, given in the Letter, of the Incarnation, and Divinity of our Saviour.</head>
               <p>COncerning the Trinity of Divine Perſons, his Lordſhip (we have ſeen) believes; they are not <hi>compleat,</hi> nor <hi>diſtinct</hi> Beings; nor <hi>ſuch</hi> Perſons as are <hi>commonly meant,</hi> when we uſe the term Perſons: we were beſt, he ſaith, to call them in general terms, <hi>the three,</hi> or <hi>the bleſſed three;</hi> and thereby ſilence all Oppoſition and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute. And for the term <hi>Son,</hi> he inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates at <hi>p.</hi> 99. <q>it doth not belong at all to any of <hi>the three;</hi> but only to our Saviour as he was the Meſſias.</q> That is, as he was the <hi>Man</hi> Jeſus. <hi>And hereby,</hi> he ſays again, <hi>all the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations concerning an eternal Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are cut off.</hi> This he ſays at <hi>p.</hi> 100. Agreeably to this (as I ſaid, <hi>more than <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian Doctrine,</hi> for the Unitarians allow the <hi>eternal Generation</hi> of the <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos, Son,</hi> or Wiſdom) he explains alſo the Incarnation, or Divinity of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. He makes the Incarnation of God in the human Nature, to be <hi>ſuch,</hi> and to have <hi>like</hi> Effects; as God's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting the <hi>Cloud of Glory,</hi> during ſome part of the Old-Teſtament Ages: for this Cloud was worſhipped, he ſaith; and he might have added, is called God, becauſe of God in it. But in <hi>his Letter,</hi> he contends; that the Indwelling of the Godhead in Chriſt, was a <hi>vital Indwelling,</hi> like that of the Soul in the Body; and not an <hi>aſſiſting Indwelling,</hi> like that of Inſpiration, or the Gift of Tongues, or of Miracles. This muſt be candidly interpreted, or it is the <hi>Apollinarian Hereſy;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in ſo many General Councils: but I am perſwaded, he meant no He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terodoxy by a <hi>vital Indwelling.</hi> He meant not, that the Humanity <hi>lives,</hi> by its Union with the Divinity; which was the Doctrine of <hi>Apollinaris:</hi> he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends only, that <q>the Humanity of the Lord Chriſt is <hi>entirely</hi> under the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and Conduct of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling Divinity; and receives <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Communications</hi> of Light, and Impulſe, from it.</q> So I find him ſpeaking at <hi>p.</hi> 107. And in the next Page, thus; <q>The eternal WORD aſſumed the <hi>Man</hi> into an inward Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomy; ſo as <hi>always</hi> to illuminate, conduct, and actuate it. This is the cleareſt Thought, we can have, of the human Nature's ſubſiſting by the Subſiſtence of the WORD; that is, of the Incarnation, or Hypoſtatical Union.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This is far enough, to be Orthodox: but the Unitarians believe ſomewhat more; they are a degree or two more Catholick and Orthodox. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve indeed, with his Lordſhip, not only that God did <hi>inſpire</hi> our Saviour; or ſo far communicated himſelf, that the Lord Chriſt wrought Miracles by the Virtue that was <hi>always</hi> in him, and not by a Power beſtowed only occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and incidentally: but that our Saviour's Humanity was <hi>conſtantly</hi> illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, conducted, and actuated by God in him; and had <hi>unfading</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications of Light, and Impulſe, from the Divinity; he was <hi>entirely</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47056:19"/>
the Impreſſions and Conduct there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Yet, as his Lordſhip alſo adds at <hi>p.</hi> 107. <q>ſtill leaving to the inferiour Mind [to the rational Soul of Chriſt] <hi>its own Liberty,</hi> and all its natural Powers.</q> And we reflect alſo on it; that 'tis with much more Juſtice and Propriety, that our Saviour is called God, on the account of ſuch Indwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God: than <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>Solomon,</hi> or even than Angels themſelves; who can be called <hi>Gods</hi> but only <hi>by Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation,</hi> or at moſt on the account of God's <hi>aſſiſting,</hi> and <hi>inſpiring</hi> them, as occaſion hapned to require. But the Unitarians, as I ſaid, believe ſomewhat more. They do not appropriate the Incarnation, to merely the WORD. They hold, that the <hi>whole</hi> Deity (or Godhead) dwelt in our Saviour; <hi>all the Fulneſs of the Godhead,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, and not only the WORD, <hi>dwelt in him bodily:</hi> Not that the whole Eſſence of the Infinite God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came commenſurate to a finite Man; or that there followed hereupon <hi>a real Communication of Idioms,</hi> as ſome have (heretically) conceited, which is in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deed a Revival of Eutychianiſm: but only as <hi>God is every where whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he is;</hi> he is God, perfect God, in one Place, in any <hi>Point</hi> of Space, no leſs than in the whole interminable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion of Place or Space.</p>
               <p>This being the Unitarian Doctrine concerning the Incarnation, hypoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or perſonal Union, and Divinity of our Saviour; always believed, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by 'em: his Lordſhip had no Reaſon, to ſnatch at ſo many Occaſions of venting his Choler on <hi>the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer;</hi> as if he were in danger of loſing his Biſhoprick, by occaſion of the Growth of Unitarianiſm; which he miſtakes to be a Departure, from the Doctrine of the Catholick Church; when 'tis nothing but an Oppoſition, to the Hereſy of the <hi>Realiſts.</hi> Of which this Prelate has made it appear, he has not the leaſt Tang.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <head>Of the Satisfaction, as 'tis ſtated in the Letter.</head>
               <p>THE Unitarians differ ſomewhat, from ſome other Catholicks, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining the Doctrine of the Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but they approve of his Lordſhip's Notions, concerning that Subject. There are two Accounts, given of the Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. One of them ſuppoſes; there was a Neceſſity, that an adequate Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction ſhould be made, to the Juſtice of God, for the Sins of Men: and that otherwiſe, God could not diſmiſs us of the perſonal Puniſhment, due by the Divine Law to our Sins. The other ſuppoſes; there was no Neceſſity, of an adequate Satisfaction, on our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half: there being no ſuch <hi>vindictive Juſtice,</hi> eſſential to God; whereby he is obliged to puniſh, unleſs a full Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction be given for Offences and Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. The greater Number of the more learned Catholicks, whether they be Proteſtants or Romaniſts, hold the latter of theſe; as well as the Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do: they believe, <q>It was neither neceſſary, nor (perhaps) poſſible; that a Satisfaction ſhould be given to the Divine Juſtice, every way equal to the eternal Puniſhment, of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47056:20"/>
Number of Sinners.</q> As my Lord of <hi>Sarum</hi> argues, at <hi>p.</hi> 35. <q>The Acts of Chriſt, tho infinite in Value, have not a ſtrict Equality; with <hi>all</hi> the Sins of ſo many Men, every one of which is of infinite Guilt.</q> He confeſſes hereby, that an adequate Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction was not only, not neceſſary; but not poſſible in the nature of the thing: unleſs there had been as many Redeemers, not only as there are Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but as there are Sins.</p>
               <p>But let us conſider, yet more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, what his Lordſhip's Doctrine is.</p>
               <p>He ſaith: <q>The Lord Chriſt was loaded with all the ill Uſage, that malicious Men could invent; he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd inexpreſſible Agonies, both in Body and Mind; and laſt of all, was crucified. But in all this, he willingly offer'd himſelf, to ſuffer <hi>upon our Account,</hi> and <hi>in our ſtead:</hi> which was <hi>ſo accepted by God,</hi> that he not only raiſed him from the Dead, and exalted him on High; but gave to him, even <hi>as he is Man, all Power both in Heaven and Earth,</hi> and offers alſo to the World Pardon of Sin.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Of this Account of <hi>the Satisfaction, the Conſiderer</hi> ſaid; the Unitarians have ever profeſſed it. His Lordſhip (in <hi>the Letter</hi>) replies; that the Racovian Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, and the firſt Writers of the Socinians, expreſly deny <hi>the expiatory Virtue</hi> of the Sacrifice of Chriſt, on the Croſs: but he owns, that ſome Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are come off from that Error, and do own <hi>the expiatory Virtue</hi> of that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. He adds; that Dr. <hi>Outram</hi>'s learned Performance on this Subject, is univerſally applauded and acquieſced in: and all, he ſaith, may be ſatisfied by Dr. <hi>Outram</hi>'s Book, what is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine generally received in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But as to the poor Wretch <hi>the Conſiderer,</hi> he is a Stranger, his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> pronounces, to the Hiſtory of this Controverſy.</p>
               <p>His Lordſhip frequently diſcovers his great Paſſion for <hi>the Conſiderer,</hi> often beſtows on him his (formed) Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and this particular Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I ſuppoſe, has the Property of moſt other Compliments; that is to ſay, the Speaker knows 'tis more than meaſure while he gives it for juſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. I ſhall leave him, and <hi>the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer,</hi> to their Monſigneuriſms; and anſwer to the thing it ſelf. Whereas he ſays, the Racovian Catechiſm de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the <hi>expiatory Virtue</hi> of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt: 'tis ſo far from being true, that this Catechiſm calls the Death and Oblation of Chriſt, on the Croſs, <hi>Sacrificium piaculare,</hi> an expiatory Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. As for the firſt Writers of the Socinians; whom alſo his Lordſhip ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, as denying that the Sacrifice of Chriſt was expiatory: thoſe firſt Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, he may pleaſe to know, were the very Authors of the Racovian Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm. This Catechiſm, which is an Abridgment and Defence of the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Doctrine, was firſt written by <hi>Smalcius,</hi> and other firſt Writers and Preachers among the Socinians; and has been improved by continual Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, till laſt of all it was publiſhed about 16 Years ſince by <hi>Benedict Wiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>watius,</hi> with the Annotations of all the moſt conſiderable Writers of the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian way.</p>
               <p>But the Unitarians muſt needs be glad, to hear his Lordſhip, who ſo well underſtands the Hiſtory of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47056:20"/>
refer us to Dr. <hi>Outram</hi>'s Book; as an applauded and generally-received Performance, and containing the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> concerning the Sacrifice of Chriſt. For the Explication of the Doctrine of <hi>the Satisfaction,</hi> firſt hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Grotius</hi> in his Notes on his Books, <hi>de Jure Belli &amp; Pacis,</hi> and (again) on the New Teſtament; and more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly explained by <hi>Ruarus</hi> and <hi>Sclichtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> in their Epiſtles: I ſay, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Doctrine of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, by theſe leading Unitarians, is ſo plainly aſſerted, and ſo fully vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated by Dr. <hi>Outram;</hi> that 'tis good News, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> (as his Lordſhip, and I believe very truly, aſſures us) doth not only univerſally receive, but applaud it. Dr. <hi>Outram</hi> was as much an Unitarian, in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Trinity, the Incarnation, and the Satisfaction, as the Compilers of the Racovian Catechiſm: but to eſtabliſh his Doctrine, he ſaw it was neceſſary, to ſet it on another Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; and to expreſs it in other Terms, than <hi>Socinus</hi> and <hi>Crellius</hi> had done. He no more believed, that the Oblation of the Lord Chriſt on the Croſs, was an <hi>adequate</hi> Satisfaction to God's <hi>Juſtice,</hi> for the Sins of Men; than even <hi>Socinus,</hi> or <hi>Crellius,</hi> did. Tho he contends that the Lord Chriſt underwent <hi>poenam vicariam,</hi> i. e. a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment <hi>in our ſtead;</hi> which Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as it is intended by the more rigid Calviniſts, was diſliked and oppoſed by <hi>Socinus</hi> and <hi>Crellius;</hi> yet it never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd into his mind, that Chriſt <hi>ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in our ſtead, as to be conſider'd by God as having our Guilt,</hi> or as undergo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>a Puniſhment equivalent thereto.</hi> On which two Points (and not on the Words <hi>in our ſtead,</hi> as his Lordſhip imagines) our whole Controverſy with ſome others, eſpecially the Calviniſt Writers, turns.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, his Lordſhip, Dr. <hi>Outram,</hi> and other Catholick Writers who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove not the Notions of ſome School-Divines, and ſome rigid Calviniſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve neither more nor leſs concerning the Sacrifice by the Lord Chriſt; than the Men of the Racovian way do. All <hi>theſe</hi> (alike) conſider our Saviour, as well in the Sufferings of his whole Life, and in his extraordinary Agonies in the Garden, as in his Paſſion on the Croſs, as ſuffering <hi>for us,</hi> and <hi>in our ſtead:</hi> his Life and Death had <hi>both</hi> of 'em the expiatory Virtue, which his Lordſhip thinks the Unitarians deny of <hi>both.</hi> And all theſe no leſs agree, againſt ſome Calviniſts, and divers Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians who follow <hi>the Schools;</hi> that the Oblation made by Chriſt was not an <hi>adequate Satisfaction,</hi> to God's <hi>Juſtice,</hi> it was rather an Application to his <hi>Mercy.</hi> They agree, he did not <hi>ſo</hi> ſuffer, in our ſtead; as to take on him <hi>our Guilt,</hi> or to undergo <hi>a Puniſhment equivalent to our Sins:</hi> no nor to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go Puniſhment <hi>properly ſo called;</hi> but only in a popular Senſe of the Word Puniſhment. For Puniſhment properly ſo called, <q>is the Evil of Suffering, inflicted on a guilty Perſon, for the evil of doing: but the Lord Chriſt having <hi>done no Evil,</hi> nor being in any Senſe <hi>a guilty Perſon;</hi> he cannot <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly</hi> be ſaid to be puniſht, but to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</q> And for the Suffering <hi>in our ſtead,</hi> this alſo is rather tolerable and paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than proper; but it may be well admitted in this Senſe, which is the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47056:21"/>
Senſe of the Catholick Church, <hi>viz.</hi> that <q>If the Lord Chriſt had not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; we (the actual Offenders) ſhould have been puniſht.</q> Briefly, his Lordſhip has imagin'd a Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, where there is really none: and while he is a Catholick, he muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue an Unitarian.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <head>In Anſwer to the Four Letters, by Mr. <hi>H. De Luzancy. To the Publiſher.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have read the 4 Letters of Mr. <hi>De Luzancy,</hi> againſt the Unitarians; and as you deſire, will make ſome Anſwer to them.</p>
               <p>His Preface makes two Attacks; tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, 1. The Conſent of <hi>the whole Chriſtian World,</hi> muſt be a ſtrong In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement to a modeſt Unitarian; to miſtruſt all his Arguments. To op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all that has been, or <hi>is great and good in the Church of God,</hi> is too much for the moſt preſuming Diſputant.</p>
               <p>The Caſe then, as Mr. <hi>L.</hi> ſtates it, is; one ſide has Argument, the other has Authority or Number. The Side or Party that has nothing but Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ought not to preſume on their Reaſons; againſt the Authority of <hi>the whole World:</hi> or as he corrects himſelf, upon ſecond Thoughts; all that is <hi>great and good in the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Mr. <hi>L.</hi> has no better way, of deciding theſe Controverſies; how do I fear, they will never be ended. The Unitarians will ſurely deny, that <hi>all the Chriſtian World,</hi> or ſo much as all that is <hi>great and good in the Church,</hi> is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: they will pretend that themſelves are a part of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World;</hi> and for <hi>great and good</hi> they need not to ſay it of themſelves, the Ableſt of their <hi>great and good</hi> Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers have often ſaid it of them. They will ſay farther; that in a Claſh between <hi>Argument,</hi> and <hi>Number;</hi> the whole <hi>World,</hi> and <hi>all that is great</hi> in it, when weighed againſt but one Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is, as if you had put nothing at all into the Scale: they will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abide by it, that Argument can be repelled by nothing but Argument; as Diamonds are cut, only by Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds.</p>
               <p>I adviſe Mr. <hi>L.</hi> who urges againſt us <hi>all the World;</hi> to conſider a little of this Paſſage, which he will find in a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, in the 2d Tome of the Works of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> 
                  <q>They are to be pitied, who judg of a Doctrine, by <hi>the numbers</hi> of thoſe who profeſs it. <hi>Phineas, Lot, Noah,</hi> St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> had the Multitude againſt 'em; yet what honeſt Man would not rather be of their ſide, than of <hi>the World's?</hi> —When you object to me, Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; you do but ſhow <hi>the great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Wickedneſs,</hi> and the <hi>great number of the Miſerable.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. His next Blow is; that, <q>Faith and Reaſon are two things: what is the Object of Faith, cannot be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:47056:21"/>
the Object of Reaſon. Nor is it ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to reject <hi>the Belief</hi> of <hi>the Myſteries</hi> of the Trinity and Incarnation; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>our narrow and corrupted Reaſon</hi> ſtarts <hi>Contradictions,</hi> in a Subject ſo much above our Capacities. It looks indeed like Charity, but is certainly an Inadvertence, to anſwer the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians in their own Way: that is, to run with them upon the ſame <hi>falſe Scent,</hi> of <hi>reaſoning on things,</hi> which we ought to believe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But in very Deed are Faith and Reaſon two things; ſo that what is the Object of Faith, cannot be the Object of Reaſon; as Mr. <hi>L.</hi> here affirms? I had thought <hi>Faith</hi> had been nothing elſe, but <q>
                     <hi>an Aſſent</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Propoſitions or Facts, upon <hi>reaſonable Proof</hi> made of them.</q> And when the Apoſtle defines <hi>Faith</hi> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Proof or <hi>Demonſtration</hi> (or, as our Tranſlation has it, <hi>the Evidence) of things not ſeen:</hi> he teaches, not only that the Object of Faith and of Reaſon is the ſame; but that there cannot be Faith without Reaſon; and that, <hi>Faith is the Product of Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſurely a very raſh Propoſition, that <q>what is the Object of Faith, cannot be the Object of <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
                  </q> For hath Faith no other Objects, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unintelligible <hi>Myſteries,</hi> or flat <hi>Non-ſenſe?</hi> All other things are the proper Objects of <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſhort of what Mr. <hi>L.</hi> advances, is; the Trinity and Incarnation are <hi>Scripture-Myſteries:</hi> therefore if a thouſand <hi>Contradictions</hi> be implied in the Belief of them; yet we muſt believe them, on the Authority of Scripture.</p>
               <p>It is certain to me, this learned Gentleman does not believe, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this looſe Scheme. I crave leave, to ask him a few Queſtions.</p>
               <p>Would he himſelf believe <hi>a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory Propoſition,</hi> or that ſo ſeemed to <hi>his</hi> Reaſon; if he found it taught in Scripture? Would he believe, that <hi>One and Two are not Three,</hi> if the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaid it? Why does he calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Reaſon, the Light ſet up in us by God himſelf; under the Names of <hi>nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> and <hi>corrupted;</hi> when he himſelf would make this ſame narrow and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Reaſon the Supream and laſt Judg of any Propoſition, that ſeemed to him <hi>plainly contradictory,</hi> or <hi>flatly impoſſible?</hi> Is there one Law for <hi>him,</hi> and another for the Unitarians? Are the Unitarians obliged to believe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, while Mr. <hi>L.</hi> is exempt from that (abſurd and impracticable) Law? Mr. <hi>L.</hi> may pretend what he pleaſes, upon hope that we cannot look into the Receſſes of his Heart; but I will not accept any Man's <hi>Oath</hi> for it, that he would aſſent to a Propoſition or Doctrine that ſeemed to him <hi>a flat Contradiction,</hi> if it were affirmed in Scripture. But if <hi>ſo;</hi> if neither Mr. <hi>L.</hi> nor any Man elſe, will believe a Doctrine that ſeems to <hi>him</hi> to be <hi>plainly Contradictory:</hi> it follows that the Unitarians rightly require, that the Contradictions they find in the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Belief of a Trinity, as 'tis ſtated by <hi>the Realiſts,</hi> be (tolerably) ſatisfied; and that <hi>to reaſon upon theſe Queſtions,</hi> is not (as Mr. <hi>L.</hi> pretends) <hi>to run upon a falſe Scent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This therefore is the firſt Queſtion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:47056:22"/>
that I deſire Mr. <hi>L.</hi> to reſolve; <hi>will he</hi> believe a Doctrine, that ſeems to him to imply <hi>manifeſt and inconteſtable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions,</hi> if ſuch Doctrine or Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition were indeed found in Scripture? Would he not ſay, that to eſtabliſh the Credibility of any <hi>Record</hi> or <hi>Book,</hi> theſe two Qualifications are equally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite: that it hath the external At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, of <hi>ſufficient Witneſſes</hi> to it; and the internal, of being <hi>conſiſtent with it ſelf, and to confeſt and indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Truths;</hi> that is, that it be free from Contradictions and Impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? If this, or ſuch like, is the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer he would make, he muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, to argue theſe Queſtions about the Trinity and Incarnation; not from Scripture only, but from Reaſon alſo: nay, from Reaſon chiefly, and ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I ask, again; if Mr. <hi>L.</hi> will believe what ſeems to his Reaſon, a flat Contradiction, ſuppoſing it to be found in Scripture: yet does he adviſe us to believe <hi>clear Contradictions,</hi> that are <hi>not clearly revealed in Scripture?</hi> Three infinite and eternal <hi>Spirits,</hi> each of them (ſingly; and by himſelf) a moſt perfect God, and yet all of them (together) but one God; this ſeems to me, a moſt <hi>clear Contradiction:</hi> am I bound to believe it, if 'tis not <hi>as clearly and inconteſtably revealed,</hi> as 'tis <hi>inconteſtably and clearly a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whatever Mr. <hi>L.</hi> may think fit to anſwer here, I judg that moſt People will be of Opinion; that the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation for it ought to be moſt clear: ſo clear, that a fair and ingenuous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner will not conteſt the <hi>Poſitiveneſs</hi> and <hi>Evidence</hi> of the Revelation. But now the Texts, and Contexts, that are alledged, to prove <hi>three eternal and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Spirits,</hi> each of them <hi>a perfect God,</hi> are clogged (Mr. <hi>L.</hi> knows) with <hi>abundance of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainties.</hi> 'Tis deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (he knows) with great Vehemence; by the ableſt Criticks of the Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Perſwaſion, that ſome of theſe Texts were originally ſo read, as they are now publiſhed in our common Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; nay ſome of them were not read at all, in any Bible, till 5 or 600 Years after the Deceaſe of the Apoſtles, and other ſacred Penmen. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>antiently</hi> read, or <hi>thus</hi> read, yea or no; there is <hi>none</hi> of them but is moſt fairly capable of a Senſe, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent with the Unity of God, as 'tis taught by the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> and <hi>Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals,</hi> and is actually ſo interpreted by divers of the moſt allowed and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Interpreters of the Church. Who ſees not here, that to introduce and believe <hi>Monſtroſities,</hi> on ſuch a craz'd Foundation as this; is to give up common Senſe, without a tolerable Cauſe for it: whenas indeed there can be no Cauſe ſo great, as may induce us to part with it? 'Tis to admit, and defend <hi>Contradictions,</hi> and that in a <hi>capital Article</hi> of Religion; when we need not: 'tis to ſacrifice the cleareſt, and moſt important dictates of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; not to any Neceſſity, but to our ſecular Intereſts, or our Wantonneſs. From which, for my part, I deſire to be ever clear.</p>
               <p>Again, I would know of Mr. <hi>L.</hi> who ſo deſpiſes <hi>(thoſe poor Trifles)</hi> Contradictions, and Impoſſibilities; and thinks them to be no Blemiſhes to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:47056:22"/>
Religion, nor any Hindrances of Faith: whether, in ſober Sadneſs, he believes, that <hi>a contradictory,</hi> either Propoſition, or Doctrine, <hi>can</hi> be true? It ſeems to me, that <hi>what is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory, is impoſſible:</hi> and 'tis agreed, I think, by Divines of all Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; that Impoſſibilities and Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions (whether they be Propoſitions or Facts) cannot be verified, by the Divine Omnipotence it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>If a Doctrine or Propoſition, that conſiſts of <hi>contradictory</hi> Parts; ſuch as, three infinite Spirits, each of which is a perfect God, and all of them but one God; can be true: there will be no ſuch thing as <hi>Falſhood.</hi>
                  </q> For we therefore ſay, ſuch a Doctrine or Propoſition is <hi>falſe;</hi> either becauſe 'tis an abſolute Nullity; or becauſe we perceive, that the Parts of it <hi>contradict</hi> one another, or they <hi>contradict</hi> ſome other Propoſition or Doctrine, that is a certain and agreed <hi>Truth.</hi> If once 'tis granted, that two Truths may <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict</hi> one another; or what is the ſame, that contradictory Propoſitions or Doctrines may be both of 'em <hi>true;</hi> when ſhall any Propoſition (but a mere Nullity) be yielded to be <hi>falſe?</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as I ſaid) <hi>Falſhood</hi> is nothing elſe, but a Contradiction to what is <hi>true.</hi> And if Propoſitions that imply Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions to one another, may yet both of them be true; they muſt both be true, while they are alſo both falſe: for while they contradict one another, and yet both of them are true; each denies the other to be true.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, I intreat Mr. <hi>L.</hi> to anſwer; <hi>would he</hi> believe a Doctrine ſaid to be revealed in Scripture, which Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Doctrine himſelf judged to be <hi>a clear and certain Contradiction?</hi> Or if he would, yet are <hi>clear and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Contradictions</hi> to be believed, that are <hi>not clearly and inconteſtably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed;</hi> but are founded on Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of very <hi>diſputable Credit and Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and moſt <hi>uncertain Senſe;</hi> in the Judgment of ſome of the ableſt (Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox) Criticks and Interpreters? And laſtly, <hi>can</hi> a Doctrine, conſiſting of <hi>contradictory Parts,</hi> be true? is it Truth, or is it Falſhood, that contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts certain Truth?</p>
               <p>I would not have Mr. <hi>L.</hi> to hope, he may elude the firſt and laſt of theſe Queſtions; by ſaying: that <hi>real</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, or Doctrines that conſiſt of Propoſitions <hi>really</hi> contradictory, cannot be true; but it may happen, that what ſhall ſeem to us, to our <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted</hi> and <hi>narrow</hi> Reaſon, a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, is not <hi>ſo.</hi> As for Inſtance, three eternal Spirits, each (ſingly, and by himſelf) a perfect God, and all of them (together) but one God; ſeems indeed a Contradiction, to our <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted</hi> Reaſon, but is therefore not a <hi>real</hi> Contradiction, becauſe 'tis reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Word of God.</p>
               <p>For, 1. He ſays, <q>
                     <hi>Three infinite Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> each of them <hi>a God,</hi> are all of them but one God: This is no <hi>real</hi> Contradiction; becauſe 'tis found in Holy Scripture.</q> Suppoſe now, he ſhould alſo ſay; <q>
                     <hi>Three finite Spirits,</hi> each of them <hi>an Angel,</hi> are all of them but one Angel.</q> Is it not a Contradiction, in what Book ſoever Mr. <hi>L.</hi> may pretend to diſcover it? If this latter is a <hi>real</hi> Contradiction, ſo (of neceſſity) is the former: becauſe the two Propoſitions, as to <hi>the formal Reaſon of them,</hi> are identically the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47056:23"/>
ſame; they differ only <hi>in their Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> One is falſly affirmed of God; the other, not more falſly, affirmed of an Angel: but the thing that makes them to be falſe, every one ſees, is this; that concerning one and the <hi>ſame Subject,</hi> we affirm <hi>different Numbers,</hi> one and three. 2. Mr. <hi>L</hi>'s only Eluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to ſo much ſound Senſe as the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians object to him, is; that human Reaſon is <hi>narrow</hi> and <hi>corrupt:</hi> and therefore we muſt not make it a Judg, of what is revealed in Scripture; but ſilently adore and believe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, notwithſtanding all the idle Clat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter made by Reaſon, concerning Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions and Impoſſibilities. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt;</hi> If the Queſtion were, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſomething that is <hi>expreſly</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in Holy Scripture; it might be plauſibly alledged, that our <hi>narrow</hi> and (as Mr. <hi>L.</hi> pretends) <hi>corrupted</hi> Reaſon ſhould ſilently ſubmit, to the Revelation of God, infinitely wiſe. If it were ſaid in <hi>expreſs Terms,</hi> 
                  <q>There are three eternal infinite Spirits; and tho each of them is a perfect God, yet all of them are but one God; Mr. <hi>L.</hi> might colourably object the <hi>Narrowneſs</hi> of the human Reaſon, when Men offer'd to reject the expreſs Declaration of God, as if it implied ſome obvious Contradictions.</q> But the caſe is otherwiſe; it is this:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Some People require us to believe, there are three infinite Spirits, <hi>each</hi> of them a God, and <hi>all</hi> of them but one God.</q> It ſeems to us, a Belief <hi>contradictory to it ſelf;</hi> and inconſiſtent with the <hi>numerical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of God, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered every where in Scripture. To the firſt part of this Exception, that the Belief propounded to us by ſome that (falſly) call themſelves the Church, is <hi>contradictory to it ſelf;</hi> Mr. <hi>L.</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers: No Matter for that; for the human Reaſon is <hi>narrow</hi> and <hi>corrupted,</hi> and therefore muſt not be allowed to judg of what God has revealed to us, in his Word. We challenge this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of Mr. <hi>L.</hi> and others, of mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Impertinence; becauſe it ſuppoſes that we pretend to charge with Self-contradiction a Revelation or <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God,</hi> and that we reaſon againſt ſomething delivered <hi>expreſly</hi> in Holy Scripture, which is the Word of God. If Mr. <hi>L.</hi> could ſhow us the Belief he exacts of us, ſet down in <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs</hi> Words, in the Word of God; his Anſwer were juſt, and to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: but ſeeing it is confeſſed to be only <hi>an Inference,</hi> that ſome Men draw from Scripture, Mr. <hi>L.</hi> in vain inſiſts on <hi>the Narrowneſs</hi> or <hi>Corruption</hi> of the human Reaſon, by occaſion of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying what is only <hi>an Inference</hi> from Scripture. I do not think he will ſay, that the Reaſon of the Unitarians is narrower or more corrupt than their Neighbours; if not, what Trifling is it, to urge the Narrowneſs or Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the human Reaſon: for if Mens Reaſon, being ſo narrow and corrupt as Mr. <hi>L.</hi> pretends, is not to be truſted in judging of, or arguing upon a Divine Revelation; may it not be as fallible in <hi>drawing Inferences</hi> from Scripture, as in <hi>judging the Conſiſtency or the Self-Contradiction of thoſe Inferences?</hi> Brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, let Mr. <hi>L.</hi> ſhow me theſe Words in Scripture; <q>There are three eternal and infinite Spirits: <hi>And again, theſe Words;</hi> three infinite Spirits, each of which is perfect God, yet all of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:47056:23"/>
them but one God.</q> He will ſay, he cannot ſhow me theſe very Words; but there are in Scripture other Words, from whence thoſe Propoſitions may <hi>be rightly inferred:</hi> and the human Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is too corrupted and narrow; that it may be ſet up as a Judg, of what is delivered in the Word of God; whatſoever Contradictions or Self-Contradictions Reaſon pretends to find in the Doctrines of Scripture, it is too fallible (becauſe 'tis both <hi>narrow,</hi> and <hi>corrupted</hi>) to be heard againſt the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom of God, ſpeaking in his Word. We reply; let the human Reaſon be as corrupted and narrow as Mr. <hi>L.</hi> and others fancy it to be: yet ſtill it will be as able and fit to judg, of the Conſiſtency, or Self-Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, of Doctrines or Propoſitions not <hi>expreſly</hi> contained in Scripture, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>inferred by Reaſon,</hi> from Scripture; as it is <hi>to infer</hi> or draw thoſe Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Doctrines from Scripture. If Reaſon may not be truſted, to judg of Doctrines that are but only <hi>Mens In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences from Scripture;</hi> it can as little be truſted, to frame or draw thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences from Scripture: its Narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Corruption muſt be diſtruſted, as much in the one caſe, as in the other. If Mr. <hi>L.</hi> hopes to ſet aſide the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, that Reaſon finds in this Creed, <hi>there are three infinite Spirits,</hi> &amp;c. we claim it as our Right, to ſet aſide that Creed, becauſe 'tis only <hi>an Inference</hi> drawn from Scripture, by the human Reaſon, which is altogether <hi>corrupted</hi> (he ſaith) and extremely <hi>narrow.</hi> Does Mr. <hi>L.</hi> deny, that the Contradictions we find in this Inference which ſome make from Scripture, <q>There are three infinite Spirits, each of them a perfect God, all of them but one God; are <hi>real</hi> Contradictions, to the human Reaſon as we <hi>now</hi> have it?</q> No; but he ſays, our Reaſon, becauſe 'tis ſo <hi>narrow</hi> and <hi>corrupt,</hi> is not to be heard againſt <hi>God.</hi> Right; but we expect, it may be heard againſt <hi>Men:</hi> that is, concerning the Poſſibility or Conſiſtency of <hi>mere Inferences</hi> made by <hi>Men,</hi> from God's Word. In a word; we contend, that the human Reaſon is as qualified, to <hi>judg</hi> of Inferences, as to <hi>frame</hi> them.</p>
               <p>We inſiſt upon this, as a full An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this uſual Subterfuge; and great, nay only Defence of all our Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers: We call every body to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that 'tis not only frivolous, but wholly impertinent. When they have declamed never ſo long, upon the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Narrowneſs of the human Reaſon: if it may not be a Judg of Inferences from Scripture; neither ſhould it preſume to make, contrive, or draw any ſuch Inferences. Our Oppoſers dare not ſay this latter; therefore neither can they, with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency to themſelves, ſay the former.</p>
               <p>But becauſe this is a famous Topick; I will ſay ſomething farther upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly;</hi> When they <hi>infer Doctrines</hi> from Scripture, which, by their own Confeſſion, imply <hi>manifeſt Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> that is, <hi>ſeem</hi> to our Reaſon as it <hi>now</hi> is, to imply manifeſt Self-Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions: and theſe Inferences, when once made, become ſo ſacred with 'em, that they muſt not be judged of, no not by that human Reaſon that made 'em. I ſay, when this is the caſe; do they not ſay hereby, that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Reaſon is <hi>infallible,</hi> which in the ſame Breath they decry as <hi>corrupt, nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:47056:24"/>
and <hi>uncapable of making a right Judgment?</hi> The Doctrines <hi>inferred by Reaſon,</hi> from the Word of God, are certain and ſacred; they ſay: but when the (malepert) Unitarian offers to examine the Conſiſtency or Poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of thoſe Doctrines, which Reaſon inferred from Scripture; all on the ſudden, they ſurprize us with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Pretence, that Reaſon is <hi>narrow</hi> and <hi>corrupt,</hi> and therefore has no Right of Suffrage in things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; they are above Reaſon, not to be judged by it. Methinks, there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily be a more apparent Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, than this very Defence of our Oppoſers, implies: they give, and take back, in the ſame Cauſe and Thing. They exclude Reaſon, from a bare Suffrage; and yet make it a Judg: they allow it to ſtamp an infallible and ſacred Character, on the Inferences it makes; but will not permit, it ſhould re-examine thoſe very Inferences; or ſhould review its own Acts, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are conſiſtent, yea or no. Reaſon, according to them, is all Eye; and at the ſame time, 'tis Cimmerian, or Egyptian Darkneſs. When 'tis wire-drawing Doctrines from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, its Deductions are as ſacred and certain, as their Divine Original: but it loſes all its happy Dexterity and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, ſo ſoon as it preſumes to re-exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thoſe Deductions, whether they are conſiſtent with themſelves; or are truly made.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>once more.</hi> How ſtrangely has the Divine Wiſdom dealt with Men, in the Hypotheſis of theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen? He requires us in <hi>his Word,</hi> they ſay, to believe <q>there are three eternal and infinite Spirits; and that tho each of them is a perfect God, yet all of them are but one God:</q> but he has ſet up in us another Light, even <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that ſhows us the quite contrary; namely, <q>That there can be but one infinite all-perfect Spirit; and that if there were <hi>three</hi> ſuch Spirits, there would be <hi>three</hi> Gods, and not one only: that is, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires us, by the written <hi>outward Word,</hi> to believe; and by the <hi>inward Word,</hi> to disbelieve: he imploys the Authority of his <hi>Revelation,</hi> to tell us one thing; and makes Faith impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by <hi>clearly ſhowing</hi> us the contrary by <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
                  </q> It is a moſt certain Truth <hi>in Heaven,</hi> they ſay; what <hi>on Earth</hi> ſeems an over-grown Abſurdity; the moſt dangerous, as well as the flatteſt and moſt obvious Contradiction.</p>
               <p>I grant, Divine Revelation is infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible; and the human Reaſon ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fallible, by Accident: as when it makes too much haſte, in judging; and when it ſoars to Objects, that are above it. But it has always been held, that the Veracity of God is concerned in it; that <hi>our Faculties ſhould be true,</hi> and be <hi>able to judg truly of what they diſtinctly and clearly perceive.</hi> And if this be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, the Doctrine of our Oppoſers is upon no better bottom, not only than ours; but than the moſt Chimerical Figments, that Fancy or Invention can advance. They can have no degree of Certainty, in the <hi>cleareſt Inferences</hi> that Reaſon at any time makes, either from the Nature, or Revelation of God; and conſequently alſo, not of their Trinity of the three eternal and infinite Spirits: there will always lie this Exception; that the Deductions made, are indeed <hi>clear and diſtinct,</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:47056:24"/>
but they are concerning <hi>Objects, above the human Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, it ought to be conſider'd; that how much ſoever an Object may be above us; yet <hi>the things affirmed, or denied concerning it,</hi> may lie within the Sphere of Reaſon; and be as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to its Cognizance, as any other Matters are. God is infinitely above me; I am infinitely far from knowing all that God is: but if I am taught ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>in expreſs Terms,</hi> or in Words that <hi>imply it,</hi> that there are <hi>three</hi> Gods, and not one only; I can as eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly judg of thoſe Words and Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and <hi>as certainly,</hi> as if they were ſaid of a <hi>finite</hi> Being. I can as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly know, that to ſay <hi>three eternal and all-ſufficient Spirits,</hi> or to ſay, <hi>three Spirits, each of which is a perfect God;</hi> amounts to this, or implies this, there are three Gods, and not one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: as I can know, <hi>three Angelical Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> or <hi>three human Beings,</hi> implies or amounts to this, three <hi>Angels,</hi> and three <hi>Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The mere Sublimity of an Object, doth not annul, or ſo much as weaken the Certainty of thoſe Affirmations or Negations concerning it; that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to ſuch Object, with other Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that are the proper and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Subjects of Reaſon. If the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, even this, <hi>an eternal and all-perfect Spirit,</hi> is multiplied, by our ſaying, <hi>three eternal all-perfect Spirits:</hi> We thereby as truly, and alſo <hi>as plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and certainly</hi> multiply Gods; as when we multiply the Definition of the Sun or Earth, or other <hi>created</hi> and <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> Beings, we thereby multiply Suns and Earths. In a word, Propoſitions that are <hi>eternal Verities,</hi> are alſo <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Verities;</hi> and are as much a Rule, by which to judg unerringly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an <hi>infinite Object,</hi> as concerning a <hi>finite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the reſt of Monſieur <hi>De Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zancy</hi>'s Book, or four Letters: I know not, whether we are concerned in it; till I know more certainly, in what Senſe he holds a Trinity of Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and the Divinity and Satisfaction of our Saviour. He pretends to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the late Prints of the Unitarians. Thoſe Prints are of two ſorts, or have two Parts; one part of 'em contains the Arguments from Holy Scripture, or from Reaſon, which evince <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God,</hi> by which we mean, that there is <hi>but one all-perfect Spirit:</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part conſiders the Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that are objected by ſome, againſt the Belief of the Unity of God; or for a Trinity of all-perfect Spirits, that is, a Trinity of Gods. To the Prints, or Parts of Prints, of the firſt ſort; Mr. <hi>L.</hi> has ſaid nothing at all: What he has ſaid upon the other part of our Books; tho we do not approve of it, yet we might admit (or tolerate) his Interpretations, if we certainly knew (as I ſaid but now) what kind of Trinity he holds, and in what Senſe he believes the Divinity and Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Saviour. If he directly ſays, the Meaning of his Interpretations, is; that there are three eternal <hi>Minds,</hi> three infinite <hi>Subſtances,</hi> three all-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Spirits:</hi> his Doctrine is condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in terms, as heretical and impious, by the late Decree of the Heads of Colleges at <hi>Oxford;</hi> in which Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, if I miſtake not, he was once a Student. And if by the Divinity of our Saviour, he intends; that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:47056:25"/>
of three infinite Spirits became incarnate in the Humanity of Chriſt; or that the Divinity was ſo incarnate, that there followed a <hi>real</hi> (and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>nominal</hi>) Communication of Idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oms: it is <hi>doubly</hi> heretical. For the Catholick Church owns but one infinite Spirit. And for a <hi>real</hi> Communication of Idioms, whereby God (actually, phyſically, or properly) became a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Man, or a particular Man <hi>real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> became God Almighty: 'tis the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychian Hereſy, condemned in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny General Councils. He is alſo an Eutychian, if he pretends; that when he finds, or thinks he finds, that our Saviour (in Scripture) is called <hi>God,</hi> has an <hi>Omniſcience</hi> or <hi>Omnipotence,</hi> or an <hi>Omnipreſence</hi> attributed to him, or is ſaid to have <hi>created</hi> or made all things: I ſay, he would be an Euty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chian, if he pretended to aſcribe theſe things to the Perſon of our Saviour, in any other Senſe but this; <hi>to God in him, i. e.</hi> to God, who did inhabit after an ineffable manner, in the Humanity of Chriſt. As to <hi>the Satisfaction;</hi> if he will have it, that Jeſus Chriſt made an <hi>adequate Satisfaction,</hi> and therefore (in Equity) <hi>not refuſable;</hi> to the Divine <hi>Juſtice,</hi> for the Sins of Men: he were beſt to conſider the Computations of the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For <hi>us,</hi> we believe, with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church; that the Lord Chriſt did <hi>truly ſatisfy</hi> Almighty God, for the Sins of Men; not by paying our Debt, to the <hi>Divine Juſtice,</hi> but by his unblemiſh'd and perfect Life, his willing and exemplary Death; the which, <hi>the Mercy</hi> of God accepted, on our Behalf, tho it was <hi>a refuſable Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This, Sir, is what I thought needful to be ſent to you; by way of Remarks on Mr. <hi>L.</hi> his four Letters, which he was pleaſed to publiſh, againſt the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarian Prints. He has written after a civil and obliging manner: I own, that he may claim it as his due; that we be ready upon all occaſions, to make to him like Returns. Whether it were his Prudence, or his Candor, or both; he was not (I ſee) willing to loſe the Eſteem of his Erudition, and Wit; by a ſnarling, ſordid, and clowniſh way of Writing; againſt us. It may be, he conſider'd; that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, and Gallantry, in this kind, is not only no Blemiſh or Hindrance to a Writer, but ſerves to recommend his Performance to his very Oppoſers, as well as to his Party and Friends.</p>
               <p>Whereas he blames ſome of our Prints, as deficient in point of Reſpect to ſome of our Antagoniſts; he ſhould firſt have read the Books, to which thoſe Prints make anſwer: he would have ſeen, there was a Provocation gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; that we could not, with any Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but take ſome notice of it. For it cannot eſcape a Man ſo diſcerning as Mr. <hi>L.</hi> is; that there is a Patience, which is the Vertue of a Chriſtian: and there is alſo <hi>a Patience, which is the Vertue of an Aſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:47056:25"/>
               <head>On the Vindication by the Bp. of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND I have read, Sir, as you alſo deſired, the new <hi>Vindication of the Doctrine of the Trinity,</hi> by the Bp. of <hi>Worceſter.</hi> I think, what a Man can ſay of it, who would ſpeak in ſhort, is; <q>He has heartily chode with the Socinians, for <hi>the Terms:</hi> and has entirely yielded <hi>the things,</hi> in queſtion; to the Unitarians.</q> He is ſuch another Anti-Unitarian, as our Father <hi>Wallis</hi> is an Anti-Socinian; who made himſelf famous, for almoſt a whole Year, for <hi>his Vindication</hi> of the Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſian Creed, and his <hi>Letters</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> againſt <hi>Socinus</hi> and the Socinians: and has been as remarkable ever ſince, for a Diſcovery made upon him; that himſelf is wholly Socinian, in thoſe very Sermons, Letters, and Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that he oppoſed to the Socinians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis a Myſtery this,</hi> that Men who give up Dr. <hi>Sherlock;</hi> nay argue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly againſt him, and his Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis of <hi>three</hi> infinite Subſtances, <hi>three</hi> All-perfect Minds and Spirits: 'tis, I ſay, <hi>a Myſtery,</hi> that they ſhould write Vindications alſo againſt <hi>us;</hi> who are in no other Hereſy, as to theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but <q>the Hereſy of <hi>one</hi> infinite Subſtance, <hi>one</hi> Eternal, All-perfect Mind and Spirit.</q> Perhaps Father <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi>'s Oppoſition, was the Effect of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Age; but his Lordſhip is not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perannuated, and he has read our Books, and (particularly) makes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Quotations out of the <hi>Diſcourſe concerning the Nominal and Real Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians:</hi> where our Conſent with the Catholick Church, in the Articles of the Trinity, and the Divinity of our Saviour, is declared, and cleared. There was therefore ſome other reaſon, why the <hi>Catelines</hi> fall to work againſt the <hi>Cethegi;</hi> and 'tis no hard matter to gueſs at it, nay to aſcertain it. But of that, hereafter.</p>
               <p>The Structure of <hi>the Vindication,</hi> is in the Form and Way of modern Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, of the <hi>preſent</hi> Mode and Cut of the Church; of all others, as ſome think, the worſt. The Speaker openly profeſſes his Method; that he will prove firſt, then Secondly, Thirdly, then Fourthly, and Fifthly. After this Declaration, comes the Subdiviſion (or new Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) of theſe Firſts, Seconds, Thirds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Laſtly, that well-known, "And now Beloved, <hi>Firſt of the Firſt.</hi> Men of Wit pretend, it is not Method, but Confuſion; for theſe Firſts, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds, Thirds, having their Subdivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions into other Firſts, Seconds, Thirds; and they again (moſt commonly) into farther Underling-Diviſions: about the middle of a Diſcourſe, but eſpecially toward the end of it, the Hearer or Reader is quite loſt; he knows not what Second, Third, or Fourth is meant; or on what part of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the Speaker (or Writer) now is.</p>
               <p>But of all Imperfections, Obſcurity (when a Doctrine is to be explained, or a Point to be argued) is the moſt offenſive and ungrateful. When a Man enters into moſt of the Books of the true Unitarians: the Subject is ſo clear
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:47056:26"/>
of it ſelf, that it ſeems, as if one came into a well-furniſht Room, hung round with radiant Lights; which ſhow eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing in it, very diſtinctly, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry agreeably. A Man ſees, perfectly, every Object; and with this Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that the clear Light about it, ſhows it more luſtrous, and more pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But on the other hand, the Books (whether they be Anſwers, or Attacks) of the <hi>Men of ſuperiour Learning and Wit,</hi> as his Lordſhip compliments him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and Friends, at <hi>p.</hi> 45. of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face; bleſs me, how like old German Monaſtries, or Inquiſition-Priſons, do they look! ſuch is the Intricacy of the Subject. How dusky, dim, and dark, are the Rooms, and Paſſages? Between Obſcurity, and Ruggedneſs, a Man cannot forbear, to hug himſelf; ſo ſoon as he is got out: and while he is within, he can diſcern nothing; or however, not with eaſe to himſelf, or Satisfaction in the thing. I cannot but complain, that his Lordſhip's Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is ſomewhat of this Nature; for tho it has much of that ſame <hi>ſuperiour Learning and Wit,</hi> yet when he argues, or anſwers, but eſpecially when he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains; I do not take his meaning, under two or three Readings. And when I have ſtrained <hi>my Jaws, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded</hi> my Teeth; to break the Shell: moſt commonly, it proves nothing but a Shell; <hi>that I am tempted, to renounce Nuts for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Contents of his Book, he ſhows; that neither Antiquity, nor Reaſon, nor Scripture is at all for us; they are all againſt us. He has, up and down, ſome Offers, at an Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Trinity; <hi>the which, we throughly approve.</hi> We judg him to be as Catholick and Orthodox in that matter, as any of our own number. Tho he has called us as many Names, and imputed as many bad things to us; as Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> himſelf (whether in his Letters, or Vindication) did: he is, for all that, no more our Enemy <hi>in Doctrine,</hi> than Father <hi>Wallis</hi> himſelf is, or than our Brother <hi>S—th.</hi> Farther, he takes up the Quarrel between Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> and Dean <hi>Sherlock;</hi> he ſhows, that they are both of 'em good Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks; the one <hi>in Intention,</hi> the other <hi>in Reality and ſober Sadneſs.</hi> 'Tis a very reconcilable Difference, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Lordſhip; whether it be ſaid (namely, <hi>in words</hi> only, while <hi>the Intent</hi> is Orthodox and Catholick) that there are three Divine Perſons, who are three eternal <hi>Spirits,</hi> three All-perfect <hi>Minds,</hi> three infinite <hi>Subſtances;</hi> with ſo many diſtinct Underſtandings, Wills, and Omnipotencies, <hi>which is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Dean</hi> Sherlock: or whether it be ſaid, there are three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in the Metaphyſical and Critical Senſe of the Term Perſons, that is, which are but <hi>one</hi> infinite All-perfect Spirit, with <hi>one</hi> only Underſtanding, Will and Omnipotence; <hi>one</hi> ſelf-ſame infinite Subſtance or Eſſence, with the <hi>three Properties,</hi> to be <hi>of none,</hi> to be <hi>begotten,</hi> and <hi>to proceed.</hi> I will go over theſe parts of <hi>the Vindication;</hi> in the order I have propoſed them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:47056:26"/>
               <head>Of Antiquity.</head>
               <p>OF Antiquity, we claim in the firſt place, the vaſt Period; from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> to our Saviour: being a Tract of 4000 Years: That is, two parts in three of all Time. The Patriarchs are ours, the Prophets ours; <hi>Adam, Seth, Enoch, Noah, Sem, Abraham, Moſes, David,</hi> ours; ſo ours, that they are yielded to us, on all hands: 'tis not ſo much as pretended, that theſe believed otherwiſe than the Unitarians do, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God. 'Tis an Argument of our Oppoſers themſelves; that <q>if <hi>Adam</hi> or the Antediluvian Patriarchs bad believed, or known the Trinity (underſtand here, <hi>of the Realiſts,</hi> namely, <hi>three Almighty Eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits;</hi>) it would have deſcended to <hi>Noah,</hi> to <hi>Sem,</hi> and from <hi>Sem</hi> to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham;</hi> from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and their Poſterity the Jewiſh Church, eſpecially to <hi>Moſes.</hi> But it appears clearly by Scripture, that <hi>Moſes,</hi> or the Church of the Jews, knew it not; therefore neither did the afore-mentioned Patriarchs, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Antediluvians or Poſtdiluvians.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> and the Bp. of <hi>Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> fearing that ſuch an Advantage as <hi>the whole Old Teſtament-time on the ſide of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> ſhould furniſh them with unanſwerable Arguments and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, for the Doctrine they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, anſwer; That tho the Trinity does not appear to have been known to the Patriarchs, or the Jews, by any of the Books of the Old Teſtament: it is to be remembred, that the Jews had alſo a <hi>Kabbala</hi> or <hi>Oral Tradition,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to them from <hi>Moſes</hi> and from God; and the Trinity was a part of this <hi>Kabbala.</hi> Where is Conſcience; or is Religion nothing but a Name? Do the Bp. and Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> believe <hi>the Kabbala;</hi> that 'tis derived from <hi>Moſes,</hi> and from God? No more than they believe the <hi>Alchoran;</hi> that it was given by Angels: as the Impoſtor, the Author of it, pretends. They contend for the Trinity, and the <hi>Kabbala;</hi> 'tis certain, that they believe not the latter: how then will they now perſwade any Man, that they believe (inwardly) the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer? They dare to ſet up a Fiction of the Phariſees, and which (one cannot imagine but) they believe to be a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; as of Divine Original, and as <hi>the unwritten Word</hi> of God: after ſuch a Prevarication, who ſhall take their Words for what they pretend to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, or not to believe? I ſcorn to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue with 'em, about the Truth of the <hi>Kabbala;</hi> for which they have nothing to alledg, and the Credit of which is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally overthrown, by the Author of the <hi>Anſwer to Dr.</hi> Bull: I ſhall only mind 'em, that if they are Jews (or rather if they are Phariſees, for the ſounder part of the Jews, the <hi>Karaites,</hi> diſclaim the <hi>Kabbala</hi>) they diſown their being Proteſtants; for 'tis a Fundamental Article of Proteſtantiſm, that <q>there is no other Word of God, but only his <hi>written Word.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Well, but ſuppoſing the <hi>Kabbala;</hi> doth it ſay any thing of <hi>a Trinity,</hi> or an <hi>eternal Son</hi> of God? <hi>Not the leaſt Word.</hi> Why then is it alledged?
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:47056:27"/>
                  <hi>Becauſe the Chaldee Paraphraſes ſpeak of the WORD, as God; and how ſhould thoſe Paraphraſes come to know the WORD, or ſpeak of him as God, but out of the</hi> Kabbala? But if the <hi>Kab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bala</hi> has nothing of the Trinity, or the WORD, how ſhould the Paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes take what they ſay of the WORD, from the <hi>Kabbala?</hi> But after all, what is it, that the Paraphraſes ſay of the WORD; do they call him <hi>God,</hi> or ſpeak of him as <hi>a Perſon?</hi> Of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces produced by the Bp. at <hi>p.</hi> 128, 129. not one of them does ſo much as ſeem to the purpoſe, but only <hi>the firſt.</hi> They ſpeak, either of the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; or of the Law; or of the Command or Order of God to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> or of the Power of God, which (in the Books of the Old Teſtament) is expreſſed by <hi>the Word,</hi> or <hi>Mandate</hi> of God; becauſe God effects whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he wills, by only willing, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, or <hi>ſaying,</hi> that it ſhall be. But <hi>the firſt</hi> Text, alledged by his Lordſhip, I know not what to ſay of it; for he quotes <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.21. when there are but 18 Verſes in that whole Chapter; nor is there any thing in the whole Chapter, that bears the leaſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance to what he quotes out of it. Therefore ſo much for <hi>Chaldee,</hi> and <hi>Kabbala;</hi> deſpiſed by all Learned Men, Jews as well as Chriſtians; and never uſed, but when the People are to be gull'd, with noiſy Nothings.</p>
               <p>The next, is the important Period, from our Saviour's beginning to preach, to the taking of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, under the Conduct of <hi>Titus Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſianus.</hi> Our Oppoſers controvert with us, this Period; but ſeeing the whole Hiſtory of it, as to the Point in queſtion, is ſet down in the Goſpels, Acts, and Epiſtles, of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: every Body, that will be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, may be informed from thoſe Holy Scriptures themſelves; whether they teach, that <hi>God is a Spirit,</hi> or on the contrary, that there are <hi>three</hi> Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, Eternal, and All-perfect Spirits?</p>
               <p>A little before the Inveſting of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> by the Roman Army under the leading of <hi>Veſpaſianus;</hi> the Jewiſh Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were warned by their Prophets, to retire out of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and remove to <hi>Pella,</hi> and other Parts (of <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Galilee</hi>) remote from the Seat of War. Theſe Chriſtians of the Jewiſh Nation were called <hi>Nazarens;</hi> and the Author of the Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> has proved, that they were <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians.</hi> His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is ſo ingenuous, as to grant it, at <hi>p.</hi> 12, 13. tho the Conceſſion in the Opinion of Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> amounts to an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute yielding the whole Controverſy, to the Unitarians: but what ſhould he do; the thing being ſo inconteſtably proved in that Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> the Bp. ſaw, it would be cried out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as meer affected Wrangling, not to give way to ſo clear a Demonſtration, as is there made of it. Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains to no purpoſe, that, <q>if the Nazarens were Unitarians, our Cauſe can be no longer defended: and the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitaries</hi> muſt be granted to have been the only Guardians, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervators of the true Faith.</q> 
                  <hi>Judic. Eccl. p.</hi> 41, 42.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Bp. inſinuates after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, that there were two ſorts of Nazarens; <hi>viz.</hi> the main Body of the Jewiſh Chriſtians, who (after the Inveſting of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) ſettled firſt at <hi>Pella,</hi> and afterwards dilated all over
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:47056:27"/>
                  <hi>Paleſtine, Moab, Arabia, Syria,</hi> nay all over <hi>Aſia; who were all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians:</hi> and another <hi>leſſer</hi> Party of them, who after the taking of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſian,</hi> were ſuffered to inhabit <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> together with the Gentiles, and abode there under 15 ſucceſſive Biſhops, even to the ſecond Siege, and ſecond taking of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by the Emperour <hi>Adrian;</hi> and <hi>theſe</hi> (his Lordſhip thinks) <hi>were not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians.</hi> This Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of two ſorts of <hi>Nazarens,</hi> or Jewiſh Chriſtians, is a pure Figment; for all the Antients who mention the Jewiſh Chriſtians or Nazarens, ſay of them, they were all Unitarians: and that the only difference among them, was; ſome of them ſaid, Jeſus was the Son of <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary by Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and the Son of God <hi>by Holineſs and Adoption;</hi> others ſaid, he was <hi>the Son of Mary only,</hi> begotten of her by the Adumbration of the Holy Ghoſt, or Power of God.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Alogians</hi> were ours; he does not offer to conteſt it: neither does he deny to us the particular <hi>Fathers,</hi> claimed by us in the Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Bull;</hi> ſaving that he is willing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe <hi>Hegeſippus, Theodotion, Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſatum,</hi> and <hi>Photinus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We will yield, <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> to his Lordſhip, when he ſatisfies the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> page 41, 42. which he will do, when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends his Sermon about <hi>Myſteries,</hi> againſt the Exceptions of <hi>the Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Hierom</hi> aſſures us, that <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> was an Unitarian: his Lordſhip would fain deny it, on the (miſtaken) Authority of <hi>Euſebius.</hi> He ought to know, that becauſe <hi>Theodotion</hi> came over from the Pagans to the <hi>Jewiſh Chriſtians;</hi> therefore <hi>Euſebius</hi> calls him a <hi>Jewiſh Proſelyte.</hi> And this he might have learned, from the Place of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> which himſelf quotes: for 'tis there ſaid, that <q>the <hi>Ebionites [a Branch of the Nazarens]</hi> following <hi>Theodotion</hi> and <hi>Aquila,</hi> contend that Jeſus was the Son of <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Photinus</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſatum</hi> have been always cenſured by Church-Hiſtorians, as undoubted Unitarians. And though his Lordſhip rightly ſays, that what they ſeem to have held con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>the Perſon of our Saviour,</hi> is ſomewhat different from the Belief of the modern Unitarians: it is not to our preſent Inquiry; which is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the Trinity,</hi> not concerning <hi>the Perſon of our Saviour.</hi> That in the Article of <hi>the Trinity, Paul</hi> and <hi>Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus,</hi> were not Unitarians; his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will never prove, nor ever at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to prove it.</p>
               <p>A great many Biſhops aſſembled (riotouſly and ſchiſmatically) againſt their Primate <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſatum,</hi> and condemned his Perſon and Doctrine; tho he was favoured by (the <hi>Heroina</hi> of that Age) Queen <hi>Zenobia;</hi> who then ruled in thoſe Parts. His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip infers from hence; that 'tis not meerly from Fears, Aws and Intereſt, that the Orthodox have maintained the Doctrine of the Trinity: no, we ſee, they aſſembled againſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned <hi>Paul;</hi> in the Dominions of a Princeſs, who favoured his Doctrine. Granting now that Q. <hi>Zenobia</hi> favoured <hi>Paul;</hi> and that <hi>Antioch</hi> (where <hi>Paul</hi> was Biſhop, and where the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks convened againſt him,) was under
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:47056:28"/>
the Authority of <hi>Zenobia;</hi> which laſt (be ſure) is falſe, whatever the firſt is: yet how will this Inſtance evince, what his Lordſhip would draw from it? For theſe Biſhops were, not only <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> but <hi>Hereticks:</hi> they rejected <hi>Homo-uſios,</hi> or that the Divine Perſons have <hi>the ſame Subſtance.</hi> If they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved a Trinity, it was not the Trinity of the Orthodox or the Catholick Church: the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and this Conventicle of Schiſmaticks, were of contrary Minds; the Conventiclers would not admit of <hi>Homo-uſios,</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> contended for, the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> put it into the Creed.</p>
               <p>I had almoſt forgot, that whereas <hi>Lucianus,</hi> ſo much celebrated by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, is claimed by us; from the Authority of <hi>Alexander,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria:</hi> his Lordſhip alledges, that Cardinal <hi>Baronius</hi> conjectures, that <hi>Alexander</hi> miſtook the Opinions of <hi>Lucianus.</hi> But in very deed, what <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> ſays of <hi>Lucianus,</hi> is too well circumſtantiated to be ſhaken, by the Conjectures of a Perſon, who lived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 1200 Years after him. For <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> not only ſays, that <hi>Lucianus</hi> eſpouſed the Cauſe of <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> againſt the Schiſmatical Biſhops, who had caballed againſt him: but farther, that whereas he thought them to be Hereticks, as well as Schiſmaticks; he ſeparated from the Communion of the Biſhop, and his two Succeſſors, that were put into the Chair of <hi>Paul,</hi> and held alſo ſeparate Meetings.</p>
               <p>But his Lordſhip urges, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians in a Council at <hi>Antioch Anno</hi> 342. produced a Creed; that was contrary to the Doctrine of <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſatum,</hi> and agreed with the Arian Doctrine: and yet the Arians ſaid, this Creed was wholly written by <hi>Lucianus.</hi> But the Hiſtorian quoted by his Lordſhip, makes doubt whether this Creed was really written by <hi>Lucianus:</hi> or whether the Arians, to ſhelter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the Authority of ſo great a Man, had not feigned it. To ſay, as his Lordſhip does; they would not impute a Creed to <hi>Lucian,</hi> that was ſo remarkably contrary to his Doctrine; in a City, where it muſt needs be well known, what had been the Doctrine of <hi>Lucian,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſatum,</hi> whom we pretend that <hi>Lucian</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: I ſay, to argue after that manner, is to be unmindful; that Forgers do not bethink them of all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, that may betray their fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Dealing; if they did, there would be no Forgeries.</p>
               <p>To add no more; his Lordſhip con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes, that <hi>D. Petavius</hi> and <hi>H. Valeſius,</hi> the exacteſt Criticks we have in Church Hiſtory, diſapprove the Conjecture and Reaſons of Cardinal <hi>Baronius;</hi> and give up <hi>Lucian</hi> to the Unitaries.</p>
               <p>This is all (that is conſiderable) that his Lordſhip has offer'd from Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; I proceed to </p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <head>Scripture and Reaſon.</head>
               <p>HIS 8th and 10th Chapters are imployed, in oppoſing (and, as he thinks, in expoſing and ridiculing) ſome Interpretations (of a few Texts)
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:47056:28"/>
of Scripture, by the Unitarians; and in attacking a few Paragraphs, in Mr. <hi>Toland</hi>'s Book, <hi>Chriſtianity not myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> I know not what it was to his Lordſhip's Purpoſe, to fall upon Mr. <hi>Toland</hi>'s Book. But if he would needs attack the Book; he ſhould have dealt fairly: he ſhould have diſcuſſed the main Argument in it, and not carpt only at a few Paſſages; and thoſe too, ſo mangled and deformed by his Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of them, that I dare to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, Mr. <hi>Toland</hi> does not know his own Book in the Biſhop's Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. I do not perceive, to ſpeak truly, but that the Book ſtill ſtands in its full Strength; if it hath not alſo acquired a farther Reputation, by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this (ſo) unſucceſsful nibling at it. But ſuppoſe <hi>the Biſhop</hi> had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed <hi>the Gentleman;</hi> what is that to <hi>us?</hi> do we offer this Book, againſt <hi>the Trinity of the Realiſts;</hi> was it written, with intention to ſerve <hi>us;</hi> doth it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any of our Allegations from <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> againſt the Trinity of <hi>Philaponus, Joachim,</hi> and <hi>Gentitis?</hi> We deſire him to anſwer to the <hi>Reaſons</hi> in our Books, againſt <hi>the Trinity of the Tritheiſts;</hi> but to theſe, he ſaith not a Word, but only falls upon Mr. <hi>Toland</hi>'s Book: in which, or for which, we are not in the leaſt concerned; nor do I think the (Learned and Ingenious) Author will hold himſelf to be intereſted, to defend that <hi>Chriſtianity not myſterious,</hi> which his Lordſhip preſents us with.</p>
               <p>As to his Exceptions againſt ſome Interpretations of Scripture, which he finds in ſome Books of the Unitarians: we ſhould have enough to do, if we went to the Preſs (to vindicate what has been already ſo well eſtabliſht;) every time that an angry Litigant is in a humour, to write againſt us. His Lordſhip had a Mind to ſhew his <hi>ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Learning and Wit; and caſting the Dice, to determine what Subject he ſhould chooſe: up comes the Trinity, and</hi> the Books of the Unitarians; <hi>upon</hi> theſe, <hi>he</hi> will gain immortal Honour. We wiſh him Luck; but not being at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to wipe off every ſmall Soil, that may happen to be ſcattered on our Books, our Oppoſers may ſafely (for us) enjoy their Victories. We care not for Proſelytes, that have no manner of Senſe; and for Perſons that have any, we dare truſt them with whatſoever <hi>Vindications,</hi> we have yet ſeen: we only deſire them, to read our Arguments (whether from <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or <hi>Scripture,</hi>) as they ſtand in our own Books; not as they are diſguiſed in <hi>Vindications.</hi> The <hi>Exempts</hi> of the Church, who are diſcharged from the mean Drudgery of <hi>Preaching</hi> the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; and are concerned only, in the noble Imployment of Commanding: how eaſy is it for them, to come out now and then, with a magiſterial Book; ſeeing, whether 'tis home to the Purpoſe or not, is ſolely at <hi>the Buyer's</hi> Peril? In ſhort, if his Lordſhip has baffled the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations of the Unitarians, againſt which he has concerned himſelf, in the Opinion of any Reader: he ſhall, for me, enjoy his Succeſs; for my part I am enough perſwaded, without further arguing the Matter, that <hi>he has ſpent his Breath againſt a Rock.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:47056:29"/>
               <head>His Lordſhip's Explication of the Trinity.</head>
               <p>AFter his Lordſhip has taken ſo much Pains, to vindicate the Doctrine of the Trinity; let us ſee, what kind of Trinity, he believes and contends for. For Mr. <hi>Biddle</hi> alſo wrote a Book for the Trinity: his Lordſhip's Title bears, <hi>A Vindication of the Doctrine of the Trinity;</hi> but Mr. <hi>Biddle</hi> far more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly and zealouſly, <hi>The Apoſtolical Opinion of the Holy Trinity aſſerted.</hi> Ay, but his Lordſhip's Trinity is <hi>the Athanaſian Trinity;</hi> he has a whole Chapter in Vindication and Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Creed of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> Well, but Father <hi>Wallis</hi> too publiſhed a Book, intituled, <hi>An Explication and Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Creed of</hi> Athanaſius. They both of them interpret the Athanaſian Creed; and then believe it: that is, believe it according to their own Senſe of it. And ſo do <hi>we;</hi> that is, <hi>we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, according to the Senſe they make of it.</hi> But his Lordſhip believes and contends for that Trinity; which the Unitarians deny, and oppoſe. I'll give thee my Cap then; what Proof do you make of his believing that Trinity, which we deny? Why, he has wrote two whole Books againſt you; one concerning the Satisfaction, the other concerning the Trinity. But my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>S—th</hi> alſo wrote two (bigger) Books; in both which, he blames and quarrels the Unitarians, as abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hereticks: and yet we ſo little think, that we have any real Difference with him, that we intend him an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Place in the <hi>Company of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> at our next General Aſſembly.</p>
               <p>His Lordſhip has a whole Chapter; 'tis that remarkable <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. beginning at <hi>pag.</hi> 68. and ending at <hi>p.</hi> 101. the longeſt, or one of the longeſt, in his Book: to ſtate the Notion of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and to vindicate it from Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions. He begins with obſerving;</p>
               <p n="1">1. <q>We muſt diſtinguiſh, between the Being of a thing, and a thing in Being. Or, between Eſſence, and Exiſtence.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <q>Between the Unity of Nature or Eſſence, and of Exiſtence or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuals of the ſame Nature.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <q>Between the Notion of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in a finite Subſtance; and in a Being uncapable of Diviſion, or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. After he has ſpoken, <hi>firſt of the first;</hi> he comes to ſay;</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <q>We muſt now diſtinguiſh the Unity which belongs to the common Nature, from that which belongs to Individuals in actual Being. And farther, the Unity of Exiſtence may be conſider'd:</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">(1.) <q>Either, where the Eſſence and the Exiſtence are the ſame; as they are in God.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) <q>Or, where the Exiſtence is contingent, as in Creatures. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the Unity of Exiſtence may be conſidered;</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. <q>Either as to it ſelf; and ſo it is Identity.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2dly. <q>Or, as to others; that is, as every one ſtands divided from every other Individual of the ſame kind, altho they all partake of the ſame common Nature or Eſſence.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:47056:29"/>
The clearing of this, <hi>he adds,</hi> is that main Point; on which, the whole Notion of theſe Matters, depends: ſo in order thereto, we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <q>What that is, whereby <hi>we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> the Difference of Individuals?</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <q>What that is, which <hi>really</hi> makes two Beings of the ſame kind to be different from each other?</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">(1.) <q>As to the Reaſon of <hi>our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception</hi> of the Difference between Individuals of the ſame kind; it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends,</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. <q>On the Difference of outward Accidents; Feature, Age, Meen, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2dly. <q>On the Difference of inward Qualities; which we may perceive by Obſervation, and which ariſe from Conſtitution, Education, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, acquired Habits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) <q>As to the <hi>true Ground</hi> of the real Difference, between the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of one Individual from the reſt; it depends on <hi>the ſeparate Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence</hi> which it hath from all others. For that which gives it a Being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from all others, and divided by individual Properties, is the true ground of the Difference between them; and that can be no other but the Will of God.—But we are not yet come, by a good way, <hi>to the bottom</hi> of the Matter.</q> Truly I am ſorry for it; for I am half tired alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and quite loſt, in this Labyrinth of 1, 2, 3; 2, 1. 2; 1, 2, 1, 2, 2: but let's go on, ſince we needs muſt. <q>As to Individuals, (ſo he proceeds, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>the bottom</hi>) there are theſe things to be conſidered.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <q>Actual Exiſtence in it ſelf; which hath <hi>a Mode</hi> belonging to it. And otherwiſe the human Nature of Chriſt, could not have been united to the Divine, but it muſt have had alſo the perſonal Subſiſtence; and conſequently, there muſt have been two Perſons in Chriſt.</q> I ſuppoſe, it may be <hi>Kabbala;</hi> or <hi>Chaldee:</hi> but Senſe it is not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <q>A ſeparate and divided Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence from all others; which ariſes from the actual Exiſtence, but may be diſtinguiſhed from it. As the human Nature of Chriſt, altho it had the Exiſtence proper to Being; yet had not a ſeparate Exiſtence, after the Hypoſtatical Union.</q> Be not abaſh'd, Sir; the Meaning only is: ſome things exiſt ſeparately, others in Union or Compoſition. But <hi>deep</hi> Men (as his Lordſhip ſomewhere ſays of his Party) muſt expreſs themſelves <hi>deeply;</hi> to keep up the Reputation, of what they (falſly) call <hi>Learning:</hi> for were their Theorems deliver'd in plain Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, they would be thought to be childiſh Trifles.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <q>The peculiar manner of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, which lies in ſuch Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as are incommunicable to any other: and therein conſiſts the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Reaſon of Perſonality. Which doth not conſiſt in a mere <hi>intelligent Being;</hi> but in that peculiar <hi>manner of Subſiſtence</hi> in that Being, which can be in no other. For when the <hi>common Nature</hi> doth ſubſiſt <hi>in Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduals,</hi> there is not only a ſeparate Exiſtence; but ſomething ſo <hi>peculiar to it ſelf,</hi> that it can be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to no other.</q> The downright <hi>Engliſh</hi> is this: <hi>Tom</hi> hath ſomething ſo peculiar to himſelf, that tho he is a <hi>Man,</hi> yet he is not <hi>Will</hi> or <hi>Ned,</hi> but only <hi>Tom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <q>There is a <hi>common Nature,</hi> which muſt be joined with this <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:47056:30"/>
of Subſiſtence,</hi> to make a <hi>Perſon;</hi> otherwiſe it would be a mere <hi>Mode:</hi> but we never conceive a <hi>Perſon,</hi> without <hi>the Eſſence</hi> in conjunction with it. But here appears <hi>no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Contradiction,</hi> in aſſerting ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Perſons</hi> in the ſame common Nature.</q> In Engliſh, thus: Tallneſs, or Leanneſs, or ſuch like <hi>Modes,</hi> do not alone make a Perſon: there muſt be ſome Eſſence, Nature, or Subſtance, added to the Mode of Tallneſs (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or Leanneſs) elſe mere Tallneſs will not be a Perſon. And hence it is clear, as the Sun; that there is <hi>no manner of Contradiction,</hi> in aſſerting ſeveral Perſons, (ſuch as Tallneſs, Lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Dulneſs,</hi> when joined to ſome Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence or Subſtance) in one and the ſame common Nature: as ſuppoſe, of Humanity. We ſhall conſider this poor Eluſion, by and by.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <q>The Individuals of the ſame kind are ſaid to differ <hi>in Number,</hi> from each other; becauſe of their different Accidents, and ſeparate Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence.</q> Or, thus; <hi>Tom</hi> and <hi>Ned</hi> are two Men, not one Man; becauſe they are <hi>ſeveral</hi> Men, and have ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>different</hi> Qualities. I think, the Critick might have left out the <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Qualities:</hi> for tho the Qualities of <hi>Tom</hi> and <hi>Ned</hi> were the ſame; yet by only being <hi>ſeveral</hi> Men, they would be <hi>two</hi> Men, and not <hi>one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <q>There muſt be <hi>a Separation in Nature,</hi> where there is a Difference of <hi>Individuals</hi> of the ſame kind. I do not ſay, an <hi>actual Separation</hi> or Diviſion, as to Place; but there is, and muſt be, <hi>in Nature,</hi> where <hi>one common Nature</hi> ſubſiſts in ſeveral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuals. For all Individuals muſt <hi>divide</hi> the Species, and the common Nature unites them.</q> Or, <hi>Will</hi> is not <hi>Harry;</hi> the human Nature is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in theſe two Perſons; yet they are both of them <hi>Men:</hi> they are not Camels, nor yet Dromedaries, for they are united in the human Nature, not in the Camel or Dromedary-Nature.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This 3dly comes but oddly after 6thly; but let us hear what it is. <q>We are now to inquire, <hi>how far theſe things will hold,</hi> as to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Trinity?</q> I ſhall anſwer in ſhort; they will not hold at all: and that, for this demonſtrative Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; which, the Builder of this intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Labyrinth, hath unhappily over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look'd. Theſe 1, 2, 3; 2, 1, 2; 1, 2, 1, 2, 2; 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 3, are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Boxes; with each of 'em a Myſtery in it: but here is the Misfortune. They ſpeak of ſuch <hi>Natures,</hi> as have no Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence but only in our Conception; mere <hi>abſtracted Natures,</hi> ſuch as <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature,</hi> Camel-Nature, Angelical Nature, that have not a real Exiſtence, but only an imaginary: for there is really no ſuch <hi>exiſting thing,</hi> as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nature, or Camel-Nature; but they are Notions only of the Mind, framed by our Underſtandings, while they are imployed in conſidering <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> (or in what Properties) all <hi>Men</hi> do agree. They all agree (for inſtance) in Rationality, and Riſibility; and therefore theſe two have been named by Metaphyſicians the <hi>human Nature.</hi> As the Natures, of which the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Boxes ſpeak, are only abſtracted notional and imaginary Natures; not really exiſting Natures: ſo (on the contrary) the Perſons in them, are not mere <hi>Metaphyſical Perſons,</hi> or ſuch <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Properties,</hi> that ſeveral of them do or <hi>can</hi> ſubſiſt in the ſame rational Being; but they are ſuch Perſons as neceſſarily ſuppoſe <hi>diſtinct Subſtances,</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:47056:30"/>
as well as <hi>diſtinct Properties.</hi> For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>the Properties</hi> that make <hi>the Perſonalities</hi> of <hi>Harry</hi> and <hi>Charles,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire diſtinct Subſtances, to make <hi>the Perſons</hi> of <hi>Harry</hi> and <hi>Charles:</hi> thoſe Properties, if they exiſted only in a <hi>common Nature,</hi> as the Humanity, and had not alſo <hi>diſtinct Subſtances;</hi> they would never make <hi>diſtinct Perſons.</hi> In ſhort, the Boxes ſpeak of <hi>imaginary Natures</hi> or Eſſences; and of <hi>Perſons,</hi> who are ſo many <hi>real Subſtances.</hi> They will not therefore hold at all in the Queſtion of the Trinity. For the Bleſſed Trinity is of a juſt contrary Nature, to the Myſteries in the Boxes. In the Trinity, the Nature is a really <hi>exiſting Nature,</hi> 'tis a <hi>ſpiritual Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> and indued with a great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Divine Attributes; not an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, or mere notional imaginary Nature: and <hi>the Perſons</hi> are as unlike to the Perſons in the Boxes; for the Divine Perſons are not <hi>diſtinct Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,</hi> or real <hi>Beings;</hi> but <hi>Properties</hi> only in a real Being, and in an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Subſtance.</p>
               <p>To argue, as his Lordſhip does; from imaginary Natures, to a real Nature: and from Perſons that are diſtinct Beings, and diſtinct Subſtances; to Perſons which, he dares not but ſay, they are only <hi>relative Properties</hi> in the ſame (intellectual) Subſtance and Being. I ſay, to argue after that faſhion, is to ſhoot as wide of his Mark; as the Natures and Perſons, of which he is to diſcourſe, are different: which is no leſs than infinitely. The Pains therefore he has taken in this long ſixth Chapter; which was deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Strength of his whole Book, are loſt: and he has all things to begin anew.</p>
               <p>You will ſay; Have we done then, with our <hi>explaining</hi> and <hi>vindicating</hi> the Trinity? No, Sir. When his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip had wrote his Book; and upon a Review of it, perceived, that he had not ſufficiently (no nor tolerably) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained his Notion of the Trinity: nor yet what is meant, either by <hi>Perſons,</hi> or <hi>Perſonalities;</hi> which muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained and diſtinguiſhed, or we ſhall diſpute about we know not <hi>what,</hi> and with we know not <hi>whom.</hi> I ſay, his Lordſhip perceiving his Overſight, wrote a Preface of 62 Pages; chiefly to declare himſelf upon, and to clear theſe Matters. I will lay together what he hath ſaid, up and down, in his Preface; which I may rightly call, <hi>his Book upon ſecond Thoughts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Trinity in Unity is <q>
                     <hi>one</hi> indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual Subſtance, under three diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Modes of Subſiſtence,</hi> p. 13. Or 'tis <hi>three peculiar Properties,</hi> in one and the ſame Divine Nature, <hi>p.</hi> 14.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But more particularly; as to <hi>Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality</hi> and <hi>Perſon:</hi> 
                  <q>A Perſonality is no more but a different <hi>Mode of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence,</hi> in the <hi>ſame</hi> common Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>p.</hi> 14.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>In created Beings, every <hi>Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> doth ſuppoſe a <hi>diſtinct</hi> Subſtance. But not from the Nature of <hi>Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> but from the Condition of the Subject (or Subſtance) in which it is, <hi>p.</hi> 15.</q> But I do not adviſe him, to explain too particularly the <hi>latter</hi> part of this Theorem; leſt <hi>the Realiſts</hi> ſhould turn it into Ridicule: 'tis a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obnoxious Propoſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>But when we come to conſider a Divine Eſſence; there can be <hi>no</hi> way of Diſtinction conceived in it, but by <hi>different Modes</hi> of Subſiſtence: or (what is the ſame) <hi>relative Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties</hi> in the ſame Divine Eſſence.</q> 
                  <hi>p.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:47056:31"/>In ſhort then; a Perſonality is only a particular <hi>Mode of Subſiſtence;</hi> and in the Divine Nature, Eſſence or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, 'tis moſt properly called <hi>a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Property.</hi> For inſtance: <hi>Paternity,</hi> or active Generation; <hi>Filiation,</hi> or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Generation, or begotten. So much for Madam <hi>PERSONALITY,</hi> now for Sir <hi>PERSON.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Notion of <hi>a Perſon,</hi> beſides the <hi>relative Property,</hi> comprizes the Divine Nature, together with it, <hi>p.</hi> 17.</q> And again, in his Book, at <hi>p.</hi> 119. <q>They agreed in the name <hi>Perſons,</hi> to expreſs their Meaning; which was: That there are three which have <hi>diſtinct Subſiſtences,</hi> and incommunicable <hi>Properties;</hi> but one and the <hi>ſame Divine Eſſence.</hi>
                  </q> You are to wot here, Sir; that by the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature,</hi> or <hi>Divine Eſſence,</hi> they mean the <hi>Deity</hi> it ſelf: that is, the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Subſtance</hi> with its ſeveral Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, Omniſcience, Omnipotence, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Juſtice and Goodneſs, and the reſt. Theſe (namely, the Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and Attributes) are called the Divine Nature, or Eſſence: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe herein are three <hi>relative Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> unbegotten, begotten, a proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; therefore each of theſe Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, when conſider'd with the Divine Eſſence and Attributes, is called <hi>a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here his Lordſhip is in bodily Fear, leſt this Explication of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or three Divine Perſons, ſhould be taken for <hi>Sabellianiſm;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be underſtood to be an entire yielding the Cauſe to the Unitarians. The Men from whom he fears this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, are <hi>the Realiſt Party;</hi> chiefly Dr. <hi>Cudworth;</hi> who ſaith of this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, that it is <q>the Philoſophy of <hi>Gotham;</hi> a nominal Trinity; and three ſuch Perſons as cannot be in Nature.</q> But ſee now, how dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly his Lordſhip comes off.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>It is not <hi>Sabellianiſm,</hi> to teach; that every Divine Perſon is <hi>a Perſon,</hi> as he hath the Divine Nature [Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence or Subſtance] belonging to him. For <hi>Sabellianiſm</hi> is the aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch <hi>relative Perſons,</hi> as have <hi>no Eſſence at all.</hi>
                  </q> p. 18, 19. So that if the Unitarians do but confeſs, that the <hi>three Properties</hi> (unbegotten, begotten, and proceeding) which are here called RELATIVE PERSONS, ſubſiſt (or <hi>are) in the Divine Eſſence,</hi> or Nature; they are not Sabellians, but Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks: they ſhould be Sabellians, if they ſaid, theſe Properties are <hi>in no Eſſence at all.</hi> But I think, they muſt be called Fools, as well as Sabellians; if they aſſerted <hi>relative Properties,</hi> or any Properties that were in no Eſſence. I perceive, his Lordſhip and we ſhall agree. But let us hear alſo how he goes on.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Farthermore it is to be noted, that there is a Communication of the Divine Eſſence, to each Divine Perſon, <hi>p.</hi> 19. For each Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon has <hi>an abſolute Nature, diſtinctly belonging to him; tho not a diſtinct abſolute Nature,</hi> p. 9. The eternal Father is, and ſubſiſts as a Father; by having a Son, and by communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating his Eſſence to another. The Relation between Father and Son, is founded on that <hi>eternal Act;</hi> by which the Father communicates his Divine Nature [Eſſence or Subſtance] to the Son.</q> 
                  <hi>p.</hi> 10. Laſtly, he adds, at <hi>p.</hi> 112. of his Book: <q>The Divine Perſons are diſtinct, as to <hi>perſonal Properties;</hi> [he means, the Father is <hi>unbegotten,</hi> the Son <hi>begotten,</hi> the Holy Spirit (neither begetting, nor
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:47056:31"/>
begotten, but) <hi>proceeding:</hi>] but they are not diſtinct, as to <hi>eſſential At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes:</hi> i. e. they have not diſtinct Omniſciencies, or Omnipotencies; they have but one Intellect, and one Energy.</q>
               </p>
               <p>You will ſay, Sir, this <hi>last</hi> is very ſound: that unbegotten, begotten, and proceeding, are <hi>diſtinct Properties,</hi> in the Divine Eſſence; and that there is but one Omniſcience, and Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, but one Omniſcient and Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, not three Omniſcients or three Omnipotents. But may there not be a Snake in the Graſs, in what is ſaid, that there is <hi>a Communication of the Divine Eſſence;</hi> and that the Father by an immanent and <hi>eternal Act,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates his Divine Nature to the Son? By no Means; for you ſhall hear from the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of <hi>the Schools;</hi> nay (for greater Surety and Caution) from Dean <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> and the <hi>Fathers;</hi> what that <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Act</hi> is, by which the Father <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates the Divine Eſſence</hi> to the Son, and both of them to the Spirit; as alſo what is meant by Father, Son, and Spirit: nothing I aſſure you, that any Unitarian ever queſtioned; but what we believe, as ſincerely, as Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Deans do. I pray, Sir, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve; we are inquiring what is the <hi>eternal Act,</hi> by which <hi>the Divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is communicated</hi> to the Divine Perſons: and what thoſe <hi>Perſons</hi> are? Let us firſt hear Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> who ſaith, he hath all the Fathers of his ſide.</p>
               <p>He affirms, 1. <q>It is eſſential, to an eternal Mind, <hi>to know</hi> it ſelf; and <hi>to love</hi> it ſelf. 2. <hi>Original Mind,</hi> or Wiſdom, or <hi>Knowledg</hi> of it ſelf, and <hi>Love</hi> of it ſelf, and of its own Image, are <hi>diſtinct Acts;</hi> and can never be <hi>one Act.</hi> 3. Theſe three Acts being ſo diſtinct, that they can never be the ſame, muſt be three <hi>ſubſtantial Acts</hi> in God; that is, the three (Divine ſubſiſting) Perſons. 4. Theſe then are the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> Characters of the diſtinct Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Trinity; <hi>the Father</hi> is <hi>Original Mind</hi> or Wiſdom. The <hi>Son</hi> is the <hi>reflex Knowledg</hi> of himſelf, [namely, of Original Mind] or the <hi>perfect Image</hi> of his own Wiſdom: that is, <hi>of the Wiſdom of Original Mind.</hi> The <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> is that <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love,</hi> which Father and Son have for each other.—All Men who know <hi>the Fathers,</hi> know that <hi>this is their conſtant Language.</hi>
                  </q> Vindic. of the Trin. <hi>p.</hi> 130. To make this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony the more conſiderable, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor intimates in the laſt Paragraph but one of his Preface; that in writing this Book, he muſt thankfully own, he was divinely aſſiſted. If you will not take the Word of Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> and <hi>the conſtant Language</hi> of the <hi>Fathers;</hi> then hear the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> with all <hi>the School-Divines,</hi> and the <hi>univerſal Church.</hi> 
                  <q>They conceived, that the <hi>primary Act</hi> of the Divine Eſſence, is its <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> this they thought might be called <hi>the Son,</hi> as being the Generation of <hi>eternal Mind.</hi> From this Fountain-Principle, <hi>eternal Mind,</hi> and the inward WORD, or <hi>Logos,</hi> or <hi>Wiſdom; a Love</hi> did iſſue forth, which was to be the Soul of the Creation, and more particularly of the Church.—This was reſted on, and became <hi>the univerſally-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Explication</hi> of the Trinity; and was dreſſed up by the Schools with a great deal of dark Nicety.</q> 
                  <hi>Diſcourſe to Clergy,</hi> p. 99.</p>
               <p>Now, Sir, lay your hand on your Heart; and anſwer, like a true Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:47056:32"/>
Do you your ſelf, or know you any of the Denomination, that queſtion this Trinity; the Trinity, our very Oppoſers ſay, of the <hi>Schools,</hi> the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and the <hi>univerſal Church.</hi> Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, 1. One Divine Nature, Eſſence, or Subſtance; with one only Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and Omnipotence: and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, with one only Intellect, and Power of Action. 2. <hi>Three Properties,</hi> called (by the Bp. of <hi>Worceſter) RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATIVE PERSONS,</hi> viz. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begotten</hi> eternal Mind, <hi>Reflex</hi> or begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Knowledg or Wiſdom, and <hi>Divine Love</hi> proceeding from both. This, from themſelves, is what they mean by <hi>Perſons,</hi> in the Trinity; and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of the Divine Nature without Diviſion or Separation, by immanent and <hi>Eternal Acts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I confeſs, I fear much; that were Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> alive, that great Divine and Philoſopher, would either reaſon, or laugh us out of this Gibberiſh: he would conſtrain us, to return to the Language of Scripture, about theſe Matters. And it is moſt true, that theſe <hi>Terms</hi> are not to be found, either in Holy Scripture; or in the Creeds, or (received) General Councils, of the Catholick Church. They were firſt advanced by ſome particular Fathers, eſpecially St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his 15 Books <hi>de Trinitate;</hi> were taken up (from them) by the Divines of <hi>the Schools,</hi> that is, of the middle Ages; and have been confirmed by the conſtant Uſe of the <hi>Moderns,</hi> or Divines of the two laſt Ages. We declare openly, <hi>and therein conſiſts our whole Hereſy,</hi> that we like 'em not; not only as they are <hi>unſcriptural,</hi> which (in matter of Faith) is a moſt juſt Exception for divers very weighty Reaſons; but becauſe by their dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Ambiguity, they give occaſion to Hereſy; not only among the People, but even among Learned Men. Theſe are the Terms that have occaſioned the Hereſy of <hi>the Realiſts,</hi> or Tritheiſts; maintained at this time, by divers Learned Men among us. Yet for Peace ſake, we admit the Terms; interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the known Senſe of the Church: which Senſe, we acknowledg, the Bps. of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and <hi>Sarum,</hi> Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> and the <hi>Oxford-Heads,</hi> have (as we have ſeen already) rightly underſtood, and (eſpecially Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> in his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Letters, under the Name of a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marine Divine) dextrouſly declared. I may paſs, I think, to the laſt thing to be conſidered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <head>The Conciliation of Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> and Dean <hi>Sherlock.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DR. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> in his Books againſt the Unitarians, had taken this for his Ground and Foundation; that the three Divine Perſons are three eternal infinite Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, each of them <hi>a</hi> God: but the three Gods are made up again into one God, by being <hi>internally conſcious</hi> to one anothers Thoughts, and Operations.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> in two (Engliſh) Books, by him written, and in three Latin Letters, excepts againſt this Explication of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; as falſe, heretical, and directly intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing three Gods. He ſaith, as <hi>we</hi> do; that the Deity is one numerical individual Nature, Subſtance, Mind, Spirit; with one only Underſtanding, Will, and Energy. As to the Divine Perſons, they are the one individual Nature or Eſſence of God, with <hi>three Relative Properties:</hi> each Property conſider'd with the Divine Eſſence, is called <hi>a Perſon.</hi> What theſe Properties and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are, hath been ſaid already.</p>
               <p>The Bp. of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> ſeeing in what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger an old Friend is, undertakes; firſt, to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:47056:32"/>
excuſe Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> from the Imputation of Hereſy: and then, to reconcile him to Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> and the Nominals. He inlarges himſelf, on theſe three Points.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Explication, not only will do no manner of Service, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards clearing the Difficulties in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Trinity; but that <q>it intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces <hi>a ſpecifick</hi> Divine Nature: which is inconſiſtent with the Divine Perfections.</q> 
                  <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>He adds, at <hi>p.</hi> 30. <q>'Tis impoſſible to conceive, that the ſame individual Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſhould be in three Perſons; <hi>as the Catholick Church teaches:</hi> if thoſe Perſons have peculiar Subſtances, of their own; <hi>as Dr.</hi> Sherlock <hi>affirms and contends.</hi>
                  </q> Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately he cites an excellent Reaſoning of <hi>Maimonides,</hi> by which to know, when Men affirm three Gods; and concludes, that Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Explication differs not from what <hi>Maimonides</hi> proves to be an introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing more Gods, <hi>p.</hi> 30. He forbears not to own, at <hi>p.</hi> 31. that he thinks it <q>impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reconcile (Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s) three in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual Eſſences or Subſtances, with <hi>(the Catholick Churches) one</hi> individual Divine Eſſence: and that the former looks too like <hi>aſſerting three Gods, and yet but one.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But now, how to ſave his Friend, from <hi>the ſecular Arm?</hi> He ſays, in ſhort; Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> holds <hi>the Article</hi> of the Trinity, and only miſtakes in <hi>the Explication</hi> of it: but it is not Hereſy, <hi>he ſaith,</hi> when a Man aſſents to a <hi>Fundamental Article;</hi> and only miſtakes in the Explication, Interpretation, or Senſe of it. <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 22, 23.</p>
               <p>But I fear, our Brother <hi>S—th.</hi> is too quick-ſighted, to let this paſs; he will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly ſay: that an Article, whether fundamental or not fundamental, and the Explication or Senſe of ſuch Article, are the very ſame thing; and that an Article <hi>falſly interpreted</hi> or explained, is by no means the Article, but a Contradiction to the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. He will certainly laugh out, that his Antagoniſts can be no way excuſed from He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy; but by giving up, at once, the whole Doctrine of the Catholick Church. For the Doctrine of the Church, is moſt certainly yielded up, if once it be granted; that a Man believes her Articles, while he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds or takes them in a wrong Senſe of them. At this rate, will he ſay, <hi>Philopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Joachim,</hi> and <hi>Gentilis,</hi> were good Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks: for what makes a Catholick, is not holding the Article in the <hi>true</hi> Meaning of it; but in any Meaning, in a falſe Meaning, or a contrary Meaning. I ſhall leave Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> to argue it out with the Bp. and paſs to the next.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He alledges, laſt of all; that tho Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> affirms three individual Eſſences, three eternal Minds, three infinite Spirits; <hi>which is Hereſy:</hi> yet he alſo ſays, <q>the Father communicated his Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or Eſſence, <hi>wholly and intirely,</hi> to the Son and Spirit, without Diviſion or Separation; <hi>which is Orthodoxy.</hi>
                  </q> We ought therefore to ſay, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> has <hi>only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted himſelf,</hi> but is not <hi>a Heretick:</hi> He holds what indeed is Hereſy, <hi>three</hi> Subſtances, <hi>three</hi> Minds, and <hi>three</hi> Spirits; but he holds alſo the Truth, <hi>one</hi> individual Subſtance, <hi>one</hi> Deity. His Lordſhip touches upon this, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times; as well in his Book, as in his Preface: nay he is ſo ſatisfied with it, that at <hi>p.</hi> 107. he cannot (he ſaith) now ſee; what is the difference, between Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> and his <hi>Nominals,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> and the <hi>Realiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſhort of this Defence, is; that if one part of <hi>a Contradiction</hi> is true and orthodox, the other falſe and heretical: the Perſon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming it, ſhall be denominated, not from his <hi>Hereſy;</hi> but from <hi>the orthodox Part</hi> of his Contradiction. For my part, I very readily agree, to this (charitable) way, of bringing off the Dr. but then, let the Charity be truly Catholick; let us extend it to others, as well as to him; and elſe it is not <hi>Charity,</hi> but <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality.</hi> A Motley of Hereſy and Orthodoxy, his Lordſhip ſays, is to be named a <hi>parte po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiori; from the ſound part,</hi> without reckning at all of the <hi>unſound:</hi> but then, I pray, let <hi>Philoponus, Joachim,</hi> and <hi>Gentilis,</hi> be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſame Law. For they ſaid, as the Doctor does; <hi>three</hi> infinite Subſtances, <hi>three</hi> eternal Minds and Spirits: and they aſſerted alſo, as he does, <hi>one Deity,</hi> one Eſſence, and <hi>one Subſtance,</hi> by the <hi>mutual Inexiſtence</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:47056:33"/>
of the Perſons; <hi>the Subordination</hi> of the ſecond, and third, to the firſt; and <hi>the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence</hi> of all of them to the Making and Government of the World; while Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi> reſolves the whole Unity of the Deity, and of the Divine Subſtance, into <hi>only the mutual Conſciouſneſs</hi> of the three <hi>Perſonal Gods.</hi> And this, not only in all his former Books; but in his laſt Pamphlet, or <hi>the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between Nominal and Real Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans examined, in Anſwer to the Diſintereſted:</hi> A Book ſo monſtrouſly erroneous, that if it eſcapes all other hands; I think verily his Second againſt the Jeſuit <hi>Sabrand,</hi> would take up Arms againſt him; the Foot-boy would detect, and expoſe, his groſs Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodoxies.</p>
               <p>We have heard his Lordſhip's way of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Controverſies, concerning the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinity; that is to ſay, among Friends, Perſons of the ſame Church and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: namely, if they will but ſay, what all have always ſaid, even <hi>Arius, Philoponus,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> and <hi>Socinus;</hi> that there is but <hi>one</hi> Deity, and <hi>one</hi> Divine Subſtance: let 'em <hi>contradict this,</hi> as much as they will, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they do not (abſolutely, and in Terms) <hi>renounce it;</hi> they ſhall be Catholicks. Dr. <hi>Pain,</hi> in his Letter to my Lord the Bp. of <hi>R.</hi> has much the ſame Salvo. For af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had ſaid (<hi>Poſtſcr. p.</hi> 25.) that God or the Trinity is an Original <hi>Eternal Mind;</hi> with an Eternal <hi>Logos (Wiſdom)</hi> or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial <hi>Ennoia</hi> or <hi>Knowledg;</hi> and an Eternal Divine Spirit proceeding from both: He concludes (<hi>p.</hi> 26.) that <q>whoſoever believes this Trinity, whether with or without Explications, whether with right or with wrong Explications; he is undoubtedly Orthodox.</q> And at <hi>p.</hi> 11. he commends the <hi>wiſe</hi> Biſhops of the Roman Church; who, tho they have Plenitude of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Authority, ſuffer the Jeſuits and other Learned Men, to vent their <hi>different</hi> Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in theſe high Queſtions: <q>without interpoſing, much leſs cenſuring either Party; ſo long as <hi>they ſubſcribe,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to <hi>the general Doctrine</hi> of the Church.</q> They allow their Writers to ſay, there are <hi>three Gods, in a Perſonal Senſe;</hi> or <hi>three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Gods:</hi> and to profeſs, <hi>three Eternals,</hi> and <hi>three Omnipotents.</hi> But then he ſaith, this Favour is extended, only to Friends, to one another; to Sons of the Church: for if Men of another Communion, make the leaſt Trip in explaining what is above all Explication, nay is incomprehenſible and unintelligible; immediately they ſhall be charged with Blaſphemy, and Atheiſm. He (not obſcurely) intimates; that the like Chriſtian Charity, Love, and good Will, (ſo he ſpeaks <hi>p.</hi> 13.) ſhould be uſed among Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, eſpecially among Clergy-men, who are of the ſame <hi>Faith.</hi> If our Friend <hi>S—th</hi> accords to this, ſo will we: for we are of the ſame <hi>Faith</hi> with the Engliſh Church, for the Church of <hi>England</hi> never believed or taught <hi>three</hi> Eternal All-perfect <hi>Minds</hi> and <hi>Spirits;</hi> the denial of which, is the only Hereſy of which we are guilty: we ſubmit to all other Explications of the Trinity, tho (as we have ſaid) we utterly diſlike ſome Words and Ways of expreſſing them.</p>
               <p>His Lordſhip has alſo reprinted his Book, concerning <hi>the Satisfaction;</hi> with a new <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face,</hi> to it. What he hath affirmed there, concerning that Point; more than has been granted, and aſſented to, in theſe (and 20 more publick) Papers; is not the Doctrine, either of the Catholick Church, or of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> 'tis only the (unautho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed) Opinion and Fancy, of particular Writers; who are as various about thoſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as they are about moſt others.</p>
               <p>My Concluſion, <hi>Sir;</hi> ſeeing we have been ſo roughly, as well as unjuſtly, treated by theſe Antagoniſts; ſhall be only to your ſelf: That I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>(With much Reſpect, and Affection) <hi>Yours.</hi>
                  </signed> 
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>March</hi> 10. 1696.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
